<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</title>
    <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171</link>
    <description>source: &lt;https://git.activitypub.dev/ActivityPubDev/Fediverse-Enhancement-Proposals/src/branch/main/feps/fep-a4ed.md&gt;

-----

authors: @pukkamustard
status: FINAL
dateReceived: 2020-10-16
dateFinalized: 2021-01-18

# FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process


## Summary

A Fediverse Enhancement Proposal (FEP) is a document that provides information to the Fediverse community. The goal of a FEP is to improve interoperability and well-being of diverse services, applications and communities that form the Fediverse.

This document describes the scope, format and process of publishing Fediverse Enhancement Proposals.


## Scope and Objectives

A Fediverse Enhancement Proposal (FEP) should be a concise and focused documentation of a specific topic that is of interest to the Fediverse community.

A proposal should always have the intention of improving the interoperability and well-being of diverse services, applications and community of the Fediverse.

The Fediverse includes applications, services and communities using the ActivityPub protocol and other protocols that foster decentralized and diverse social media and culture.

Proposals may include descriptions of technical protocols and mechanism, documentation of experimental work or current best practices.

Proposals are not limited to technical topics and may focus on social and cultural aspects.

Proposals may be entertaining and humorous (unlike this proposal).


## Language, Document Structure and Format

All Fediverse Enhancement Proposals must be written in English, be properly formatted as CommonMark [CommonMark] and be reasonably grammatical.

Authors should use inclusive language and examples and refrain from using oppressive terminology [Internet-Draft-terminology].

### Proposal Title and Identifier

Every Fediverse Enhancement Proposals must have a descriptive title.

An identifier is computed from the proposal title as the first 7 digits of the sha256 hash (in hex). The identifier can be computed from the title with standard Unix tools:

```
$ echo -n &quot;The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process&quot; | sha256sum | cut -c-4
a4ed
```

By using the hash of the title as identifier we reduce the burden on editors to assign unique ids. This require proposal titles to be unique.

### Metadata

Proposal metadata is placed at the top of the document as key-value pairs between opening and closing ~---~.

Following metadata key-value pairs may be placed at the top of a proposal:

- `authors`: A comma separated list of authors of the proposal.
- `status`: Indicates the proposal status. Can be either `DRAFT`, `WITHDRAWN` or `FINAL`.
- `dateReceived`: Date of when the proposal was added to the repository (when status is set to `DRAFT`).
- `dateWithdrawn`: Date of when the proposal status was set to `WITHDRAWN` (only for proposals with status `WITHDRAWN`).
- `dateFinalized`: Date of when the proposal status was set to `FINAL` (only for proposals with status `FINAL`).
- `relatedFeps`: A comma separated list of related FEPs (e.g. `FEP-a4ed, FEP-141a, FEP-686f`).

Future FEPs may specify additional metadata fields.

### Required Sections

Every FEP should include at least following sections:

- Summary: A short (no more than 200 words) summary of the proposal.
- Copyright: Indicating that the proposal has been placed in the public domain.

Following sections may be included in a proposal:

- History: An overview of previous related efforts and how they relate to the proposal.
- Implementations: If applicable an overview of services or applications that implement the proposal at time of submission.
- References: A list of documents and resources referenced by the proposal.

### Copyright

Fediverse Enhancement Proposals must be placed in the public domain by the authors with a CC0 1.0 Universal (CC0 1.0) Public Domain Dedication.


## The Fediverse Enhancement Proposals Process

```
                                     +-------+
                           +-------&gt; | FINAL | 
                           |         +-------+
         +-------+         |
--------&gt;| DRAFT | --------+
         +-------+         |
             ^             |         +-----------+
             |             +-------&gt; | WITHDRAWN |
             |                       +-----------+
             |                             |
             +-----------------------------+
```

1. A Fediverse Enhancement Proposal can be submitted by individuals or groups of individuals (authors). See the `SUBMISSION.md` file for a list of accepted submission methods.
2. Within seven days one of the editors will read and respond to the proposal. The editor checks if the proposal conforms to the required structure and fits the scope and objective of the FEPs. The editor may request the authors to clarify, justify, or withdraw the proposal. Such a request must not reflect the personal bias of an editor. Rather, it will be made strictly to maintain a high quality of submissions. The editors reserve the right to reject a submission when a proposal amounts to blatant misuse of the process. The authors may seek feedback from the wider community if the submitted proposal is rejected or clarifications are requested.
3. If a FEP editor approves a submission it receives the status `DRAFT` and is added to the repository.
4. While a proposal has the status `DRAFT`:
   - Authors are responsible for initiating community discussion and collecting feedback.
   - Authors may submit updates to the proposal which will be checked in to the repository by an editor.
   - Authors may withdraw the submission upon which an editor will set the status of the submission to `WITHDRAWN`.
5. After at least 60 days the authors may request the proposal to be finalized. This is done by requesting final comments on the proposal.
   - If there are no community objections within 14 days and the authors can show that they have initiated sufficient awareness and discussion of the proposal, an editor will set the status of the submission to `FINAL`.
6. If after 120 days the authors have not requested the proposal to be finalized or there is no community consensus, an editor will set the status of the submission to `WITHDRAWN`.
7. A proposal with status `FINAL` can not be changed or updated.
8. A proposal with status `WITHDRAWN` remains in the repository and can be resubmitted.

### Editors

A list of editors is maintained in the `EDITORS.md` file at the root of the FEP repository.

### Submission Methods

A list of methods in which a proposal may be submitted is maintained in the `SUBMISSION.md` file at the root of the FEP repository.

## History

The process and format described in this proposal is influenced by other community driven documentation efforts such as the BitTorrent Enhancement Proposal Process [BEP-1], Scheme Request for Implementation [SRFI] and the IETF RFC Series [RFC-8729].


## References

- [SRFI] Dave Mason, [Scheme Request For Implementation - Process](https://srfi.schemers.org/srfi-process.html)
- [BEP-1] David Harrison, [The BitTorrent Enhancement Proposal Process](http://bittorrent.org/beps/bep_0001.html), 2008
- [RFC-8729] Housley, R., Ed., and L. Daigle, Ed., [The RFC Series and RFC Editor](https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8729), 2020
- [CommonMark] John MacFarlane, [CommonMark Spec](https://spec.commonmark.org/0.29/) Version 0.29, 2019
- [Internet-Draft-terminology] Mallory Knodel, [Terminology, Power and Oppressive Language](https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-knodel-terminology)


## Copyright

CC0 1.0 Universal (CC0 1.0) Public Domain Dedication 

To the extent possible under law, the authors of this Fediverse Enhancement Proposal have waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this work.</description>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 25 Apr 2021 05:55:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <category>Fediverse Enhancement Proposals</category>
    <atom:link href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
        <title>FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <h2>
<a name="fep-process-1" class="anchor" href="#fep-process-1"></a>FEP process</h2>
<p>Yes, that’s true, but in that case you’d have metadata on the other FEP which make it effectively not-FINAL-anymore. Like you have “this version” and “latest version”. I am assuming that any significant update must undergo the entire review process. Once the update becomes FINAL, then a warning on the old one must be shown “This is not the latest FINAL version” or something, similar to what you see at W3C.</p>
<p>If an update is underway in the process, does it have the same title + ID? That might be confusing. Alternatively an update could be part of the same document, i.e. it contains all versions, but that’d be confusing too.</p>
<p>Note that it gets complicated pretty quick. A W3C spec is designed to be something self-contained, whereas a FEP is an enchancement and not necessarily be ‘atomic’ i.e. it may need to be adapted to comply with other FEP’s as they are finalized. There are relationships.</p>
<p>Talking W3C… we may reuse the exact same mechanism. I figure it takes care of most of this. We want the FEP’s to be practical, least ceremonial, but they should also be useful and a sprawl of FEP’s - once the process gets traction - may go against that.</p>
<h2>
<a name="compliance-2" class="anchor" href="#compliance-2"></a>Compliance</h2>
<p>In addition to the FEP process itself arises the question: How to find out what FEP’s an implementation complies to?</p>
<p>I suggest that - for now - this should be in the FEDERATION.md document, proposed last year by <a class="mention" href="/u/darius">@darius</a> in <a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/documenting-federation-behavior-in-a-semi-standard-way/453" class="inline-onebox">Documenting federation behavior in a semi-standard way?</a> proposed the FEDERATION.md convention, and discussed in <a href="https://www.w3.org/2020/02/08-social-minutes.html">SocialCG 2020-02-08</a>.</p>
<p>How this works should be documented in the FEP process too, imho.</p>
<hr>
<p>Note, I have proposed an extension to FEDERATION.md and will continue discussion in: <a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/improvement-to-federation-md-convention-murmurations/1573" class="inline-onebox">Improvement to FEDERATION.md convention: Murmurations</a></p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/33">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/33</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Apr 2021 05:55:36 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1171-33</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171.rss">FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[cjs]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I wonder if we need a new state, an update mechanism, or just RFC-style later-ones-just-supercede.</p>
<p>It is possible an older item isn’t 100% superceded, just parts of it, so I am hesitant to add a new state – this would imply a whole thing is obsolete.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/32">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/32</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 24 Apr 2021 11:45:22 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1171-32</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171.rss">FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <h1>
<a name="feedback-after-the-fep-became-final-starts-here-1" class="anchor" href="#feedback-after-the-fep-became-final-starts-here-1"></a>Feedback AFTER the FEP became FINAL starts here …</h1>
<hr>
<p>This FEP has become <code>FINAL</code> and…</p>
<blockquote>
<p>A proposal with status <code>FINAL</code> can not be changed or updated.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Now suppose I would like to change it. What’s the procedure? Should one write another FEP that suppercedes the current one if it becomes FINAL. If so, how do we document that so it is clear to everyone? Or should FEP’s be Versioned instead?</p>
<p>The change I am thinking about is following:</p>
<ul>
<li>While in <code>DRAFT</code> mode there should not be a Timer that is ticking (the 60 day period). This is the stage where you prepare your proposal before it is ready for the world.</li>
<li>Add an additional workflow step <code>PROPOSED</code> where the 60-day review period starts.</li>
</ul>
<p>The workflow then looks as follows:</p>
<pre><code class="lang-auto">                                                          +-------+
                                                +-------&gt; | FINAL | 
                                                |         +-------+
         +-------+          +----------+        |
--------&gt;| DRAFT | --------&gt;| PROPOSED |--------+
         +-------+          +----------+        |
             ^                                  |         +-----------+
             |                                  +-------&gt; | WITHDRAWN |
             |                                            +-----------+
             |                                                  |
             +--------------------------------------------------+
</code></pre>
<p>Why extend?</p>
<ul>
<li>So all drafts being prepared are in one place.</li>
<li>So you can work with others to hone it together before actually proposing.</li>
</ul>
<p>For the case where a new FEP supercedes another this may be reflected in its state, plus a reference to the superceding FEP is added to the old one. Maybe a better state name is in order e.g. <code>ARCHIVED</code> or even (<em>maybe</em>) <code>DEPRECATED</code> in some cases…</p>
<pre><code class="lang-auto">                                                          +-------+                +------------+
                                                +-------&gt; | FINAL |--[other-FEP]--&gt;| SUPERCEDED |
                                                |         +-------+                +------------+
         +-------+          +----------+        |
--------&gt;| DRAFT | --------&gt;| PROPOSED |--------+
         +-------+          +----------+        |
             ^                                  |         +-----------+
             |                                  +-------&gt; | WITHDRAWN |
             |                                            +-----------+
             |                                                  |
             +--------------------------------------------------+
</code></pre>
<p>CC <a class="mention" href="/u/pukkamustard">@pukkamustard</a> <a class="mention" href="/u/cjs">@cjs</a></p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/31">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/31</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 13 Mar 2021 07:23:04 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1171-31</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171.rss">FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[pukkamustard]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Claire via SocialHub <a href="mailto:noreply@socialhub.activitypub.rocks">noreply@socialhub.activitypub.rocks</a> writes:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Sorry for being a bit late to the party. My gripes with the<br>
process so far were:</p>
<ul>
<li>there no being clear way to submit the FEP, but that has been<br>
fixed</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p><img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/images/emoji/twitter/+1.png?v=9" title=":+1:" class="emoji only-emoji" alt=":+1:"></p>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>the FEP IDs changing, but I expect this won’t change again</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>Yes, sorry about that. FEP-8fcf and FEP-f1d5 were a bit special as<br>
they were submitted before the process itself was finalized. This<br>
should not happen again.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The current document looks good, although I wonder if it should<br>
provide guidance and venues for authors to get discussion and<br>
feedback on their proposals.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is an important point that has been brought up previously<br>
(see thread above).</p>
<p>I’m very reluctant to give any concrete recommendations or<br>
requirements on venues for discussing proposal. My hope is that<br>
such venues will develop naturally. When these are established it<br>
might make sense to document these venues. This can be done in an<br>
additional FEP. In best case these would be venues that fit with<br>
the spirit of the Fediverse and are federated/decentralized (as<br>
opposed to this highly centralized forum).</p>
<blockquote>
<p>One very minor typo: BitTorrent Enhancment Proposal Process →<br>
BitTorrent Enhancement Proposal Process</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Thanks for the catch. Fixed with<br>
</p><aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/original/1X/e96071ab96a5e76fc14e8098123273b2bc357025.png" class="site-icon" width="180" height="180">
      <a href="https://git.activitypub.dev/ActivityPubDev/Fediverse-Enhancement-Proposals/pulls/15" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Gitea: Git with a cup of tea</a>
  </header>
  <article class="onebox-body">
    <img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/original/1X/d829e756063e30af848f047504a4c3f847b44536.png" class="thumbnail onebox-avatar" width="290" height="290">

<h3><a href="https://git.activitypub.dev/ActivityPubDev/Fediverse-Enhancement-Proposals/pulls/15" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">FEP-a4ed: Fix typo</a></h3>

<p>Fixes typo in FEP-a4ed (#10).

See https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/29</p>


  </article>
  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>
  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/30">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/30</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2021 09:57:38 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1171-30</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171.rss">FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[Claire]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Sorry for being a bit late to the party. My gripes with the process so far were:</p>
<ul>
<li>there no being clear way to submit the FEP, but that has been fixed</li>
<li>the FEP IDs changing, but I expect this won’t change again</li>
</ul>
<p>The current document looks good, although I wonder if it should provide guidance and venues for authors to get discussion and feedback on their proposals.</p>
<p>One very minor typo: BitTorrent Enhancment Proposal Process → BitTorrent Enhancement Proposal Process</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/29">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/29</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jan 2021 22:47:52 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1171-29</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171.rss">FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[rhiaro]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I also think the FEP process could be a good way to incubate extensions to AS2, which can then be adopted through a proposal to the CG and added to the AS2 namespace. Since the CG had not manage to come up with a process for this so far, we can talk about adopting the FEP for it at some point.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/28">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/28</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jan 2021 16:51:22 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1171-28</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171.rss">FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[rhiaro]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p><a class="mention" href="/u/pukkamustard">@pukkamustard</a> I finally read FEP-a4ed and it looks great. A really solid basis for coherent communication in the community.</p>
<p>There’s scope for publishing FINAL FEPs as Social Incubator <a href="https://www.w3.org/community/reports/" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">CG Reports</a> if there’s interest from the community in producing documents with the w3c header on, under <a href="http://w3.org" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">w3.org</a>. As well as being preserved at a persistent URL, they have the advantage of being easily submitable to Working Groups as input documents for formal standardisation in future.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/27">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/27</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jan 2021 14:21:05 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1171-27</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171.rss">FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[pukkamustard]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I kindly request final comments on “FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process”.</p>
<p>Notable changes since the proposal has been received:</p>
<ul>
<li>Reduce number of characters in identifier to 4. More readable and good enough.</li>
<li>Specify the <code>EDITORS.md</code> and <code>SUBMISSION.md</code> files.</li>
<li>Increase time before proposal is auto-withdrawn to 120 days.</li>
<li>Update some references.</li>
</ul>
<p>See also the <a href="https://git.activitypub.dev/ActivityPubDev/Fediverse-Enhancement-Proposals/issues/10" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">tracking issue</a>.</p>
<p>I have <a href="https://git.activitypub.dev/ActivityPubDev/Fediverse-Enhancement-Proposals/pulls/14" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">requested finalization</a> in 14 days. If there are no objections, the proposal will become final on the 18th of January.</p>
<p>Thanks!</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/26">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/26</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 15:43:56 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1171-26</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171.rss">FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>A post was merged into an existing topic: <a href="/t/business-domains-ld-vocabulary-extensions-and-namespaces/1255/2">Business domains, LD vocabulary extensions and namespaces</a></p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/25">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/25</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 10:40:45 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1171-25</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171.rss">FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="pukkamustard" data-post="22" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/pukkamustard/40/111_2.png" class="avatar"> pukkamustard:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Would you want to submit a FEP addressing this?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>You mean a FEP to update the FEP FEP <img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/images/emoji/twitter/wink.png?v=9" title=":wink:" class="emoji" alt=":wink:"></p>
<p>I may pick this up at a later date. There’s a good basis now, with which we can run for the moment. See what makes sense or not later on.</p>
<hr>
<p>Something else. Yesterday some interesting background on FEP-like processes:</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/original/1X/3a89fe65b92227595f9774b75a6372d099ac3043.png" class="site-icon" width="300" height="300">
      <a href="https://candost.blog/how-to-stop-endless-discussions/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="07:20AM - 31 December 2020">Candost Dagdeviren – 31 Dec 20</a>
  </header>
  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:690/178;"><img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/optimized/1X/a2c922ac36324d74b5f616cc26cd87edf42d7530_2_690x178.jpeg" class="thumbnail" width="690" height="178" srcset="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/optimized/1X/a2c922ac36324d74b5f616cc26cd87edf42d7530_2_690x178.jpeg, https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/optimized/1X/a2c922ac36324d74b5f616cc26cd87edf42d7530_2_1035x267.jpeg 1.5x, https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/optimized/1X/a2c922ac36324d74b5f616cc26cd87edf42d7530_2_1380x356.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/optimized/1X/a2c922ac36324d74b5f616cc26cd87edf42d7530_2_10x10.png"></div>

<h3><a href="https://candost.blog/how-to-stop-endless-discussions/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">How to Stop Endless Discussions</a></h3>

<p>When we find ourselves in endless debates where everyone defends their idea, we don't know how to handle the situation.</p>


  </article>
  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>
  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>And a <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=25622149">HN discussion</a> about the article (80+ comments).</p>
<p>NABC model from Stanford was mentioned, which stands for Need, Approach, Benefit, Competitors. Both Need and Competitors are most interesting. Separatng <strong>Need</strong> from Approach is great for the understanding of the author, while <strong>Competitors</strong> “is the part the authors have to consider competitors of their proposal.”. It has the effect of:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>“Thinking about an alternative solution instead of their suggestion requires people to focus on the problem instead of blindly loving and defending their solutions.”</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Overall “The process seeks a <strong>consent-based</strong> environment, <strong>not a consensus-based</strong> one [AND] brings <strong>accountability</strong> , as well”</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/24">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/24</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 09:59:10 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1171-24</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171.rss">FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[pukkamustard]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote group-smithereen" data-username="grishka" data-post="21" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/grishka/40/196_2.png" class="avatar"> grishka:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>If I’m proposing a technical thing, is it preferable for it to have been implemented already?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I think it is nice to have at least one working implementation (good for figuring out all the things one forgets), but there is no strict requirement.</p>
<aside class="quote group-smithereen" data-username="grishka" data-post="21" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/grishka/40/196_2.png" class="avatar"> grishka:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>If I’m adding fields to an ActivityPub object, and I expect them to be used widely in the future, which namespace should I be using? My own, i.e. <code>http://smithereen.software/ns#</code> ? ActivityStreams? Something else?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Excellent question.</p>
<p>FEPs do not have any control of what should be added to ActivityStreams. Maybe it might make sense to add a FEP namespace (e.g. <code>https://activitypub.dev/fep/ns#</code>) where things can be added but in the mean time I think it is better to use your own.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/23">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/23</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 08:29:11 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1171-23</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171.rss">FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[pukkamustard]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="aschrijver" data-post="19" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/aschrijver/40/278_2.png" class="avatar"> aschrijver:</div>
<blockquote>
<p><a class="mention" href="/u/cjs">@cjs</a> yes, that would be easiest maintenance-wise, and I think that this <em>should</em> be included in the FEP template, imho.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I am reluctant to add such a requirement. I do not think that discussion should be referenced from the FEP itself. The FEP by itself should be enough to understand the matter.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="aschrijver" data-post="19" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/aschrijver/40/278_2.png" class="avatar"> aschrijver:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Right now the issue tracker in the FEP repo is unused. The workflow might be that - as soon as an open issue pops up in discussion - someone (e.g. the author) creates a FEP-related issue, with an appropriate label, and maybe a user assignment indicating who is responsible for dealing with it. So for example:</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I think that is a good idea.</p>
<p>I have created tracking issues for the 3 <code>DRAFT</code> FEPs:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://git.activitypub.dev/ActivityPubDev/Fediverse-Enhancement-Proposals/issues/10" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://git.activitypub.dev/ActivityPubDev/Fediverse-Enhancement-Proposals/issues/10</a></li>
<li><a href="https://git.activitypub.dev/ActivityPubDev/Fediverse-Enhancement-Proposals/issues/11" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://git.activitypub.dev/ActivityPubDev/Fediverse-Enhancement-Proposals/issues/11</a></li>
<li><a href="https://git.activitypub.dev/ActivityPubDev/Fediverse-Enhancement-Proposals/issues/12" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://git.activitypub.dev/ActivityPubDev/Fediverse-Enhancement-Proposals/issues/12</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Pull request <a href="https://git.activitypub.dev/ActivityPubDev/Fediverse-Enhancement-Proposals/pulls/13" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">#13</a> includes a GitTea template for these tracking issues.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="aschrijver" data-post="13" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/aschrijver/40/278_2.png" class="avatar"> aschrijver:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Oh, and imho the README should have a list or table of FEP’s in the repo, with link + brief description + status.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Also added as interim solution in <a href="https://git.activitypub.dev/ActivityPubDev/Fediverse-Enhancement-Proposals/pulls/13" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">#13</a>.</p>
<p>I have also increased the time before a FEP automatically goes from <code>DRAFT</code> to <code>WITHDRAWN</code> from 90 days to 120 days. This is mostly because I have been away and almost missed the date…Generally a bit more time can not harm.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="aschrijver" data-post="20" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/aschrijver/40/278_2.png" class="avatar"> aschrijver:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I guess in my <a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/17">most recent comments</a> above, it indicates there’s already a need for this, but in a slightly more specific and practical manner (if y’all agree with that feedback, that is).</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Would you want to submit a FEP addressing this?</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/22">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/22</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 08:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1171-22</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171.rss">FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[grishka]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I have a couple of questions about the FEP process.</p>
<ul>
<li>If I’m proposing a technical thing, is it preferable for it to have been implemented already?</li>
<li>If I’m adding fields to an ActivityPub object, and I expect them to be used widely in the future, which namespace should I be using? My own, i.e. <code>http://smithereen.software/ns#</code>? ActivityStreams? Something else?</li>
</ul>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/21">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/21</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 25 Dec 2020 17:35:47 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1171-21</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171.rss">FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group quote-modified" data-username="pukkamustard" data-post="15" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/pukkamustard/40/111_2.png" class="avatar"> pukkamustard:</div>
<blockquote>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="aschrijver" data-post="13" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/aschrijver/40/278_2.png" class="avatar"> aschrijver:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Oh, and imho the README should have a list or table of FEP’s in the repo, with link + brief description + status.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>This is something that can be very well be done by a static-site generator (or similar) and I am a bit reluctant to add it, as it does add considerable maintenance burden.</p>
<p>Ok, if we concentrate on doing this in a nice presentation of FEPs (e.g. <code>library.activitypub.dev</code> ) and revisit index in README after?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Sure, this would work. There should be an easy navigation from the static site to the markdown doc to PR to in the repo then.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group quote-modified" data-username="pukkamustard" data-post="15" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/pukkamustard/40/111_2.png" class="avatar"> pukkamustard:</div>
<blockquote>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="aschrijver" data-post="13" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/aschrijver/40/278_2.png" class="avatar"> aschrijver:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Maybe there should be an additional step, where ‘the community’ feedback <em>must</em> be collected in the repo (e.g. as issue comments), even if to explicitly state “I stand behind this proposal” which is as valuable as discussions (especially when coming directly from fedi app maintainers).</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I hope a general understanding of what this means will develop naturally and we do not have to specify strictly the form and medium of discussion.</p>
<p>I’d suggest leaving it out of FEP-a4ed. In the future when we have tested the waters and seen what kind of discussions work, we might have a <code>FEP-6c17:  Best Practices for Initiating Discussion and Collecting Feedback on a FEP proposal</code> . What do you think?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I guess in my <a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/17">most recent comments</a> above, it indicates there’s already a need for this, but in a slightly more specific and practical manner (if y’all agree with that feedback, that is).</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/20">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/20</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 05:14:12 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1171-20</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171.rss">FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p><a class="mention" href="/u/cjs">@cjs</a> yes, that would be easiest maintenance-wise, and I think that this <em>should</em> be included in the FEP template, imho.</p>
<p>On the other point my experience is that discussion threads (such as this one with now 18 comments, or the Followers Sync FEP with 41 posts) are so easily TL;DR’ed, where they just respond to the most recent comment. You could say it is their fault then if they missed an open issue or decision in parsing the history of the thread. This saves the author some time, but shifts the burden to each and every reader.</p>
<p>The authors are probably most deeply aware of all ins and outs of the FEP, and are responsible for the collection of feedback already. Part of that might include providing this summary of open issues / decision points that allow readers to drill into the subject matter quickly.</p>
<p>Right now the issue tracker in the FEP repo is unused. The workflow might be that - as soon as an open issue pops up in discussion - someone (e.g. the author) creates a FEP-related issue, with an appropriate label, and maybe a user assignment indicating who is responsible for dealing with it. So for example:</p>
<blockquote>
<h3>FEP-f1d5: Include software.version in NodeInfo? &nbsp; <code>[decision]</code>
</h3>
<p>Assigned to: <a class="mention" href="/u/cjs">@cjs</a><br>
Discussion: <code>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-f1d5-nodeinfo-in-fediverse-software/1190/4</code></p>
<p><a class="mention" href="/u/macgirvin">@macgirvin</a> proposed to exclude <code>software.version</code> from NodeInfo because inclusion might pose a security issue.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The issue need not be larger than that. Discussion is on the forum. Once a clear agreement is reached the issue is updated with a <code>[resolved]</code> label and some text, then closed. Before the FEP enters finalization stage the Issues should be added to References section (or a separate section just for issues).</p>
<p>(Note that you could also create individual labels for each FEP, and then there’s no need to create a list, but instead you include the url to the filtered issues on that label in References section)</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/19">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/19</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2020 04:55:58 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1171-19</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171.rss">FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[cjs]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>My personal vote is for the second option, for FEPs to link to:</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="aschrijver" data-post="17" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/aschrijver/40/278_2.png" class="avatar"> aschrijver:</div>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>A link to the forum discussion topic / post where the decision was argumented and taken.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
</aside>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/18">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/18</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2020 20:04:21 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1171-18</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171.rss">FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Some remarks regarding <a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-f1d5-nodeinfo-in-fediverse-software/1190/4" class="inline-onebox">FEP-f1d5: NodeInfo in Fediverse Software</a></p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="cjs" data-post="4" data-topic="1190">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/cjs/40/584_2.png" class="avatar"><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-f1d5-nodeinfo-in-fediverse-software/1190/4">FEP-f1d5: NodeInfo in Fediverse Software</a>
</div>
<blockquote>
<p>As such, I’d like to avoid putting the first bullet in the FEP.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>The discussion of a possible security issue took place in a toot, and was followed-up on the forum, where - in this situation - it may be decided that this should not be documented in the FEP (as it is arguably a ‘security-by-obscurity’ issue that makes matters worse), BUT…</p>
<p>The issue was a valid point that was brought up, and the decision not to include is possibly made somewhere deep in a long forum discussion thread. Not only should the original author be aware of it, but any other AP implementer should too.</p>
<p>Therefore 2 things may be part of the FEP document format:</p>
<ul>
<li>A list of open issues, or rather decision points, where the outcome may be documented too e.g.: “We’ll avoid security-by-obscurity and include version information”</li>
<li>A link to the forum discussion topic / post where the decision was argumented and taken.</li>
</ul>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/17">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/17</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2020 11:26:21 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1171-17</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171.rss">FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="pukkamustard" data-post="15" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/pukkamustard/40/111_2.png" class="avatar"> pukkamustard:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Ok, if we concentrate on doing this in a nice presentation of FEPs (e.g. <code>library.activitypub.dev</code> ) and revisit index in README after?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Yes, that would also work if the README contains a clear reference to the list. Agreed.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="pukkamustard" data-post="15" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/pukkamustard/40/111_2.png" class="avatar"> pukkamustard:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>In the future when we have tested the waters and seen what kind of discussions work, we might have a <code>FEP-6c17:  Best Practices for Initiating Discussion and Collecting Feedback on a FEP proposal</code> . What do you think?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Super idea.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="pukkamustard" data-post="15" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/pukkamustard/40/111_2.png" class="avatar"> pukkamustard:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I invite you to consider yourself familiar with the process.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Woot, thx &nbsp; <img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/images/emoji/twitter/partying_face.png?v=9" title=":partying_face:" class="emoji" alt=":partying_face:"></p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/16">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/16</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2020 07:31:13 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1171-16</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171.rss">FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[pukkamustard]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="aschrijver" data-post="13" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/aschrijver/40/278_2.png" class="avatar"> aschrijver:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I think what’s still missing is what happens when things get FINAL.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Absolutely. The idea was to first concentrate on the FEP documents itself and once it is in half-way decent form allow it to be presented in a nicer format. The document structure of FEPs was intentionally made easy to use from static-site generators. Some ideas on how and where to present FEPs in a nicer format:</p>
<ul>
<li>library.activitypub.dev (cc <a class="mention" href="/u/cjs">@cjs</a>)</li>
<li>activitypub.rocks:  I’m all for adding FEPs there as well. I can submit a patch that makes haunt read FEPs and display them. However, who controls <code>activitypub.rocks</code>? Where and who hosts the site? Who decides what goes on there? And why not move <code>git.activitypub.dev</code> to <code>git.activitypub.rocks</code>? I think this should be forked to a topic for itself.</li>
</ul>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="aschrijver" data-post="13" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/aschrijver/40/278_2.png" class="avatar"> aschrijver:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Also a topic with pointers and explainer might be permanently pinned to the top of this forum: “FEP’s: Wanna enhance the Fediverse? Here’s how the process works”</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Props to <a class="mention" href="/u/how">@how</a> for doing this.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="aschrijver" data-post="13" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/aschrijver/40/278_2.png" class="avatar"> aschrijver:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Oh, and imho the README should have a list or table of FEP’s in the repo, with link + brief description + status.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>This is something that can be very well be done by a static-site generator (or similar) and I am a bit reluctant to add it, as it does add considerable maintenance burden.</p>
<p>Ok, if we concentrate on doing this in a nice presentation of FEPs (e.g. <code>library.activitypub.dev</code>) and revisit index in README after?</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="aschrijver" data-post="13" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/aschrijver/40/278_2.png" class="avatar"> aschrijver:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>In Readme: “[After submission] you are now <strong>required</strong> to …” and in FEP-a4ed “Authors are <strong>responsible</strong> …”. I find the latter a better, more friendly description.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p><img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/images/emoji/twitter/+1.png?v=9" title=":+1:" class="emoji" alt=":+1:"> done (<a href="https://git.activitypub.dev/ActivityPubDev/Fediverse-Enhancement-Proposals/pulls/6" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://git.activitypub.dev/ActivityPubDev/Fediverse-Enhancement-Proposals/pulls/6</a>)</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="aschrijver" data-post="13" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/aschrijver/40/278_2.png" class="avatar"> aschrijver:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>But what if someone started with good intention, FEP accepted, then slacks off in doing community outreach, asks for finalization, and after 2wks… it becomes FINAL?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>The default path is: <code>DRAFT</code> -&gt; <code>WITHDRAWN</code>. And if interest in a proposal fades this is what would happen.</p>
<p>There is a lot of room for interpretation what is required for a proposal to be come final. FEP-a4ed says:</p>
<pre><code class="lang-auto">  - If there are no community objections within 14 days and the authors can show that they have initiated sufficient awareness and discussion of the proposal, an editor will set the status of the submission to `FINAL`.
</code></pre>
<p>The “burden-of-proof” lies with the author but what exactly is “sufficient awareness and discussion” is vague.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="aschrijver" data-post="13" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/aschrijver/40/278_2.png" class="avatar"> aschrijver:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Maybe there should be an additional step, where ‘the community’ feedback <em>must</em> be collected in the repo (e.g. as issue comments), even if to explicitly state “I stand behind this proposal” which is as valuable as discussions (especially when coming directly from fedi app maintainers).</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I hope a general understanding of what this means will develop naturally and we do not have to specify strictly the form and medium of discussion.</p>
<p>I’d suggest leaving it out of FEP-a4ed. In the future when we have tested the waters and seen what kind of discussions work, we might have a <code>FEP-6c17:  Best Practices for Initiating Discussion and Collecting Feedback on a FEP proposal</code>. What do you think?</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="aschrijver" data-post="13" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/aschrijver/40/278_2.png" class="avatar"> aschrijver:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I am not familiar with FEP processes</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I invite you to consider yourself familiar with the process. <img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/images/emoji/twitter/slight_smile.png?v=9" title=":slight_smile:" class="emoji" alt=":slight_smile:"></p>
<p>There should not be much magic to it. The goal of <code>FEP-a4ed</code> is to understandably and correctly describe the process.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/15">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/15</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 07 Dec 2020 11:08:09 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1171-15</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171.rss">FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[how]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Hello,</p>
<p>I created a new topic to host this discussion so it provides:</p>
<ol>
<li>a direct link to the repository entry</li>
<li>a clean first post to host the future final version</li>
</ol>
<p>I described the whole thing in <a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/about-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposals/1168/1" class="inline-onebox">About the Fediverse Enhancement Proposals</a>.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/14">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/14</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2020 17:22:54 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1171-14</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171.rss">FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[system]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>source: <a href="https://git.activitypub.dev/ActivityPubDev/Fediverse-Enhancement-Proposals/src/branch/main/feps/fep-a4ed.md">https://git.activitypub.dev/ActivityPubDev/Fediverse-Enhancement-Proposals/src/branch/main/feps/fep-a4ed.md</a></p>
<hr>
<p>authors: <a class="mention" href="/u/pukkamustard">@pukkamustard</a><br>
status: FINAL<br>
dateReceived: 2020-10-16<br>
dateFinalized: 2021-01-18</p>
<h1>FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</h1>
<h2>Summary</h2>
<p>A Fediverse Enhancement Proposal (FEP) is a document that provides information to the Fediverse community. The goal of a FEP is to improve interoperability and well-being of diverse services, applications and communities that form the Fediverse.</p>
<p>This document describes the scope, format and process of publishing Fediverse Enhancement Proposals.</p>
<h2>Scope and Objectives</h2>
<p>A Fediverse Enhancement Proposal (FEP) should be a concise and focused documentation of a specific topic that is of interest to the Fediverse community.</p>
<p>A proposal should always have the intention of improving the interoperability and well-being of diverse services, applications and community of the Fediverse.</p>
<p>The Fediverse includes applications, services and communities using the ActivityPub protocol and other protocols that foster decentralized and diverse social media and culture.</p>
<p>Proposals may include descriptions of technical protocols and mechanism, documentation of experimental work or current best practices.</p>
<p>Proposals are not limited to technical topics and may focus on social and cultural aspects.</p>
<p>Proposals may be entertaining and humorous (unlike this proposal).</p>
<h2>Language, Document Structure and Format</h2>
<p>All Fediverse Enhancement Proposals must be written in English, be properly formatted as CommonMark [CommonMark] and be reasonably grammatical.</p>
<p>Authors should use inclusive language and examples and refrain from using oppressive terminology [Internet-Draft-terminology].</p>
<h3>Proposal Title and Identifier</h3>
<p>Every Fediverse Enhancement Proposals must have a descriptive title.</p>
<p>An identifier is computed from the proposal title as the first 7 digits of the sha256 hash (in hex). The identifier can be computed from the title with standard Unix tools:</p>
<pre><code class="lang-auto">$ echo -n "The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process" | sha256sum | cut -c-4
a4ed
</code></pre>
<p>By using the hash of the title as identifier we reduce the burden on editors to assign unique ids. This require proposal titles to be unique.</p>
<h3>Metadata</h3>
<p>Proposal metadata is placed at the top of the document as key-value pairs between opening and closing ~—~.</p>
<p>Following metadata key-value pairs may be placed at the top of a proposal:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<code>authors</code>: A comma separated list of authors of the proposal.</li>
<li>
<code>status</code>: Indicates the proposal status. Can be either <code>DRAFT</code>, <code>WITHDRAWN</code> or <code>FINAL</code>.</li>
<li>
<code>dateReceived</code>: Date of when the proposal was added to the repository (when status is set to <code>DRAFT</code>).</li>
<li>
<code>dateWithdrawn</code>: Date of when the proposal status was set to <code>WITHDRAWN</code> (only for proposals with status <code>WITHDRAWN</code>).</li>
<li>
<code>dateFinalized</code>: Date of when the proposal status was set to <code>FINAL</code> (only for proposals with status <code>FINAL</code>).</li>
<li>
<code>relatedFeps</code>: A comma separated list of related FEPs (e.g. <code>FEP-a4ed, FEP-141a, FEP-686f</code>).</li>
</ul>
<p>Future FEPs may specify additional metadata fields.</p>
<h3>Required Sections</h3>
<p>Every FEP should include at least following sections:</p>
<ul>
<li>Summary: A short (no more than 200 words) summary of the proposal.</li>
<li>Copyright: Indicating that the proposal has been placed in the public domain.</li>
</ul>
<p>Following sections may be included in a proposal:</p>
<ul>
<li>History: An overview of previous related efforts and how they relate to the proposal.</li>
<li>Implementations: If applicable an overview of services or applications that implement the proposal at time of submission.</li>
<li>References: A list of documents and resources referenced by the proposal.</li>
</ul>
<h3>Copyright</h3>
<p>Fediverse Enhancement Proposals must be placed in the public domain by the authors with a CC0 1.0 Universal (CC0 1.0) Public Domain Dedication.</p>
<h2>The Fediverse Enhancement Proposals Process</h2>
<pre><code class="lang-auto">                                     +-------+
                           +-------&gt; | FINAL | 
                           |         +-------+
         +-------+         |
--------&gt;| DRAFT | --------+
         +-------+         |
             ^             |         +-----------+
             |             +-------&gt; | WITHDRAWN |
             |                       +-----------+
             |                             |
             +-----------------------------+
</code></pre>
<ol>
<li>A Fediverse Enhancement Proposal can be submitted by individuals or groups of individuals (authors). See the <code>SUBMISSION.md</code> file for a list of accepted submission methods.</li>
<li>Within seven days one of the editors will read and respond to the proposal. The editor checks if the proposal conforms to the required structure and fits the scope and objective of the FEPs. The editor may request the authors to clarify, justify, or withdraw the proposal. Such a request must not reflect the personal bias of an editor. Rather, it will be made strictly to maintain a high quality of submissions. The editors reserve the right to reject a submission when a proposal amounts to blatant misuse of the process. The authors may seek feedback from the wider community if the submitted proposal is rejected or clarifications are requested.</li>
<li>If a FEP editor approves a submission it receives the status <code>DRAFT</code> and is added to the repository.</li>
<li>While a proposal has the status <code>DRAFT</code>:
<ul>
<li>Authors are responsible for initiating community discussion and collecting feedback.</li>
<li>Authors may submit updates to the proposal which will be checked in to the repository by an editor.</li>
<li>Authors may withdraw the submission upon which an editor will set the status of the submission to <code>WITHDRAWN</code>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>After at least 60 days the authors may request the proposal to be finalized. This is done by requesting final comments on the proposal.
<ul>
<li>If there are no community objections within 14 days and the authors can show that they have initiated sufficient awareness and discussion of the proposal, an editor will set the status of the submission to <code>FINAL</code>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>If after 120 days the authors have not requested the proposal to be finalized or there is no community consensus, an editor will set the status of the submission to <code>WITHDRAWN</code>.</li>
<li>A proposal with status <code>FINAL</code> can not be changed or updated.</li>
<li>A proposal with status <code>WITHDRAWN</code> remains in the repository and can be resubmitted.</li>
</ol>
<h3>Editors</h3>
<p>A list of editors is maintained in the <code>EDITORS.md</code> file at the root of the FEP repository.</p>
<h3>Submission Methods</h3>
<p>A list of methods in which a proposal may be submitted is maintained in the <code>SUBMISSION.md</code> file at the root of the FEP repository.</p>
<h2>History</h2>
<p>The process and format described in this proposal is influenced by other community driven documentation efforts such as the BitTorrent Enhancement Proposal Process [BEP-1], Scheme Request for Implementation [SRFI] and the IETF RFC Series [RFC-8729].</p>
<h2>References</h2>
<ul>
<li>[SRFI] Dave Mason, <a href="https://srfi.schemers.org/srfi-process.html">Scheme Request For Implementation - Process</a>
</li>
<li>[BEP-1] David Harrison, <a href="http://bittorrent.org/beps/bep_0001.html">The BitTorrent Enhancement Proposal Process</a>, 2008</li>
<li>[RFC-8729] Housley, R., Ed., and L. Daigle, Ed., <a href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8729">The RFC Series and RFC Editor</a>, 2020</li>
<li>[CommonMark] John MacFarlane, <a href="https://spec.commonmark.org/0.29/">CommonMark Spec</a> Version 0.29, 2019</li>
<li>[Internet-Draft-terminology] Mallory Knodel, <a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-knodel-terminology">Terminology, Power and Oppressive Language</a>
</li>
</ul>
<h2>Copyright</h2>
<p>CC0 1.0 Universal (CC0 1.0) Public Domain Dedication</p>
<p>To the extent possible under law, the authors of this Fediverse Enhancement Proposal have waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this work.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/1">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/1</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2020 17:19:21 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1171-1</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171.rss">FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Nice work!</p>
<p>I think what’s still missing is what happens when things get FINAL. We have created something authoritative now, right? So that should be advertised on a prominent location preferably. I wonder about the current location being most suitable for that. I see git.activitypub.dev more as the workspace for FEP’s, and ideally, maybe FINAL FEB’s should be mentioned on activitypub.rocks landing page (though just linked to the repo with some info to it, that would be enough imho). Activitypub.rocks is <span class="hashtag">#1</span> search result for ActivityPub and authoritative for the spec (besides the W3C, of course).</p>
<p>Also a topic with pointers and explainer might be permanently pinned to the top of this forum: “FEP’s: Wanna enhance the Fediverse? Here’s how the process works”</p>
<p><strong>Edit</strong>: Oh, and imho the README should have a list or table of FEP’s in the repo, with link + brief description + status.</p>
<p>Some other feedback:</p>
<ul>
<li>In Readme: “[After submission] you are now <strong>required</strong> to …” and in FEP-a4ed “Authors are <strong>responsible</strong> …”. I find the latter a better, more friendly description.</li>
<li>But what if someone started with good intention, FEP accepted, then slacks off in doing community outreach, asks for finalization, and after 2wks… it becomes FINAL?</li>
</ul>
<p>I am not familiar with FEP processes, but the last point may mean that hardly anyone noticed the FEP in the first place, and the FEP is of little value or detrimental to the quality of the process itself. Maybe there should be an additional step, where ‘the community’ feedback <em>must</em> be collected in the repo (e.g. as issue comments), even if to explicitly state “I stand behind this proposal” which is as valuable as discussions (especially when coming directly from fedi app maintainers).</p>
<p>Additionally either the FEP repo or activitypub.rocks or both might keep track of projects that have actually adopted / incorporated / implemented the FEP, which serves to demontrate its usefulness, and is both encouragement for others to adopt, as well as providing reference material (e.g. example code) for doing so.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/13">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/13</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2020 09:43:57 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1171-13</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171.rss">FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[pukkamustard]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>A small update to FEP-a4ed just got merged. I hope this addresses the issues raised here. Quick summary:</p>
<ul>
<li>Identifiers are now only 4 characters long (FEP-a4ed instead of FEP-a4edc7b). Slightly more memorable at a probably acceptable chance of collision.</li>
<li>Updated IETF Terminology draft to latest version (thanks <a class="mention" href="/u/aschrijver">@aschrijver</a>)</li>
<li>Add a <code>SUBMISSION_METHODS</code> file to the root of the repository that includes the exact address of the repo and how to submit a proposal. This addressed the issue brought up by <a class="mention" href="/u/claire">@Claire</a> and at the same time allows the repo to be moved if ever necessary.</li>
</ul>
<p>See the pull request for a diff: <a href="https://git.activitypub.dev/ActivityPubDev/Fediverse-Enhancement-Proposals/pulls/5" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://git.activitypub.dev/ActivityPubDev/Fediverse-Enhancement-Proposals/pulls/5</a></p>
<p>Some notes on the proposal status (as an illustration how submission process works):</p>
<ul>
<li>It has been 46 days since FEP-a4ed was submitted (16th October 2020).</li>
<li>The initial draft period lasts for at least 60 days - until the 15th of December 2020.</li>
<li>On the 15th of December (or shortly after) I will request final comments on the proposal from you, the community. If there are no objections the propsoal will be finalized (receive status <code>FINAL</code> 14 days after - on the 29th of December)</li>
</ul>
<p>The submission process takes a bit of time. The hope is that such a long time allows comments, suggestions and objections to be made without haste.</p>
<p>Personally, I am happy with the pace. The submission has not required constant attention from me and the work involved is reasonable.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/12">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/12</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2020 08:38:17 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1171-12</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171.rss">FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I don’t know if it is better, but this link also tracks the IETF terminology doc <a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-knodel-terminology/">https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-knodel-terminology/</a> (found via the <a href="https://github.com/w3c/idcg/issues/15">W3C Internet Diversity CG</a> which also has a <a href="https://w3c.github.io/manual-of-style/#inclusive">Manual of Style</a> with terminology suggestions).</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/11">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/11</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 08:03:40 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1171-11</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171.rss">FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[Claire]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="pukkamustard" data-post="9" data-topic="1171">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/pukkamustard/40/111_2.png" class="avatar"> pukkamustard:</div>
<blockquote>
<p><a class="mention" href="/u/claire">@Claire</a>, does that work for you and resolve the issue?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Yeah, that works, opened a PR!</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/10">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171/10</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 23 Oct 2020 12:32:27 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1171-10</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-a4ed-the-fediverse-enhancement-proposal-process/1171.rss">FEP-a4ed: The Fediverse Enhancement Proposal Process</source>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
