<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</title>
    <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453</link>
    <description>This historical topic conserves the original discussion about the https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-socialhub-community-values/1391.

### Proposal stage

Since this is a @staff proposal, the policy ~~will~~ enter&lt;ins&gt;ed&lt;/ins&gt; into force &lt;del&gt;after a week&lt;/del&gt; &lt;ins&gt;on&lt;/ins&gt; ([date=2021-02-19 timezone=&quot;Europe/Brussels&quot;]), to leave a bit of time for debate, in the hope to clarify any ambiguous point that may appear. All members of this forum will have to take action (either agree or disagree) to stop the daily flood of reminders.</description>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 17:01:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <category>SocialHub Policy</category>
    <atom:link href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
        <title>Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[how]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>This historical topic conserves the original discussion about the <a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-socialhub-community-values/1391" class="inline-onebox">SocialHub Community Values Policy</a>.</p>
<h3>Proposal stage</h3>
<p>Since this is a <a class="mention-group" href="/groups/staff">@staff</a> proposal, the policy <s>will</s> enter<ins>ed</ins> into force <del>after a week</del> <ins>on</ins> (<span data-date="2021-02-19" class="discourse-local-date" data-timezone="Europe/Brussels" data-email-preview="2021-02-18T23:00:00Z UTC">2021-02-18T23:00:00Z</span>), to leave a bit of time for debate, in the hope to clarify any ambiguous point that may appear. All members of this forum will have to take action (either agree or disagree) to stop the daily flood of reminders.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/1">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/1</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 17:01:25 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1453-1</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453.rss">Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[how]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/57">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/57</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 16:48:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1453-57</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453.rss">Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[how]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Then, I would like to proceed to the next stage, calling to everyone to read the policy and take a stand.<br>
Later today or the next day I will move this discussion to a dedicated linked topic and edit the first post to reflect the new stage.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/56">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/56</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2021 14:10:04 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1453-56</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453.rss">Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[kaniini]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Yes, that seems fine.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/55">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/55</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2021 08:59:56 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1453-55</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453.rss">Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[how]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group quote-modified" data-username="rhiaro" data-post="1" data-topic="1391">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/rhiaro/40/712_2.png" class="avatar"> rhiaro:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I’ve updated the Policy to make it clear we are not trying to place unreasonable burdens on developers or other participants in open source communities who can’t be held responsible for actions of wider communities or other users of their projects.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="system" data-post="1" data-topic="1391">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/original/1X/2957f9f20df131569f26dd7b28bbe7f4af5739f5.png" class="avatar"> system:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>The intent of this policy is <em>not</em> to exclude wholesale any developers involved with projects or communities who unknowingly interact with bad actors, or who are struggling to or unable to eliminate behavior that goes against this policy in their wider communities. Similarly, we do not expect developers of open source projects to be responsible for every installation or fork of their codebase and will of course take the realities of this into account when making any moderation decisions.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Given the update, <a class="mention" href="/u/kaniini">@kaniini</a> (and others) are you fine with this policy?</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/54">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/54</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2021 08:13:32 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1453-54</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453.rss">Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[rhiaro]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <blockquote>
<p>It effectively forces all SocialHub members to (in turn) enforce social justice on all communities using their software.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>We don’t force anything. We already discussed the concern about burden on adjacent communities/projects, and plan to clarify, I just didn’t have time to write anything yet.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Enforcing <em>any</em> single world view on the Fediverse is the path to totalitarianism, not to the freedom that I believe we are seeking.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>To be clear, we have no power over “the Fediverse”, only the behaviour that is acceptable in this forum, and SocialCG meetings and events.</p>
<p>Agree with <a class="mention" href="/u/how">@how</a>’s response, flipping the policy is nonsensical.</p>
<p>Saying bigotry is not welcome or tolerated here is not discriminatory and should not even be controversial.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>what if you don’t know they are an adversarial group?</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a class="mention" href="/u/kaniini">@kaniini</a> I would consider this caught by the “good faith” phrase. I do plan to try to improve the text to address your earlier concerns, as soon as I can. We also need to make sure moderation decisions are transparent, collaborative and reversible if we make mistakes, to mitigate any accidental harm to genuine contributors.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/53">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/53</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2021 14:27:28 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1453-53</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453.rss">Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[conscientousobjector]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="how" data-post="50" data-topic="1453">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/how/40/94_2.png" class="avatar"> how:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I hope we can advance to actual proposals.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I have an actual proposal: We don’t need this proposal. The W3C guidelines go far enough.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/52">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/52</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2021 00:12:32 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1453-52</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453.rss">Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[kaniini]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="how" data-post="50" data-topic="1453">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/how/40/94_2.png" class="avatar"> how:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>if you respond to a plead for help and support from an adversarial group, it’s another story.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>This bothers me, for a few reasons:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>what if you don’t know they are an adversarial group?</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>this seems like a substantial overreach of SocialCG into the internal operations of projects.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>I’ve already explicitly stated the boundary I am comfortable with (commit rights).  If commit rights prove insufficient, we can revise later.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/51">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/51</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 09 Feb 2021 10:50:09 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1453-51</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453.rss">Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[how]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="conscientousobjector" data-post="49" data-topic="1453">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/c/3d9bf3/40.png" class="avatar"> conscientousobjector:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Enforcing social justice creates a new group of vulnerable people (those who disagree with it) and justifies harm against them (as ‘accountability’ in the form of cancellation, harassment, etc.).</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I cannot accept this reversing. The policy statement clearly defines boundaries, and doing harm is beyond this boundary. I think you’re confusing community boundaries – the sort of things we do not accept – with some abstract relativist worldview. We’re not talking about enforcing stuff on people, but simply to mark a line of no-go. Following your logic, we should be complacent with fascists because they do not agree with social justice. Well, no: it is not us who harass people and threaten them.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="conscientousobjector" data-post="49" data-topic="1453">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/c/3d9bf3/40.png" class="avatar"> conscientousobjector:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Enforcing <em>any</em> single world view on the Fediverse is the path to totalitarianism, not to the freedom that I believe we are seeking.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Then we do not have boundaries. Or can we? If you can come back with a proposal that makes sense, not enforcing a single world view, I can start thinking about it, but your binary flipping of a coin does not make any sense.</p>
<p>This policy is to encourage diversity, not diversity-averse uniformity. Being a bigot is not being diverse, it’s being against diversity. Shedding light on a problem does cast shadows, but also marks limits.</p>
<p>AFAIC the main objection made by <a class="mention" href="/u/kaniini">@kaniini</a> is that it feels like making software developers responsible for the abuse of some of their users. What I’d like that we clarify is that it does not: but it also encourages that software developers do not sympathize with harmful users and communities. If you respond to a security bug, it makes sense to fix it ; if you respond to a plead for help and support from an adversarial group, it’s another story. But still, we’re not a police force. This is a line drawn in the sand, if you cross it, it’s legitimate for the community to question your presence, and it’s fair that you’re<br>
given a chance to think about it and act accordingly (that’s the meaning of:</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="system" data-post="1" data-topic="1391">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/original/1X/2957f9f20df131569f26dd7b28bbe7f4af5739f5.png" class="avatar"><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1391/1">Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</a>
</div>
<blockquote>
<p>We reserve the right to exclude projects which tolerate such behaviours within their communities, or <em>have not made a good faith effort to discourage such behaviours.</em></p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>So, to conclude : this is not about <em>identity politics</em> nor a binary coin that you can flip ; it’s about <em>unwanted behaviors</em> and the limit we draw for active participation in <em>this</em> community.</p>
<p>I hope we can advance to actual proposals.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/50">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/50</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 09 Feb 2021 10:43:55 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1453-50</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453.rss">Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[conscientousobjector]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I suggest that this proposed policy is more significant than it first appears. It effectively forces all SocialHub members to (in turn) enforce social justice on all communities using their software. Failure to do so will result in the contributor’s exclusion from the SocialHub community and the support that this community offers.</p>
<p>I understand that this proposal is motivated by a genuine desire to protect vulnerable people. I commend that desire.</p>
<p>Enforcing a single world view (whether that of social justice or any other) on all independent social projects, however, is a Very Bad Idea.</p>
<p>If you disagree with that statement, it may be that you have complete confidence in social justice as world view. Perhaps you believe that social justice is so clear and obvious that anyone who questions it must be motivated by a desire to retain their unjustly-held power (bigots, fascists, etc.). Perhaps you suspect me of having these motives.</p>
<p>It is precisely this (over)confidence in the virtue of a particular world view, however, which is the problem. The only way to prevent significant overreach of a world view is for each person to have the right to question and critique orthodox beliefs.</p>
<p>Enforcing social justice creates a new group of vulnerable people (those who disagree with it) and justifies harm against them (as ‘accountability’ in the form of cancellation, harassment, etc.). This harm is justified by the <em>overconfidence</em> mentioned in my last paragraph - the belief that dissenters <em>must</em> be driven by selfish motives and, therefore, that the faithful have an obligation to punish them and lay the blame at their feet. This is the same logic that oppressive regimes use to brutally punish dissenters and blame the dissenters for their own punishment.</p>
<p>You might respond by saying that you do not wish to prevent people from discussing ideas, you only wish to prevent harm to vulnerable people. To that I suggest that social justice has such far-reaching goals in redefining language, culture and law that there is very little room for anyone to move without transgression. Consider that, for instance, a Black person is only a Black person if they fully agree with and abide by every tenet of social justice, otherwise they become an unprotected white-adjacent lower-case ‘b’ black person who is scorned. Social justice loves only the people who fully surrender to it and it hates everyone else - even members of vulnerable groups that it claims to protect. This, I respectfully suggest, is not love at all.</p>
<p>It is difficult to see this when considering your own world view.</p>
<p>Imagine a proposed policy for SocialHub which said the following:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>we do not welcome participation (however polite) by contributors to projects which are designed or primarily used for:</p>
<pre><code>- disseminating ideas which oppose traditional and/or family values,
planning, encouragement of or inciting violence against conservative people.
- promoting leftist ideas or other authoritarian systems and practices.
- perpetuating, promoting, or enacting socialism or Marxism.
</code></pre>
<p>We reserve the right to exclude projects which tolerate such behaviours within their communities, or have not made a good faith effort to discourage such behaviours.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Would you be opposed to such a policy? Of course you would, and rightly so.</p>
<p>You might be opposed to it because you believe the ideas contained in it to be toxic. I suggest, however, that you should oppose any policy which enforces a single world view on every person. Even - and most especially - the world view that you personally hold to be true.</p>
<p>Enforcing <em>any</em> single world view on the Fediverse is the path to totalitarianism, not to the freedom that I believe we are seeking.</p>
<p>Thank you for reading my objection to this proposal. I am happy to answer any questions, concerns or objections that you have.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/49">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/49</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 09 Feb 2021 03:07:28 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1453-49</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453.rss">Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[rhiaro]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>The proposal is precisely to highlight that we stand with vulnerable groups in particular, and will not disregard the experiences of those at the disadvantaged end of a systematic power imbalance. It is not always obvious that that is the case.</p>
<p>The W3C CECP applies to everyone, and for everyone. Please read it, if you haven’t. It covers all kinds of distasteful behaviour, none of which are accepted in this community.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/48">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/48</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 06 Feb 2021 23:38:03 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1453-48</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453.rss">Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[Hyolobrika]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p><em><a class="mention" href="/u/sebastian">@Sebastian</a> invited me to post my views as a user of the Fediverse after I replied to <a href="https://mastodon.social/@sl007/105668934648745319" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">his post</a> pointing to this proposal and discussion.</em><br>
Is this proposal signing intended just for ActivityPub developers or end users too?<br>
Either way I object to it. Namely that distasteful behaviour seems to only be considered a problem when vulnerable groups are the victims. Shouldn’t everyone have the benefits of a kind community, not just a few?</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/47">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/47</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 06 Feb 2021 15:13:29 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1453-47</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453.rss">Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[rhiaro]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <blockquote>
<p>The policy statement as presently required would require Mastodon and Pleroma to reject all forms of contribution from those groups, including security-impacting bug reports, lest falling in violation of the policy statement</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I agree that this interpretation is absurd, and not what was intended. I’d like to continue to work on the wording to avoid this interpretation in future. This was kind of what I was trying to capture with “good faith”, but obviously needs to be clearer. Thanks again for the feedback, all in this thread.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/46">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/46</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 06 Feb 2021 13:54:44 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1453-46</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453.rss">Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[Sebastian]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>/meta<br>
<em>pinned this post globally</em><br>
reason: It concerns all socialhub users and should be immediately visible.<br>
It would otherwise go below the fold of the main stream.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/45">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/45</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2021 08:58:06 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1453-45</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453.rss">Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[kaniini]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="schmittlauch" data-post="43" data-topic="1453">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/schmittlauch/40/84_2.png" class="avatar"> schmittlauch:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>One example is stalking: When one participant is stalking another person, that obviously does not only happen on this forum. But being stalked somewhere else still makes this space unsafe if their stalker is allowed to be in the same community.<br>
Similarly, playing polite here while throwing racist or TERF slurs to members of this community via other channels is also something I find hard to accept – in the long term, this causes marginalised people to leave while their adversaries are staying.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>This is precisely the reason I chose to leave Pleroma – it became obvious we weren’t all playing on the “same team.”  So it made sense to step out of the way and do something else.</p>
<p>I agree that a boundary should be set there.  As participants in SocialCG, we should all be playing on the same team, and not slagging each other outside of the work environment.  So hard +1 from me on that front.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="schmittlauch" data-post="43" data-topic="1453">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/schmittlauch/40/84_2.png" class="avatar"> schmittlauch:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Once they have been made aware of the problematic entity of who they’re dealing with – the allegations need to be substantiated of course – then the decision of whether to continue this interaction or not becomes their liability.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Mostly this, <em>but</em> what if the evil entity is reporting a legitimate bug (say, a security bug) that impacts <em>all</em> users of the software?  Should they be disallowed from doing so?</p>
<p>I might not personally like authors of certain fediverse software, but if they reported bugs to me, I would want to fix those bugs so that everyone benefits.</p>
<p>So I think the appropriate boundary is whether a problematic entity possesses commit rights to the software: users involved in a project which is affiliated with SocialCG must abide by the policy statement during the period of that engagement or the affiliation will be terminated.</p>
<p>This is a concrete and most importantly objective boundary that does not impose any undue burden on a downstream.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/44">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/44</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2021 01:33:14 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1453-44</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453.rss">Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[schmittlauch]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <h2>scope of the policy</h2>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="aschrijver" data-post="38" data-topic="1453">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/aschrijver/40/278_2.png" class="avatar"> aschrijver:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>From my understanding everyone is in agreement (but anyone pls chime in if they see it differently) that the effort to <em>‘provide community safety and ensuring community health’</em> - part of which in form of a policy, CoC, diversity statement, or whatever we agree it to be - is indeed scoped <em>exclusively</em> to SocialCG, SocialHub and affiliated sites plus repositories.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I do see a problem with strictly limiting the scope of this to SocialCG and SocialHub comunications. Because the linked W3C CoC lists some <em>unacceptable behaviour</em> that’d be impossible to regard when exclusively focusing on this platform.<br>
One example is stalking: When one participant is stalking another person, that obviously does not only happen on this forum. But being stalked somewhere else still makes this space unsafe if their stalker is allowed to be in the same community.<br>
Similarly, playing polite here while throwing racist or TERF slurs to members of this community via other channels is also something I find hard to accept – in the long term, this causes marginalised people to leave while their adversaries are staying.</p>
<p>Striking the balance in such a way that people do not bring in their nitty-gritty personal minor conflicts is challenging, indeed. But as part of this policy is understanding how stalking, racial slurs and similar are not just personal issues, I think that’s doable.</p>
<h2>responsibility for downstream project interactions</h2>
<p>While I advocate for not restricting the scope of the policy too narrowly (see above), I suggest to restrict its reach somewhere else:</p>
<p><a class="mention" href="/u/kaniini">@kaniini</a>’s concerns about weaponised downstream liability sound reasonable to me, so I suggest that by default a project is not immediately liable for actions of or interactions with non-project members.<br>
I suggest to combine this with an idea similar to the liability restrictions of hosting providers or with a <em>good samaritan clause</em> (disclaimer: I’m neither a lawyer not from the anglosphere of jurisdiction). When interacting with external users, bug reporters, or contributors, good faith and naivety of the project members is assumed in case the entity they are interacting with is in violation of this policy here. Once they have been made aware of the problematic entity of who they’re dealing with – the allegations need to be substantiated of course – then the decision of whether to continue this interaction or not becomes their liability.</p>
<h2>transparency of moderation decisions</h2>
<p>As we just have seen, discussing the legitimacy of moderation decisions is hard to do when it is not even clear what had happened.<br>
So in spirit of transparency, I suggest that some especially strong moderation decisions need to be published in a summarised and anonymous form afterwards.</p>
<p>Example: account deleted/ project rejected because of clear ties to the QAnon myth, which is in violation of our policy on racism and violence.</p>
<hr>
<p>These are some ideas for improvement. Once they have been discussed, I am willing to put them into actual policy phrasing.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/43">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/43</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2021 01:20:28 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1453-43</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453.rss">Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[how]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>The current matter concerns the scope of the proposal: it’s about what we want within the SocialCG and the SocialHub, e.g., to avoid having the <a class="hashtag" href="/c/software/14">#<span>software</span></a> category reaped with software supporting <code>alt-tech</code> values that we do not share ; it’s about making this space <em>uninviting</em> for people whose political views are to step on other people’s heads. It is not about chastising software developers whose software is serving such communities. But it’s definitely about not having here people who encourage such unwanted values that are both contrary to the W3C CEPC and an ethics respectful of others.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/42">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/42</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2021 23:40:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1453-42</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453.rss">Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[Sebastian]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <blockquote>
<p>the policy will enter into force after a week (  February 9, 2021 )</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think the first step should be to make it one more week.<br>
Apart from making clear about</p>
<blockquote>
<p>downstream users</p>
</blockquote>
<p>personally I will talk about technical improvements too tomorrow with some others.<br>
Remember what<br>
<a class="mention" href="/u/cristinadelisle">@CristinaDeLisle</a><br>
said in SocialCG:<br>
“so when you as an admin were peering with another instance you are showing  your set of values, and if that other instance believes that they are sharing those values, that instance can peer with you”<br>
If we would have a minimum set of values like human rights, I think, it could help technical.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/41">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/41</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2021 21:19:12 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1453-41</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453.rss">Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Thank you. Yes, this point has been clearly made. I feel it needs no further repeating, only improving.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/40">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/40</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2021 20:38:49 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1453-40</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453.rss">Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[kaniini]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="aschrijver" data-post="38" data-topic="1453">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/aschrijver/40/278_2.png" class="avatar"> aschrijver:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>From my understanding everyone is in agreement (but anyone pls chime in if they see it differently) that the effort to <em>‘provide community safety and ensuring community health’</em> - part of which in form of a policy, CoC, diversity statement, or whatever we agree it to be - is indeed scoped <em>exclusively</em> to SocialCG, SocialHub and affiliated sites plus repositories.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>The problem is that while the intent is that the policy statement be scoped to projects affiliating with SocialCG, it is phrased in such a way that projects are responsible for their downstream users, which they have no control over.</p>
<p>Mastodon can’t control the fact that counter.social, Gab and dozens of alt-right instances use their software.</p>
<p>Pleroma can’t control the fact that KiwiFarms, Spinster, and dozens of alt-right instances use their software.</p>
<p>The policy statement as presently required would require Mastodon and Pleroma to reject all forms of contribution from those groups, including security-impacting bug reports, lest falling in violation of the policy statement, and thus being exposed for punitive actions from the SocialCG admin team.</p>
<p>This is <em>completely absurd</em>, but it is how the policy statement is worded, and as a result concern trolls will demand it be applied that way.</p>
<p>Until and unless there is explicit recognition of the boundary between SocialCG and project autonomy, I will not agree to this policy statement and I encourage all other developers to also reject it.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/39">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/39</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2021 20:34:33 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1453-39</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453.rss">Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p><a class="mention" href="/u/kaniini">@kaniini</a>, I find myself once again in agreement with most of what you say, and I have argued in similar direction in other conversations.</p>
<p>From my understanding everyone is in agreement (but anyone pls chime in if they see it differently) that the effort to <em>‘provide community safety and ensuring community health’</em> - part of which in form of a policy, CoC, diversity statement, or whatever we agree it to be - is indeed scoped <em>exclusively</em> to SocialCG, SocialHub and affiliated sites plus repositories.</p>
<p>I’ve also argued that - though technology is not neutral, and this community not entirely apolitical - we should try to be as neutral as possible, but with clear values and boundaries than cannot be crossed (without consequences, moderation action, etc.)</p>
<p>Because after all - and this may also need to be better defined - we are a community hub that exists for the purpose of:</p>
<ol>
<li>Evolving ActivityPub / Fediverse technology standards and practices, and the adoption of these by developers.</li>
<li>Discussing / researching / improving / advocating Fediverse culture, social structure and new appliances.</li>
</ol>
<p>(I know that most people currently in this community joined on the premise of point 1. Positioning is open for discussion, OT here)</p>
<p>Now as for the reason of some of the points in the policy that led to most discussion. A not-so-hypothetical case (because it happened) where the project of a member itself led to controversy, multiple people expressing concerns and one other leaving the community (but returning when seeing this effort).</p>
<p>Think of a case where the imagery used in the project itself (e.g. project logo, opengraph images + description, names used, etc.) does not conform to community values. So by even pasting a link into a forum post one would cross the line.</p>
<p>(I think in the particular case that we dealt with, it was debatable whether the action was warranted, but notwithstanding that fact people were feeling really uncomfortable / unsafe. So action was taken)</p>
<p><strong>Edit</strong>:</p>
<p>I forgot to mention that related to point 2. above, an example of discussion within scope of SocialHub imho is a topic I created yesterday, namely: <a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/improving-fediverse-culture-and-social-behavior/1397" class="inline-onebox">Improving fediverse culture and social behavior</a>. The various tracks to achieve this improvement boil down to technical solutions and advocacy approaches.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/38">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/38</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2021 19:20:43 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1453-38</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453.rss">Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[kaniini]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="rhiaro" data-post="32" data-topic="1453">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/rhiaro/40/712_2.png" class="avatar"> rhiaro:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>We are hoping to have a loose statement of values and trust in the discretion of the chairs and (collectively not individually) forum moderators, rather than try to define a set of hard and fast rules.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Unfortunately the proposal as presently stated is not a collection of positive rights, but instead a collection of obligations for project managers to consider carefully.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="rhiaro" data-post="32" data-topic="1453">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/rhiaro/40/712_2.png" class="avatar"> rhiaro:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>The idea here is to put out a statement that reassures members of this community that they are safe.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>If the idea is to publish a diversity statement, then publish a diversity statement, not a policy statement which imposes undue burden on projects which are already struggling with manpower issues.</p>
<p>In this sense, you can do that by writing a statement such as:</p>
<hr>
<p>ActivityPub is a critical protocol facilitating interoperability in a diverse network of participating instances.  Accordingly, as stewards of ActivityPub, SocialCG affirms that all are welcome to a technical community free of harassment.  We recognize that disparities are present in the technical industry at large and strive to build a more open, inclusive and democratic Social Web.  This means that behavior from participants which is not aligned with this statement is unwelcome.  In those scenarios, SocialCG reserves the right to remove access to SocialCG resources.</p>
<hr>
<p>The last thing I would like to say is that policies as the proposed policy is presently stated are formulated with good intentions, but then ultimately become utilized (due to their vagueness) against marginalized people that other stakeholders disagree with.</p>
<p>The USA Patriot Act was created to enable investigation and criminal prosecution against supporters of the Al Qaeda terror organization.  However, in reality, most uses of the USA Patriot Act involved surveillance of anti-war protestors or people related to anti-war protestors.</p>
<p>It is important when formulating policy to consider how people down the road may abuse that policy to their own ends.</p>
<p>As presently stated, this policy extends guilt-by-association (and thus the possibility of punitive action) to project developers who have no actual control over what end-users do.  It is possible to achieve the goals of the policy statement by rewriting it in a way that does not impose this obligation on downstreams.  Doing so is critically important if SocialCG is to be seen as the legitimate steward of ActivityPub.</p>
<p>If this policy goes into force without substantive rework, please delete my account at that time.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/37">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/37</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2021 17:20:45 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1453-37</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453.rss">Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[kaniini]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Another hypothetical situation.</p>
<p>Say Gab comes back and reimplements ActivityPub, and then finds a security flaw in the way ActivityPub is specified.  Should SocialCG ignore this report because it came from Gab?</p>
<p>I think it is important to consider how mixing politics into a technical community might be harmful for the technical output of a technical community.</p>
<p>If we find ourselves rejecting security reports or useful technical discussion simply because it came from a pariah, then we are ultimately harming the marginalized people the policy is trying to improve the safety of, by exposing them to security issues due to ignoring them because they came from a pariah.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/36">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/36</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2021 17:08:10 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1453-36</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453.rss">Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[kaniini]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="how" data-post="33" data-topic="1453">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/how/40/94_2.png" class="avatar"> how:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>But if Mastodon developers are here, and Gab developers are not, there is a good reason.<br>
The idea is to prevent hostile disruption, not to chastise AP developers. If you can see it as a statement of good faith, as a <em>positive right</em> (I think this is the issue at play here, that European right and U.S. right come from entirely different places, the latter leading to considering ‘most draconian interpretations’ while the former leading to consider the ‘spirit of the law’), then you might reconsider…</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>The reason Gab never came here is because they didn’t care about ActivityPub in the first place.  They just wanted access to Mastodon’s ecosystem of apps.</p>
<p>From the perspective of somebody who has poured thousands of hours of time into ActivityPub, this requires risk analysis.  When you are analyzing a proposal for risk, you must assume the most draconian interpretation possible: hope for the best, prepare for the worst.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="how" data-post="33" data-topic="1453">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/how/40/94_2.png" class="avatar"> how:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>But you can still make some of them feel they’d rather use another software by refusing to normalize their oppressive presence in your community.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I would rather determine what presences are tolerable in <em>my</em> community based on my own judgement instead of having people who are not part of <em>my</em> community making the decision for me.  I have already drawn the lines in the sand I am comfortable with, but this policy proposal, as presently stated, would require a different posture.</p>
<p>Like with software licenses, we cannot assess risk based on what the current moderation team says their interpretation of the policy is – we must go by what the actual statement says.</p>
<p>Please limit the scope of this proposal to interactions with SocialCG only.  If the intention is to meddle in how downstream projects run their communities, then when compared to the value of this community, non-participation is more fruitful.</p>
<p>We are adults, capable of making appropriate decisions for our communities, we do not need the threat of SocialCG expulsion as part of that process.</p>
<p>For the Web and the Social Web to be healthy, a wide variety of political views must be tolerated.  No, this does not mean that we need to tolerate white supremacy or nationalism, or even work with those who do, but it does mean that we need to respect the boundaries of downstream projects.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="how" data-post="33" data-topic="1453">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/how/40/94_2.png" class="avatar"> how:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I think a project has some control over their communities: forks or parallel projects only count as your community if you’re happy with collaborating with them. If you exclude them because of their ethics you will have “made a good faith effort to discourage such behaviours.”</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Lets look at a hypothetical situation.</p>
<p>Say KiwiFarms downloads and installs your fediverse software for their instance, and then they find a problem with the software and open a bug.  Under this policy, as presently stated, fixing the bug, or really doing anything other than banning them from the bug tracker, would count as collaboration, and the developers would then be in violation of the policy.</p>
<p>This is a problem because while KiwiFarms might have hit the hypothetical bug, other users are as well.</p>
<p>What if it is a security bug that is harming users?  Should we wait until a different user reports the bug?  What if they include a patch?  Should we reject the patch and waste time writing a new one in a way that they cannot claim copyright on?</p>
<p>Why does SocialCG feel it is appropriate to force projects to evaluate these questions?  If we are forced to evaluate these questions, the answer becomes clear: replace SocialCG with something else that does not force us to evaluate these questions.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="how" data-post="33" data-topic="1453">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/how/40/94_2.png" class="avatar"> how:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>The ACM ethics board</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>The original point I was making here is that the ACM ethics board provides due process, meaning that the accused has the right to defend themselves from the allegations made against them.  This protects everyone involved from abuse, and is something lacking in most of these policies, including this one.</p>
<p>However…</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="how" data-post="33" data-topic="1453">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/how/40/94_2.png" class="avatar"> how:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>involves “non-discrimination” against… <em>military status</em></p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I find the fact that you find that distasteful concerning.  In many countries, marginalized people wind up joining the military because they are poor and joining the military allows them to build a career and thus gain upward mobility.  To discriminate against a person simply because they chose to take what options were available to them for upward mobility is disturbing, especially when, again, at least in the US, the military is the primary path for upward mobility for those living below the poverty line.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="how" data-post="33" data-topic="1453">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/how/40/94_2.png" class="avatar"> how:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>If you think the policy is against you, I certainly misunderstood your politics, <a class="mention" href="/u/kaniini">@kaniini</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>It’s not against <em>my</em> politics personally, but it is against my philosophy towards the scope and role of SocialCG as steward of ActivityPub.  I believe, strongly, that ActivityPub is for all who want to use it (including Gab), and that this position results in a strong, robust, democratic Social Web.</p>
<p>Does SocialCG have an obligation to promote the software created by those platforms?  Of course not, but honestly, should SocialCG be promoting <em>any</em> software at all?</p>
<p>Fight nazis in the streets, not by conscripting developers into fighting them for you.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="how" data-post="33" data-topic="1453">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/how/40/94_2.png" class="avatar"> how:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Let’s find ways to clarify that developers are not responsible for downstream usage, but also that <em><strong>community members flagging instances, users</strong></em></p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>In the first part of this sentence, you agree that developers are not responsible for downstream instances, but then (emphasis added) claim that the root of my concern is a legitimate scope of the proposed policy statement.  You cannot have it both ways.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="how" data-post="33" data-topic="1453">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/how/40/94_2.png" class="avatar"> how:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>if a developer is called upon that, for example, his new contributor is part of an organization promoting racism, then he should do something about associating with them, because this is in his reach.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>See the previous KiwiFarms scenario.</p>
<p>As “contributor” is not defined, we must assume that end-user bug reports (possibly with patches) are contributions.  I want to write code and merge patches, not do background checks on potential contributors’ political beliefs.</p>
<p>Society has become hyper-polarized, and this proposal and everything leading up to this proposal are a result of that.  It is important to think about why this has happened if we wish to champion an open, democratic Social Web, which is my primary interest, not litigation of a contributor’s personal beliefs.</p>
<p>If I determine I don’t want to collaborate with someone, I am capable of making that determination without SocialCG telling me who I can or cannot collaborate with.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="how" data-post="33" data-topic="1453">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/how/40/94_2.png" class="avatar"> how:</div>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>The scope is the SocialCG and the SocialHub.</strong> It may affect the Fediverse positively but we’re not a State with an army, you know.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>If the scope is SocialCG and SocialHub, then why does it matter who uses or contributes to the downstream project?</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/35">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/35</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2021 16:39:24 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1453-35</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453.rss">Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[Sebastian]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Thank you<br>
<a class="mention" href="/u/rhiaro">@rhiaro</a><br>
and<br>
<a class="mention" href="/u/how">@how</a></p>
<p>for clarifications and taking the time!</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/34">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453/34</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2021 12:28:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1453-34</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/policy-proposal-socialhub-community-values/1453.rss">Policy Proposal: SocialHub Community Values</source>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
