<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</title>
    <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353</link>
    <description>ActivityStreams has defined and standardized a set of Social concepts, that has given rise to the _Microblogging-oriented_ Fediverse we have today. It worked great to integrate diverse microblogging apps, model lightweight discussion threads, give Likes and Boosts, etc. It does not work so great when squeezing all kinds of entirely different apps into this business domain to facilitate interoperability.

&gt; **Threat**: Stretching the applicability of currently available Social concepts too much results in semantic incompatibilities

To a man with only a hammer, everything looks like a nail. &quot;Yeah, this must be an `as:Note` if you want to federate.&quot; and later on we&#39;ll find that &quot;Hey, my `as:Note` is not your `as:Note`.&quot; and clients will have a hard time making sense of it all. Additionally:

&gt; **Threat**: Sticking to mostly Microblogging domain, not benefiting from Linked Data versatility, means we are easily disrupted.

One new ActivityStreams type we are starting to explore and adopt is the `as:Group` and there is [not yet consensus](https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/groups-implementation/591) how it should be implemented in a compatible way.

But what I notice is that - in many cases - it is more than merely a Group actor we are trying to model. It is part of a larger domain.

&gt; **Observation**: We are trying to model Community domains instead of merely Groups.

Communities are _everywhere_ in our society and we all participate in many different ones at the same time. They are more than simply groups, and often have intricate and complex social organization structures.

This forum, and all Discourse forums for that matter, also define a Community, which consists of the forum members. Many other softwares (like e.g. the new and innovative [PubPub](https://www.pubpub.org/) Collaborative Publishing platform) also are community oriented. Are the new Fediverse applications that investigate using `as:Group` type also actually defining broader community concepts? If they do then each of these projects has at least one thing in common. They all:

- **Reinvent the wheel of how a Community should be defined**

And as a result all of these will be incompatible with each other, creating community islands that may never share features and members of other communities / community-based softwares. Where they do share, the integrations will be bolt-ons via bridges and adapters.

As  part of my Fediverse advocacy and setting up [Fediverse Futures](https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/c/fediversity/fediverse-futures/58) initiative I was making the case to both Discourse and PubPub that **Community Has No Boundary**. See the discussions I started for more background:

- [Community has no boundary: Discourse-as-a-Fabric](https://meta.discourse.org/t/174578)
- [Federating PubPub. Community Has No Boundary](https://github.com/pubpub/pubpub/discussions/1249)

But I now realize that I was advocating on an application-by-application basis, and this is a common issue. The question is, shouldn&#39;t we avoid all this duplicate work and the incompatibility?

&gt; **Opportunity**: Standardize a set of common Community concepts as an extension of ActivityStreams / ActivityPub.

Besides talking community there are currently many discussion on adopting more powerful Moderation tools for Fediverse instances. The outcome of these discussion may lead to the adoption of one or more [Fediverse Enhancement Proposals](https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/c/activitypub/fep/54).

&gt; **Question**: If Moderation FEP&#39;s are adopted, should they be based on current ActivityStreams model, or part of a Community domain?

## Standardizing a Community domain?

There are many ways to approach defining Community in a standard way. The definition can focus on just the organizational aspects, or on the complete model of how communities are usually represented in online web interfaces. I don&#39;t know what the best approach is in this regard, though I am in favor to focus on organizational structures first.

&gt; **Discussion topic**: Do you see the merits in defining a Community domain, and if so then what should it contain?

I will present some prior work I found that may inspire the discussion.

### Sociocracy 3.0: Evolve Effective Collaboration At Any Scale

That a community organization structure is more than just a group is very well demonstrated by [Sociocracy 3.0](https://sociocracy30.org/). This CC-BY-SA pattern library that advertises itself as &quot;free social technology for growing agile and resilient organizations&quot;. Here are group structures supported by it:

![Sociocracy organization structures](upload://5QS8ATshAct5zxrjtGuMaSKU2bT.jpeg)

The group structures lend themselves well to model communities, but the pattern library itself defines many organization patterns / different domains that can be modeled on top of them. Here&#39;s the overview of its patterns:

![Sociocracy pattern library](upload://cGEyQZOdOltjxJha3a2SZ0jTpvR.png)

**Important**: The idea of the pattern library is that you only adopt what you need. Nothing less, nothing more.

### SIOC: Semantically-Interlinked Online Communities

SIOC defines an entire range of RDF classes on how communities might be represented online.

On the [Fedeproxy](https://fedeproxy) forum of @dachary someone [pointed out](https://forum.fedeproxy.eu/t/fedeproxy-great-case-study-for-fediverse-futures/44/3) the [SIOC project](http://sioc-project.org/) linked data ontologies. This is an example of a Forum-oriented model that can be defined based on the ontology (though it lacks SIOC classes like `Community` and `Thread`):

![semantically-interlinked-online-community-ontology|620x399, 75%](upload://vqlt14OfQyoNRMTE87WvxYY5ebk.png) 

These are some additional classes that can be used (there are more):

![sioc-ontology-types|503x500](upload://bE500h39X11ZjbQfWUYf1BHg8FY.png)

---

**Edit**:

In addition to the above I would like to remark that..

&gt; **Best-practice**: ActivityStreams should be considered more as a **Core Ontology** and not as THE ontology of the Fediverse.</description>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 06:30:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <category>Fediverse Futures</category>
    <atom:link href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
        <title>Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I published the <a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/presenting-fedi-foundation-empowerment-for-socialhub-community/1816">First draft of Fedi Foundation</a> website yesterday, and one the pages I created was:</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/original/2X/d/d6eb1d923f07bf9718277468cfa9e8e262f59d88.ico" class="site-icon" width="15" height="16">
      <a href="https://fediverse.codeberg.page/2021/03/community-has-no-boundary/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fedi.foundation</a>
  </header>
  <article class="onebox-body">
    

<h3><a href="https://fediverse.codeberg.page/2021/03/community-has-no-boundary/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Exploring the «Community Has No Boundary» paradigm</a></h3>

<p>Communities are everywhere in daily life, intricately connected. So why are they so fragmented and isolated online?</p>


  </article>
  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>
  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>This page is just a sketch, but the idea is that the Fedi Foundation site will contain a library of Pattern documents for various domain-specific extensions that can be built on top of ActivityPub. This page already has some text of how that may look like, but should be further extended (as well as refined and with improved layout).</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/29">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/29</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 06:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1353-29</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353.rss">Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Thank you for that information. That model may well be too rigid indeed. It may be because it is mostly still mostly conceptual.</p>
<p>Your mention of Type Objects leads me to bring up something that’s a bit off-topic, though still interesting. I will address this in a separate forum topic in due time.</p>
<h3>
<a name="pattern-libraries-1" class="anchor" href="#pattern-libraries-1"></a>Pattern libraries</h3>
<p>I’ve long been thinking that - as we extend the Fediverse to more and more different domains - we may define reusable solutions / vocab extensions / designs etc. as Patterns that other implementers can relatively easily adopt to create interoperable solutions.</p>
<p>As it happens I was just reading one of Aldo de Moor’s latest papers <a href="https://communitysense.nl/papers/2020_Schuler%20et%20al_New%20Community%20Research%20and%20Action%20Networks.pdf">New Community Research and Action Networks</a> (PDF), which also mentions creating pattern libraries:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>A pattern in this sense is a generalized description of a problem and a solution. And they are called “patterns” because they are repeatable in a general way. The originators of the pattern approach state that each pattern they identified  “…describes  a  problem  which  occurs  over  and  over again  in  our  environment,  and  then  describes  the  core  of  the solution to that problem, in such a way that you can use this solution a  million  times  over  without  ever  using  it  the  same  way twice.”Thus,  patterns  can  be  used  to help  provide  general approaches to problems that can be tailored to specific situations.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Note that <a href="https://patterns.sociocracy30.org/map.html">Sociocracy 3.0</a> mentioned above is a pattern library too. Along with the paper is the <a href="https://www.publicsphereproject.org/patterns/lv">Public Sphere Project</a> pattern library as an example (though these patterns are very generalized).</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/28">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/28</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 22 May 2021 12:47:38 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1353-28</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353.rss">Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[bhaugen]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>How many of the Types in those models could be inferred from records of Interactions?  How many of them are actually Roles?</p>
<p>One of the patterns we’ve seen is using Types for things that change, and then the Type becomes rigid.</p>
<p>For example, we’ve seen more than one model where Agents were either Customers or Suppliers, which meant that the same Agent could not be both. If Agent relationships had Roles, then the same Agent could have more than one Role in relation to another Agent. Moreover, whether an Agent was a Customer or a Supplier or both could be inferred from their history of Interactions. And then some other Interaction could emerge that was neither Customer nor Supplier but something else again.</p>
<p>I would need to get much deeper into that model as used in practice to understand if they are using Types too rigidly or not, but I’m suspicious.</p>
<p>[edited] Another question: in Valueflows, the Roles are user/community-defined Type Objects and more can be added as they emerge. The number of hard-coded Types are minimal.<br>
<a href="https://gameprogrammingpatterns.com/type-object.html" class="onebox" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://gameprogrammingpatterns.com/type-object.html</a></p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/27">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/27</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 22 May 2021 12:16:09 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1353-27</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353.rss">Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Thanks a lot <a class="mention" href="/u/lynnfoster">@lynnfoster</a>!</p>
<p>While you were typing I was too. Re-reading a paper posted before…</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="lynnfoster" data-post="8" data-topic="1353">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/lynnfoster/40/892_2.png" class="avatar"> lynnfoster:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Incidentally this also applies to the names of the relationships between them. For example one group within 2 weeks of implementation changed “member” to “affiliate”. Thus the attempt to keep the standard model as minimal as possible.)</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>The paper offers a full-blown conceptual model, something more related to what I’d like to have in my own future federated app…</p>
<p><img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/original/2X/c/cb4818952d23e8d0f3145aa75a41d7d30bb6c932.jpeg" alt="The community network conceptual model" data-base62-sha1="t0joh1n9w8eTQFlHBfqb17IgAPE" width="550" height="390"></p>
<p>Though I don’t want to move away from finding the minimal definition to work with, the aforementioned <a href="https://www.mdpi.com/2078-2489/9/7/151/htm#sec4-information-09-00151">A Community Network Ontology for Participatory Collaboration Mapping: Towards Collective Impact</a> paper by <a href="https://www.communitysense.nl/author/ademoor/">Aldo de Moor</a> of CommunitySense specifies the entirety of the community concept and for relationships has a number of different types:</p>
<div class="md-table">
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>CONNECTION TYPE CATEGORIES</th>
<th>CASE CONNECTION TYPES</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Association-connections</td>
<td>Member Of (5); Owner Of (2); Beneficiary Of; Has Client; Involved Partner; Research Partner Of; Stakeholder Of</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Involvement-connections</td>
<td>Involved In (15); Organizes (6); Informedness (2); Sponsor Of (2); Responsible Partner;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Access-connections</td>
<td>Supports (3); Used In (2); Enables; Has Capability; Has Resource; Uses</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Production-connections</td>
<td>Strengthens (6); Weakens (6); Has Result (4); Produces (4); Located In (3); Story About (2); Used In (2); Case About; Dialogue; Followed By; Generates; Gives; Has Capability; Has Contract; Country of Origin; Country of Work; Data Source About; Involved Organization; Question/Issue About; Uses; Working On</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Contribution-connections</td>
<td>Contributes To (7); About (5); Aimed At; Has Domain; Has Impact; Has Theme</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Structural-connections</td>
<td>Part Of (16); Related To (3); Type Of</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div><p>Just putting this out there, as maybe when extending our own concepts, we may be entering terrain where the additional semantics may start to make sense. Btw, with what Valueflows already provides a lot of this can already be captured, though less explicitly.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>Update</strong>: Much of what is in the model above I would - for may own purposes - model in separate domains e.g. Governance, Collaboration, etc.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/26">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/26</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 22 May 2021 11:56:29 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1353-26</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353.rss">Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[lynnfoster]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p><a class="mention" href="/u/aschrijver">@aschrijver</a> here are some collected examples of agent relationships in economic networks that have used or are using our old software.  These are all bi-directional because that’s all we supported, although I understand that we need to support uni-directional relationships like Follower.  Hopefully this is answering your question; if you want more or different info, let us know, very happy to talk more about this.</p>
<p>An R&amp;D open value network:<br>
Representative (member)<br>
Sponsor<br>
Donor<br>
Affiliate (member)<br>
TechShop User (member)<br>
FabLab Member (member)<br>
Exchange Firm (sub-organization)<br>
Supplier/Customer (trading partner)<br>
Project (sub-organization)<br>
Custodian (sub-organization)</p>
<p>A local herbal exchange network:<br>
Grower (member)<br>
Harvester (member)<br>
Drying Site (member)<br>
Seller (member)<br>
Administrator (member)</p>
<p>A high school fablab network:<br>
Customer/Supplier (trading partner)<br>
District School (member)<br>
Drop-off Point (member)<br>
Employee<br>
Donor<br>
Member</p>
<p>A network based on a crypto currency:<br>
Coordinator (member)<br>
Participant (member)<br>
Support (member)<br>
Self Employed Member (member)<br>
Customer/Supplier (trading partner)<br>
Local Node (sub-organization)<br>
Child (sub-organization)</p>
<p>A local food network that is a multi-stakeholder co-op:<br>
Farmer (member)<br>
Distributor (member)<br>
Administrator (member)<br>
Processor (member)<br>
Institutional customer (member)</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/25">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/25</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 22 May 2021 11:48:08 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1353-25</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353.rss">Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p><a class="mention" href="/u/lynnfoster">@lynnfoster</a> <a class="mention" href="/u/bhaugen">@bhaugen</a> do you have more good examples to look at of different relationship networks you encountered in practice?</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/24">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/24</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 22 May 2021 04:40:07 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1353-24</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353.rss">Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I follow-up to the <a href="https://friend.camp/@darius/106067444293032880">Neighborhood discussion</a> with <a class="mention" href="/u/darius">@darius</a> I posted a great article I found (co-authored it appeared by a collegue of Darius). The article is interesting from two aspects:</p>
<ul>
<li>First of all for game design, as the title suggests (anyone apply it in a <a href="https://spritelyproject.org/#fantasary">Fantasary</a> PoC for <a class="mention" href="/u/cwebber">@cwebber</a>? <img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/images/emoji/twitter/wink.png?v=9" title=":wink:" class="emoji" alt=":wink:"> )</li>
<li>But in a larger context the concepts can be applied to Communities (i.e. this topic)</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<h2><a href="https://www.projecthorseshoe.com/reports/featured/ph18r8.htm">Design Practices for Human Scale Online Games [ and Communities! ]</a></h2>
<p>When researching what it meant to make human-scale systems, we found several key concepts from social psychology. Each provides a set of constraints for social design. <strong>Social game design operates within the physical and mental constraints of the human animal</strong>, so it pays to understand these constraints and build them into our designs.</p>
</blockquote>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/23">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/23</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2021 06:57:19 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1353-23</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353.rss">Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I had a chat with <a class="mention" href="/u/darius">@darius</a> based on <a href="https://friend.camp/@darius/106067444293032880">interesting toot</a> on how “local only” posting contributes to community vitality, and Darius mentioned planning an extension to <a href="https://github.com/hometown-fork/hometown/wiki">Hometown</a> to add support for “Neighborhoods”. Very interesting concept, and related to this topic:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Friend Camp has about 50 active users and I just noticed we have more than half a million posts here since August 2018! I mean that’s 11 a day per person on average but still. That seems wild to me.</p>
<p>Last I checked something like 75% of our posts are unfederated. That’s still 125 thousand posts sent to the fediverse. I think local-only posting increases the vitality of community, increasing the volume of overall activity, and contributing more to the fediverse than a less vital instance would.</p>
<p>In other words: if Friend Camp never had local only posting, we would not have cohered as a community, and we would have contributed far less to the fediverse as a whole than we do with the ability to post unfederated.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Here is the a GH gist outlining the Neighborhood idea:</p>
<blockquote>
<h2><a href="https://gist.github.com/dariusk/53cf4c52d499304c53df4a3839ad0e00">Hometown Neighborhoods</a></h2>
<p>I am now working on a third layer of communication: a medium-trust layer. This layer (which is actually pretty high trust as far as these things go) is called a “neighborhood”. Let’s say that the users of coolpeople.social have decided that the users of awesomepeople.social are really amazing and they want to share more with them. The coolpeople and the awesomepeople mutually decide to join a “neighborhood”, which means that neighborhood-level posts on either server can be seen by everyone on both servers.</p>
<p>This means that when you make a post on Hometown there will be three choices in a little dropdown toggle:</p>
<ul>
<li>local (just the people on your server)</li>
<li>neighborhood (just the people on your server and a small group of other servers)</li>
<li>federated (the whole world)</li>
</ul>
<p>[…] I do plan to publish neighborhoods as <strong>a specification</strong>.</p>
</blockquote>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/22">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/22</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 21:10:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1353-22</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353.rss">Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote group-smithereen" data-username="grishka" data-post="20" data-topic="1353">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/grishka/40/196_2.png" class="avatar"> grishka:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I’m very much against perpetuating such legacy workarounds, like “mention this account and it boosts”, to make conceptually incompatible systems compatible at the expense of UX.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Yes, I agree with you on that. There shouldn’t be a “compatibility-at-all-costs” and cramming everything in a microblogging jacket. But still an investigation of current practices is in order followed by considerations of adopting what makes sense.</p>
<p>The standardization does not necessarily lead to the ugliness, and regardless of the beauty and elegancy of any extension, implementers always can make the decision to mold stuff in their project so it microblogs, however awkwardly.</p>
<p>Thanks for pointing to the FEP (and for writing it! <img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/images/emoji/twitter/pray.png?v=9" title=":pray:" class="emoji" alt=":pray:">  ). Though I’m not the expert that knows all the AP intrinsics and complexity I may have some useful feedback (need to find some time, though <img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/images/emoji/twitter/woozy_face.png?v=9" title=":woozy_face:" class="emoji" alt=":woozy_face:"> ).</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/21">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/21</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 13 Mar 2021 06:47:18 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1353-21</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353.rss">Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[grishka]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="aschrijver" data-post="19" data-topic="1353">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/aschrijver/40/278_2.png" class="avatar"> aschrijver:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Thinking that whatever this extension should turn out to be it should be backward-compatible, or at least easily mapp-able, to group solutions currently out there in the wild.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Actually, I don’t make any efforts to make it compatible with existing microblogging software. And it indeed isn’t, because it relies heavily on walls. Those that I wrote <a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-400e-publicly-appendable-activitypub-collections/1438">a FEP</a> about.</p>
<p>Mastodon does show a “group” tag next to it, and you can join it (I recognize both <code>Join</code> and <code>Follow</code>), and that’s about it. You can’t interact with it because that requires sending activities that Mastodon knows nothing about.<br>
<div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/original/1X/97ce8fa7e62daf913849e946dfe2dcbce770897a.png" data-download-href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/97ce8fa7e62daf913849e946dfe2dcbce770897a" title="Снимок экрана 2021-03-12 в 17.03.13"><img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/optimized/1X/97ce8fa7e62daf913849e946dfe2dcbce770897a_2_537x500.png" alt="Снимок экрана 2021-03-12 в 17.03.13" data-base62-sha1="lEWEvbcKPVTAAOOM2sNzwWFfagq" width="537" height="500" srcset="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/optimized/1X/97ce8fa7e62daf913849e946dfe2dcbce770897a_2_537x500.png, https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/original/1X/97ce8fa7e62daf913849e946dfe2dcbce770897a.png 1.5x, https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/original/1X/97ce8fa7e62daf913849e946dfe2dcbce770897a.png 2x" data-small-upload="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/optimized/1X/97ce8fa7e62daf913849e946dfe2dcbce770897a_2_10x10.png"><div class="meta"><svg class="fa d-icon d-icon-far-image svg-icon" aria-hidden="true"><use xlink:href="#far-image"></use></svg><span class="filename">Снимок экрана 2021-03-12 в 17.03.13</span><span class="informations">656×610 40.1 KB</span><svg class="fa d-icon d-icon-discourse-expand svg-icon" aria-hidden="true"><use xlink:href="#discourse-expand"></use></svg></div></a></div></p>
<p>And, IMO, that’s fine. You can’t exactly reconcile all the problems that arise when you try to interoperate disparate software. People usually understand that. You can’t make a microblogging server participate in a forum network without it all looking ugly to the user on the microblogging side and to the developer on the forum side. I’m very much against perpetuating such legacy workarounds, like “mention this account and it boosts”, to make conceptually incompatible systems compatible at the expense of UX.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/20">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/20</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Mar 2021 14:13:14 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1353-20</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353.rss">Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p><a class="mention" href="/u/grishka">@grishka</a> in <a class="hashtag" href="/c/software/smithereen/52">#<span>software:smithereen</span></a> has implemented true <code>as:Group</code> support. Thinking that whatever this extension should turn out to be it should be backward-compatible, or at least easily mapp-able, to group solutions currently out there in the wild.</p>
<p>Right now for Smithereen a decision has to be made how to represent the role of group members, where there can be Admins and Moderators. Quoting from <a href="https://mastodon.social/@grishka/105873629796506302">this toot</a> and subtoot:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/original/1X/2d2643b353d30af64cf6fefef901d93cb49bceaf.png" alt="smithereen-group-roles" data-base62-sha1="6rpsYDqQ7oq997YMGBlWjEh7tvx" width="245" height="177"></p>
<p>Still not sure how to represent these group admins in <a href="https://mastodon.social/tags/ActivityPub">#ActivityPub</a> objects tho. PeerTube uses a similar construct for its channels and uses <code>attributedTo</code> to link a channel with its managing user. But I can have multiple admins per group, that’s the point <img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/images/emoji/twitter/thinking.png?v=9" title=":thinking:" class="emoji" alt=":thinking:"></p>
</blockquote>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/19">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/19</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Mar 2021 06:39:08 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1353-19</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353.rss">Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[lynnfoster]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <blockquote>
<p>This is how <code>Relationship</code> object is defined in ActivityStreams</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Yes thanks, we took inspiration from AS naming there, hoping for some merging some time. <img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/images/emoji/twitter/slightly_smiling_face.png?v=9" title=":slightly_smiling_face:" class="emoji" alt=":slightly_smiling_face:"></p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="aschrijver" data-post="17" data-topic="1353">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/aschrijver/40/278_2.png" class="avatar"> aschrijver:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>The <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/activitystreams-vocabulary/#dfn-relationship-term" rel="noopener nofollow ugc"> <code>relationship</code> </a> property has some <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/activitystreams-vocabulary/#connections" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">additional info</a> in that the relationshp defines an RDF-like <code>subject predicate object</code> pairing, where the property is the predicate and defined as Object. So it might hold the URI to a `vf:AgentRelationshipRole I would think.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Seems like that could work.  As you point out, the range is Object, so it seems intended to be defined pretty generally.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/18">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/18</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 09 Mar 2021 19:15:29 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1353-18</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353.rss">Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group quote-modified" data-username="lynnfoster" data-post="16" data-topic="1353">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/lynnfoster/40/892_2.png" class="avatar"> lynnfoster:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Yes. Hopefully not too OT, but wouldn’t it be wonderful if we could create a separate spec for people, organizations, groups, their relationships, user accounts, etc.? […]  I speak only theoretically, but would love to try it. Another day though I guess.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Fully with you on that! It’d be <img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/images/emoji/twitter/heart.png?v=9" title=":heart:" class="emoji" alt=":heart:"> lovely, and much needed too.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="lynnfoster" data-post="16" data-topic="1353">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/lynnfoster/40/892_2.png" class="avatar"> lynnfoster:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>But I could be wrong, my head doesn’t wrap well around tech with agency…</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>In the software development pipelines example with which I updated my previous post (Github as example), developers / IT orgs integrate services without ever contacting a human at the organization that provides them, possibly even without ever visiting the organization website.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="lynnfoster" data-post="16" data-topic="1353">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/lynnfoster/40/892_2.png" class="avatar"> lynnfoster:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Sorry about the UML / relational representation, hope that communicates OK</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Quite okay, familiar with it.</p>
<p>This is how <code>Relationship</code> object is defined in ActivityStreams:</p>
<pre><code class="lang-json">{
  "@context": "https://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams",
  "summary": "Sally is an acquaintance of John",
  "type": "Relationship",
  "subject": {
    "type": "Person",
    "name": "Sally"
  },
  "relationship": "http://purl.org/vocab/relationship/acquaintanceOf",
  "object": {
    "type": "Person",
    "name": "John"
  }
}
</code></pre>
<p>The <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/activitystreams-vocabulary/#dfn-relationship-term"><code>relationship</code></a> property has some <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/activitystreams-vocabulary/#connections">additional info</a> in that the relationshp defines an RDF-like <code>subject predicate object</code> pairing, where the property is the predicate and defined as Object. So it might hold the URI to a `vf:AgentRelationshipRole I would think.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="lynnfoster" data-post="16" data-topic="1353">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/lynnfoster/40/892_2.png" class="avatar"> lynnfoster:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I’m speaking without any experience on an AP implementation, so may be totally off base.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I am also not where I want/need to be in terms of experience level, and hope other experts will jump into the thread <img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/images/emoji/twitter/blush.png?v=9" title=":blush:" class="emoji" alt=":blush:"></p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/17">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/17</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2021 21:36:37 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1353-17</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353.rss">Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[lynnfoster]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <blockquote>
<p>ValueFlows vs. AS/AP compatibility will probably mostly be defined in terms of model equivalency</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Yes.  Hopefully not too OT, but wouldn’t it be wonderful if we could create a separate spec for people, organizations, groups, their relationships, user accounts, etc.?  That everyone could use?  Seems like a lot of people are working on this piece of their particular puzzle, you mention some, also seeing it in Holochain and Hylo for example.  And it seems like if people could create person-centric apps where the person could have an identity outside and across user accounts and different distributed technologies (fediverse, solid, holochain, etc.), it could solve a lot of problems relating the real world to applications.  And groups could have a globally unique identity too.  I speak only theoretically, but would love to try it.  Another day though I guess.</p>
<p>[edit: I posted this without seeing the last 2 comments, so I am behind the discussion around bots.]</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Since you are not dealing with the Organization directly but only with its Service, you might consider the service to be the economic agent</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think of it as who is responsible in the real world.  But I could be wrong, my head doesn’t wrap well around tech with agency…</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You might have a situation where an Organization offers many such services with different payment plans.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In that statement, the Organization is the agent, the services are economic resources, with a little-r.  And there would be some agent behind the SaaS itself I would think, even if it is a consortium of some kind.  And agents fulfilling could be different agents.  But again, very willing to be wrong as use cases develop.</p>
<p>Moving on to thinking about relationship models, this is what VF has now, just as food for thought.  It borrowed some of the naming from AS, but needed a few more pieces.  And could be changed to be more AP friendly by figuring out the whole agent/actor mapping piece.  (Sorry about the UML / relational representation, hope that communicates OK.)</p>
<p><img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/original/1X/06eca311286dd4af94b961ec7abb11a9ce92e3e2.png" alt="Agent" data-base62-sha1="ZfR98pzodUiwPBAcM6N0az7Cp4" width="364" height="341"></p>
<p>I think User Account (or similar) would be connected to Person, one person can have many user accounts, whether across instances, across technologies, or over time.</p>
<p>The Role Behavior gives some “hard-coded” types of roles, thus freeing up the AgentRelationshipRole to be completely user defined otherwise.  It would be something like “member”, “sub-organization”, “trading partner”, maybe a few others, the list is not well defined yet.</p>
<p>In AP, maybe the agent relationship roles in use by a group or organization could define new collections, similar to the followers collection in the spec?  Or maybe just standard defined collections for the behavior roles, which can be agreed on?  I’m speaking without any experience on an AP implementation, so may be totally off base.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/16">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/16</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2021 21:08:15 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1353-16</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353.rss">Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="bhaugen" data-post="14" data-topic="1353">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/bhaugen/40/104_2.png" class="avatar"> bhaugen:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>An example where the bot created the economic resources unaided by humans? At this stage of AI development, there’s always some humans in the chain.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I was referring to things that are not (AI-driven) bots. If I obtain a SaaS service that auto-bills me on each API call then, there’s no human involved in the chain, and - though it goes to the back-end Organization in the end - payment is even handled in the transaction (e.g. via a Stripe payment provider, also a SaaS service, that is integrated in the exchange). The value comes from the Service directly.</p>
<p>(Question is more related to VF, because in many occasions it is not directly community-related. But I guess there might be an ‘accounting’ bot that reports on SaaS transactions that occurred → on Github you have a bunch of services that interact with issues and pull requests, that might be examples of this)</p>
<p><strong>Update</strong>:</p>
<p>I don’t know too much about VF, so this may be off the mark, but…</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="bhaugen" data-post="14" data-topic="1353">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/bhaugen/40/104_2.png" class="avatar"> bhaugen:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>An example where the bot created the economic resources unaided by humans?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Github is actually a good example. It offers various ways for 3rd-party service integrations, most important is <a href="https://github.com/features/actions">Github Actions</a>, and online marketplace. Many of these are paid services. Now suppose that Github handled the payment via a single subscription, or it offered an enterprise plan providing free access to a portfolio of popular 3rd-party services.</p>
<p>You’d have (fictitious) <code>dependabot</code>, <code>stalebot</code>, <code>qualitybot</code> etc. that automatically jump in during your development workflow at specific stages and do their work. No human intervention, apart from initial activation of the bot and maybe some config settings.</p>
<p>The Organization that you pay (Github) is different from the 3 Organizations that provide the bot. Furthermore, suppose you also have Gitlab which doesn’t offer this package directly, you might want to obtain these bots from their separate providers. I have to read up to VF, though, because if “economic agent” means ‘where-the-money-goes-to’, my argument is void <img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/images/emoji/twitter/slight_smile.png?v=9" title=":slight_smile:" class="emoji" alt=":slight_smile:"></p>
<p>(PS. There are a <a href="https://github.com/DopplerHQ/awesome-bots">whole bunch of bots</a> providing interesting services)</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/15">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/15</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2021 20:13:08 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1353-15</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353.rss">Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[bhaugen]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group quote-modified" data-username="aschrijver" data-post="12" data-topic="1353">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/aschrijver/40/278_2.png" class="avatar"> aschrijver:</div>
<blockquote>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="lynnfoster" data-post="11" data-topic="1353">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/lynnfoster/40/892_2.png" class="avatar"> lynnfoster:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I don’t think we can say “the bot made me do it”.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>It is broader than bots.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>This is a half-baked thought. Will bake it more as we continue this and related discussions.</p>
<p>I think for a bot or a service that participate in economic activities, the Economic Agent is the agent that runs the bot or service, and, (for example), if the bot or service provides economic resources, the “real” provider is the agent that the resources came from.</p>
<p>An example where the bot created the economic resources unaided by humans? At this stage of AI development, there’s always some humans in the chain. When the robots can design and create their own robots, we have hit the Singularity, and all bets are off. But not yet…</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/14">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/14</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2021 20:01:09 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1353-14</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353.rss">Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="bhaugen" data-post="10" data-topic="1353">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/bhaugen/40/104_2.png" class="avatar"> bhaugen:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>This is a sidelight to the main topic, but every economic network we’ve seen is also a social network.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I like this insight. I was clear to me in the real-world meaning, but also nice that it applies to online social media use cases as well.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/13">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/13</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2021 19:52:48 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1353-13</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353.rss">Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="lynnfoster" data-post="11" data-topic="1353">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/l/eb8c5e/40.png" class="avatar"> lynnfoster:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>If I understand you correctly, you fall back to the Organization. Services (the kind that are actors) for example I don’t think are economic agents. I don’t think we can say “the bot made me do it”.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>It is broader than bots. Any SaaS service counts. I.e. invoking an API on a paid subscription plan or a pay-per-use. You might have a situation where an Organization offers many such services with different payment plans. Or even theoretically that the service of some standardized API can be fulfilled by multiple back-end parties (don’t have examples of that though). Since you are not dealing with the Organization directly but only with its Service, you might consider the service to be the economic agent, and when obtaining multiple services it is easier to distinguish them.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="lynnfoster" data-post="11" data-topic="1353">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/l/eb8c5e/40.png" class="avatar"> lynnfoster:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Organizations can be community members, if allowed by the community. But yeah, we think there are Person roles and permissions in an Organization that will allow a Person to “act on behalf of” an Organization.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>In this situation the Organization starts to have group-like characteristics too, where the representatives are the real community members. The other case is where the Organization is a single entity and when e.g. posting to it, it is opaque how it is handled within the organisation.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/12">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/12</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2021 19:46:34 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1353-12</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353.rss">Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[lynnfoster]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p><a class="mention" href="/u/aschrijver">@aschrijver</a> wow back.  A few responses; more later.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>If a non-incorporated Community is funded by donations (e.g. via an OpenCollective), is it an economic agent? I think it is.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Yes it is.  Anything that can perform economic activity, including giving/receiving/exchanging resources, or producing/changing resources, is an economic agent.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Given a paid SaaS Service can it be considered an economic agent? Or do you fall-back to the Organization that offers it?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>If I understand you correctly, you fall back to the Organization.  Services (the kind that are actors) for example I don’t think are economic agents.  I don’t think we can say “the bot made me do it”.  But I’m not sure everyone would agree… <a class="mention" href="/u/bhaugen">@bhaugen</a> ?  I can see a place for agents that are ecosystemic possibly, but don’t really know.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>What does it mean if an Organization is community member? Probably only some representatives participate in the community.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Organizations can be community members, if allowed by the community.  But yeah, we think there are Person roles and permissions in an Organization that will allow a Person to “act on behalf of” an Organization.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Shouldn’t VF also generalize to having any agent possibly be an ecomic agent? (Maybe you already do so, idk)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Yes I think so, thanks.  That was what I was trying to accomplish by merging non-agent Groups and agent Organizations somehow - but we don’t need to do it that way, any agent-y thing could be an economic agent just by engaging in economic behavior.  In VF, we haven’t had to worry about it yet because we have only needed to care about economic agents.  When we try to map and interconnect with AP (or any social networking) then we need to think more broadly.  Which is good.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/11">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/11</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2021 19:37:05 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1353-11</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353.rss">Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[bhaugen]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="aschrijver" data-post="9" data-topic="1353">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/aschrijver/40/278_2.png" class="avatar"> aschrijver:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>You shouldn’t consider AS/AP as particular to social-only apps.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>This is a sidelight to the main topic, but every economic network we’ve seen is also a social network. And if their economic and social interactions can be integrated, they work much more smoothly.</p>
<p>For example, these folks <a href="https://learndeep.org/" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://learndeep.org/</a> recruited an engineering college class to fork some of our older economic network software for their high school fablab network, and one of the features they recently added was chat. Everybody went, “yay! now we can chat about this stuff!”</p>
<p>(P.S. that’s why we want to build economic network software on top of social network software.)</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/10">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/10</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2021 11:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1353-10</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353.rss">Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Wow, what a wonderful feedback. I truly <img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/images/emoji/twitter/heart.png?v=9" title=":heart:" class="emoji" alt=":heart:">  love this <a class="mention" href="/u/lynnfoster">@lynnfoster</a>, thank you! I will - with my still very limited expertise on vocab modeling - try to provide some useful additional observations…</p>
<ul>
<li>Keep concepts as low-level as possible in order to achieve greatest versatility in the model.</li>
<li>Many / most concepts can be tailored by means of user-defined classifications.</li>
<li>ValueFlows vs. AS/AP compatibility will probably mostly be defined in terms of model equivalency.
<ul>
<li>(Note: In AS this requires e.g. <code>"type": ["Person", "foaf:Person"]</code> which most apps don’t support currently)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Group is the central idea for this extension. In terms of AS I’d say:</p>
<ul>
<li>An as:Group has members, which can be any concrete class representing any Actor type (this is standards-compliant).</li>
<li>The membership of an Actor is expressed by its roles, and that may use (one or more) as:Relationship.</li>
</ul>
<p>The above already comes a long way, but is a bit different to ValueFlows in the types of actors / agents it allows.</p>
<p>Note that the AS definition of Group (“Represents a formal or informal collective of Actors.”) is already a specialization of the universal concept of Group (“Any Group of Objects”) and does not take roles into account, but also doesn’t define how membership must be modeled, which is fine.</p>
<p>In terms of AP and this Community extension I wonder if a special as:Collection type should be defined to represent membership. If feel followers / following doesn’t cut it. Maybe as:Group has a ‘members’ collection. But it would be quite breaking with what’s out there at present. In current group modeling efforts (e.g. <a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/groups-implementation/591">here</a>), we are trying to fit everything in the existing standard specs with as:Join, as:Follow, etc. (and having no consensus how this should be done interoperatively).</p>
<h2>Some examples</h2>
<h3>Community in software (Discourse)</h3>
<p>Discourse considers itself community software, and I have pitched the <a href="https://meta.discourse.org/t/community-has-no-boundary-discourse-as-a-fabric-ideation-brainstorm/174578">“[discourse] community has no boundary”</a> paradigm there. I’ll use their software (e.g. this forum) as example when looking at various actor types being part of Community (as:Group):</p>
<ul>
<li>First of all one Discourse installation (currently) represents one <strong>Community</strong> (the top-level as:Group).</li>
<li>
<strong>Person</strong> actors are <em>not</em> directly represented, but represented by one or more user accounts they create.
<ul>
<li>OT: Bit of a problem here. At admin level the forum knows something about this, but it might be okay to map accounts directly to Persons. Alternatively there might be an implicit Person that has Relationships representing accounts, which raises new problems. Or Account can be a separate custom Actor type. Or… [feedback welcome]</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<strong>Group</strong> actors exist in Discourse to represent sub-groups of the top-level Community group, and cannot be nested.
<ul>
<li>Communities in general may have <em>nested groups</em> (conceptually <em>staff</em> → <em>moderators</em> → <em>admins</em> are implicitly nested).</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<strong>Application</strong> actors participate in the community too. There’s <code>@system</code> account interaction on behalf of the application.
<ul>
<li>There’s also <code>@discobot</code> community ‘butler’ bot. This can be an Application actor (though Service fits too).</li>
<li>Many softwares with membership concepts have bots, think e.g. IRC. There might a custom Bot actor type.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<strong>Service</strong> actors may be provided by various Discourse plugins, where the service reports / listens to the forum.
<ul>
<li>Think of Github, Discourse, Mattermost, Opencollective integrations.</li>
<li>Some of these are a bit of a stretch. In general I think certain (SaaS) Services can act as full-blown members.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<strong>Organization</strong> actors, like Persons are not directly represented, but there can be organization accounts.</li>
</ul>
<p>It is interesting to think of what would happen if Discourse adopted the “community has no boundaries” paradigm…</p>
<ul>
<li>There would be membership relationships between Communities (instances of discourse).</li>
<li>There’d probably be truly a concept of nested groups to be supported.</li>
<li>There might be additional requirements to define community intersections/overlap (“we only share these categories”).</li>
</ul>
<p>And currently there would be limitations in the way cross-community membership can be defined. Identities are tied to instances and we lack SSO, identity providers, roaming identity or whatever other mechanism to provide this. Solving the Identity problem on fedi would be fantastic, but goes way beyond this topic.</p>
<h3>Real-world communities</h3>
<p>When representing communities as they exist in the real world, things come closer to ValueFlows. In that regard I’m wondering the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>If a non-incorporated Community is funded by donations (e.g. via an OpenCollective), is it an economic agent? I think it is.</li>
<li>Given a paid SaaS Service can it be considered an economic agent? Or do you fall-back to the Organization that offers it?</li>
<li>What does it mean if an Organization is community member? Probably only some representatives participate in the community.</li>
</ul>
<p>Shouldn’t VF also generalize to having any agent possibly be an ecomic agent? (Maybe you already do so, idk)</p>
<hr>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="lynnfoster" data-post="8" data-topic="1353">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/l/eb8c5e/40.png" class="avatar"> lynnfoster:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>That wouldn’t affect social-only networks not using VF</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Just to be sure: You shouldn’t consider AS/AP as particular to social-only apps. Though it is now primarily used and presented for the social space, application is much broader. I make this argument in <a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/positioning-activitypub-de-emphasize-being-part-of-the-fediverse-as-primary-usp/1197" class="inline-onebox">Positioning ActivityPub: De-Emphasize "Being Part of the Fediverse" as primary USP</a> and the <a class="hashtag" href="/c/fediversity/fediverse-futures/58">#<span>fediversity:fediverse-futures</span></a> category is about exploring these broader application / business domains. E.g. <a class="hashtag" href="/c/software/forgefed/60">#<span>software:forgefed</span></a> is an example of a non-social application to extend AS/AP.</p>
<hr>
<p>(PS. In your REA reference the REA Ontology Paper link is dead, here’s <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20200718064638/https://msu.edu/user/mccarth4/Alabama.doc">the latest archive.org</a> [DOC] version)</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/9">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/9</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2021 07:18:02 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1353-9</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353.rss">Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[lynnfoster]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p><strong>TL;DR:</strong> To describe a Community, what is the minimum we need?  We need a Group with a user-defined classification of “Community”.  We need all the Persons (or other Groups) with a relationship to the Group.  These relationships (roles) are also user-defined.</p>
<p><strong>Excrutiating detail</strong></p>
<blockquote>
<p>Valueflows has a pretty minimal set of primitives that allow almost everything to be user-defined. Bonfire extended them a bit based on experience in Moodlenet. <a class="mention" href="/u/lynnfoster">@lynnfoster</a> of Valueflows and <a class="mention" href="/u/mayel">@mayel</a> of Bonfire are discussing how to make it all even more minimal and should have something to report soonish.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Haven’t had a chance to work through this recently with <a class="mention" href="/u/mayel">@mayel</a> .  He’ll be able to speak to implementation details way better than I can.  In the meantime, I’d like to give a short history of what we decided earlier, and why I’d like to change that a bit, as one contribution to the ongoing discussion here.</p>
<p>History:  Valueflows uses foaf:Agent, with subclasses foaf:Person and org:Organization.  VF uses Agent as “economic agent” for its purposes, and has also inherited the name Agent from an ontology called <a href="https://valueflo.ws/appendix/rea.html" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">REA</a> (Resources Events Agents), which it is based on.  ActivityStreams of course has as:Person, as:Organization, as:Group, all of which are actors (there is no actual Actor class, but specific protocol is defined in AP).  Mayel and I decided in an initial discussion of how to map VF and AS (we were thinking of it as extending AP with VF for economic networking) by defining vf:Person and as:Person as equivalent, vf:Organization and as:Organization as equivalent, and using as:Group.  Organization would be defined as having economic agency, and Group would be defined as not having economic agency.   (We did not find the AS definitions to be very helpful.)  In any case, in the mapping, an agent is always an actor, but not all actors are agents.</p>
<p>What I later discovered I don’t like about our earlier decision is that if a non-economic Group decides it wants to start acting as an economic agent, so as an Organization, it now wants a different type.  Not so good in many technologies, and exposes that really economic agency is more a role than a type.</p>
<p>What I do like about our earlier decision is that we added a classification property to Organization and Group that gives users a chance to name and define these for themselves.  So, for this thread topic, people could define an as:Group classifiedAs “Community”, which could come from an existing public taxonomy.  Or not.  (In general, our experience working with different groups/organizations is that it is important to them to be able to name these things for themselves, to express nuance that is important to them.  There are always new ways people name types of groups/organizations - “Distributed Cooperative Organization (DisCO)” or “Open Value Network” come to mind.  Incidentally this also applies to the names of the relationships between them.  For example one group within 2 weeks of implementation changed “member” to “affiliate”. Thus the attempt to keep the standard model as minimal as possible.)</p>
<p>Some general thoughts about what to do: I’d like for VF to be able to keep Agent, but consider the definition more loosely (which foaf does actually).  That wouldn’t affect social-only networks not using VF.  I’d like to have agents (and that kind of actor too) be either a Person or a [some name that covers all agents that are not a person].  That last thing merges Organization and Group.  Really if a Group even has a name, it has something like agency.  Unfortunately, it might be hard to merge those because AS (and FOAF) already has them as separate concepts.</p>
<p>And then more specific kinds would be handled by user-definable classifications, not more classes or types. This is really the important part, we could do this and keep both as:Organization and as:Group, since they are already defined.</p>
<p>This is getting kind of long, I’ll make a separate comment with more thoughts about relationships, and a suggested diagram, probably tomorrow though.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/8">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/8</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 06 Mar 2021 23:37:56 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1353-8</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353.rss">Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="bhaugen" data-post="6" data-topic="1353">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/bhaugen/40/104_2.png" class="avatar"> bhaugen:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>So that means a fairly minimal set of primitives that any community can use to define themselves and their organizational relationships.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Yes, this also has my preference…</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="aschrijver" data-post="1" data-topic="1353">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/aschrijver/40/278_2.png" class="avatar"> aschrijver:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>The definition can focus on <em>just the organizational aspects</em>, or on the complete model of how communities are usually represented in online web interfaces. I don’t know what the best approach is in this regard, though I am in favor to focus on organizational structures first.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>In the above I was just collecting some stuff that is already out there, and that we may borrow from or build upon. If there were an existing vocabulary that we can subset and reuse, then that might be better in terms of standardization than creating something entirely new.</p>
<p>I feel that the ideas behind Sociacracy (though it provides a specific take on organization structure, with double-linking and such) are an attractive starter, i.e.</p>
<ul>
<li>Show the community models as simple diagrams.</li>
<li>Describe how they work in comprehensive short texts.</li>
<li>Make those a pattern library, where you are free to choose from as you expand with additional community concepts.</li>
<li>And give each pattern a vocubulary snippet to adopt.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Update</strong>: Oh, and I think the ability to define relationships between communities, have overlapping cross-sections i.e. the whole “community has no boundaries” paradigm is something to think about. How do you integrate with other communities?</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/7">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/7</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 06 Mar 2021 07:48:34 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1353-7</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353.rss">Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[bhaugen]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I agree with the idea of standardizing on at least enuf community-organization vocabulary so ActivityPubs can interoperate.</p>
<p>But I also agree with the people who want communities to define it themselves.</p>
<p>So that means a fairly minimal set of primitives that any community can use to define themselves and their organizational relationships.</p>
<p>Several of the research findings seem way too prescriptive to me. SIOC, for example.</p>
<p>Valueflows has a pretty minimal set of primitives that allow almost everything to be user-defined. Bonfire extended them a bit based on experience in Moodlenet. <a class="mention" href="/u/lynnfoster">@lynnfoster</a>  of Valueflows and <a class="mention" href="/u/mayel">@mayel</a> of Bonfire are discussing how to make it all even more minimal and should have something to report soonish. I’m pinging them here to suggest that they report in this thread when they are ready.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/6">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/6</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 19:10:01 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1353-6</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353.rss">Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Some other Community-related resources I found …</p>
<blockquote>
<h3><a href="https://www.mdpi.com/2078-2489/9/7/151">A Community Network Ontology for Participatory Collaboration Mapping: Towards Collective Impact</a></h3>
<p><em>“Addressing societal wicked problems requires collaboration across many different community networks. In order for community networks to scale up their collaboration and increase their collective impact, they require a process of inter-communal sensemaking. One way to catalyze that process is by participatory collaboration mapping. In earlier work, we presented the CommunitySensor methodology for participatory mapping and sensemaking within communities. In this article, we extend this approach by introducing a community network ontology that can be used to define a customized mapping language to make sense across communities […]”</em></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<h3><a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/236669552_A_reference_profile_ontology_for_Communities_of_Practice"> A reference profile ontology for Communities of Practice</a></h3>
<p><em>“Communities of Practice (CoP) integrate people in a group in order to learn in a collaborative way. In these communities it is necessary to establish a formal and standardized representation of the interests and the knowledge that emerges from the CoP. With this scenario in mind, this paper presents a reference ontology for a user profile representation in a CoP framework. The main idea of this framework is to realize that a foundation for the semantic web is feasible to aggregate on virtual communities in the context of collaborative learning. The concern of this work is to establish a reference ontology for the general profile that can be used as guidelines to build a computational CoP framework for realizing such a foundation.”</em></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<h3><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1501.02662"> Social Participation Ontology: community documentation, enhancements and use examples</a></h3>
<p><em>“Participatory democracy advances in virtually all governments and especially in South America which exhibits a mixed culture and social predisposition. This article presents the “Social Participation Ontology” (OPS from the Brazilian name Ontologia de Participação Social) implemented in compliance with the Web Ontology Language standard (OWL) for fostering social participation, specially in virtual platforms. The entities and links of OPS were defined based on an extensive collaboration of specialists. It is shown that OPS is instrumental for information retrieval from the contents of the portal, both in terms of the actors (at various levels) as well as mechanisms and activities. Significantly, OPS is linked to other OWL ontologies as an upper ontology and via FOAF and BFO as higher upper ontologies, which yields sound organization and access of knowledge and data. In order to illustrate the usefulness of OPS, we present results on ontological expansion and integration with other ontologies and data. Ongoing work involves further adoption of OPS by the official Brazilian federal portal for social participation and NGO s, and further linkage to other ontologies for social participation.”</em></p>
</blockquote>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/5">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/5</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2021 17:06:44 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1353-5</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353.rss">Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension?</source>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
