<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Baldur Bjarnason</title>
    <link>https://www.baldurbjarnason.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Baldur Bjarnason</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Jul 2021 10:56:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://www.baldurbjarnason.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Ways of reading without the influence of community</title>
      <link>https://www.baldurbjarnason.com/2021/ways-of-reading/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jul 2021 10:56:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.baldurbjarnason.com/2021/ways-of-reading/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I realised quite a while ago that my web reading habits are very different from most others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My primary source of web reading is my feed reader, still. And unlike how most seem to use feed readers, I mostly follow sites that are sporadically updated. About twenty updates roughly on a daily basis. The remaining 1600 feeds update once a month, or even only a couple of times a year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The theory is that those who post rarely generally only post when they have something really interesting to say, while the rest (like me with &lt;a href=&#34;https://notes.baldurbjarnason.com/&#34;&gt;my link blog&lt;/a&gt;) is posting out of habit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I also tend to follow all of the links in an article or a post. And if those are interesting, I&amp;rsquo;ll follow the links there as well. On a good day, my entire breakfast reading time is sucked up by following down an interesting thread of links.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Following links is essential if you enjoy finding new papers. People never link to PDFs directly in a feed and rarely from social media. But they will link to a PDF in the text of a blog post.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, I have a tendency to reread old blog posts because some of them are genuinely great.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daniel Cook&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://lostgarden.home.blog/blog-archive/&#34;&gt;Lost Garden&lt;/a&gt; is one of the best resources on game design theory and UX design you can find. I enjoy revisiting Christopher Allen&amp;rsquo;s thoughts on social software and collaboration on his blog &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifewithalacrity.com/&#34;&gt;Life With Alacrity&lt;/a&gt;. Kathy Sierra&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://headrush.typepad.com/creating_passionate_users/&#34;&gt;Creating Passionate Users&lt;/a&gt; is a revolutionary read every time I revisit it. Her &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Badass-Making-Awesome-Kathy-Sierra/dp/1491919019/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1440557437&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=badass+making+users+awesome&#34;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; is amazing too but there is just something about a good blog that I genuinely love. A good blog has bite-sized posts mixed in with weightier ones. It carries with it a slice of the time it arrived in: a snapshot of contemporary culture. It reflects the author&amp;rsquo;s social network through links, quotes, and other references.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of those links are dead now, mind you. I know because I also always follow links when I reread an old post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good blogs disappear regularly too. I&amp;rsquo;ll have an urge to dig up an old blog I haven&amp;rsquo;t read in years only to find it gone. Sometimes entire authors seem to get cleaned off the face of the web. Tim O&amp;rsquo;Reilly, for example, one of the most influential thinkers and commentators on the web and tech, used to be a prolific blogger but most of those links are now broken, his blog posts scrubbed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another important aspect of habitually re-reading old blogs is reevaluation. How do a person&amp;rsquo;s ideas and arguments age? Dismissing the stuff that was obviously garbage when new (Chris Anderson&amp;rsquo;s Long Tail, for example) it&amp;rsquo;s surprising how often your first reaction to a blog post or an idea is coloured by your community. You may think that you are a bastion of independent thinking but if your immediate community generally views Kevin Kelly in a positive light, odds are that your first reaction to his nonsense is that it, well, isn&amp;rsquo;t nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, his &lt;a href=&#34;https://kk.org/thetechnium/1000-true-fans/&#34;&gt;1000 true fans&lt;/a&gt; essay has become web canon and you&amp;rsquo;ve almost certainly seen people link to it as an accurate observation of how modern media works. Except it gets almost everything about modern web media wrong where the dominant rule is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Matthew_effect&#34;&gt;Matthew Effect&lt;/a&gt;: anybody who reaches 1000 fans and doesn&amp;rsquo;t get absolutely trashed by fandom toxicity, community management, or screwed over by payment providers, will end up with 10 000 fans, and then 100 000 fans. The rich get richer while the rest are stuck at 300 supporters, all of whom are also creators shuffling around the money they get from their 300 supporters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With web-scale, moderate web media successes will either fade, burn out, or grow to become big successes. Almost all of the money is in the short head of the curve or in being a platform nickle-and-diming the hundreds of thousands who are earning next to nothing in the actual long tail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if your immediate community still remembers his hyping up of the dot-com bubble or his declaration that the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wired.com/1997/03/ff-push/&#34;&gt;browser was dead&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;1997&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; then odds are that any given link to his work will be framed in qualifiers and scepticism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And your reading will be harsher for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the writers whose writing was &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; framed very harshly by the tech community back in the mid-to-late 2000s (2005-2010) at least, was Nicholas Carr. At the time, it seemed that everybody, from moderate sceptics to zealous tech-boosters, just &lt;em&gt;hated&lt;/em&gt; everything he wrote. So, even if you were predisposed to being critical of the state of the web, you read him with scepticism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, re-reading him years later, with the benefit of hindsight, and a lot of it begins to look just plain prescient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;When we view the Web in religious terms, when we imbue it with our personal yearning for transcendence, we can no longer see it objectively. By necessity, we have to look at the Internet as a moral force, not as a simple collection of inanimate hardware and software. No decent person wants to worship an amoral conglomeration of technology.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And so all the things that Web 2.0 represents – participation, collectivism, virtual communities, amateurism – become unarguably good things, things to be nurtured and applauded, emblems of progress toward a more enlightened state. But is it really so? Is there a counterargument to be made? Might, on balance, the practical effect of Web 2.0 on society and culture be bad, not good? To see Web 2.0 as a moral force is to turn a deaf ear to such questions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roughtype.com/?p=110&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The amorality of Web 2.0&lt;/em&gt;, Nicholas Carr&lt;/a&gt; (2005)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you consider that Web 2.0 is the initial seed for the modern web and modern social media, these observations start to look quite interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tech has suffered from a hype cycle for the longest time. A proposed innovation gets hyped up to the sky until it either doesn&amp;rsquo;t pan out or until it becomes too mundane to interest tech&amp;rsquo;s boosters. Criticism from outside of tech is easily handled. Those people don&amp;rsquo;t &amp;lsquo;get&amp;rsquo; it (whatever the &amp;lsquo;it&amp;rsquo; is). They are jealous of the success of the tech industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People in tech, software especially, reserve a particular animosity towards criticisms that come from &amp;lsquo;inside the house&amp;rsquo;, from people who know tech, understand it, have even been a part of implementing it, and aren&amp;rsquo;t happy about where it has been going. Nicholas Carr had been writing about tech for years in 2004. He was supposed to be &amp;lsquo;one of us&amp;rsquo;. Then as now, when somebody like Carr dares prick one of tech&amp;rsquo;s bubbles, the response is almost feral.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of a sudden, the self-labelled &amp;lsquo;rational, independent thinkers&amp;rsquo; start behaving like tantrum-throwing toddlers who grasp at anything and everything as an excuse to perpetuate the tantrum. A single mention of the people responsible for something in tech gets dismissed as an ad hominem attack. Straightforward hypothetical scenarios drawn from experience (and abstracted to protect those involved) get dismissed as straw men.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And men, always men, who regularly boast about their reasoning skills become very, very angry. Especially if the critic is a woman. Not only would she be risking her career but also her very safety as stalking and physical threats are far too common for women who dare draw attention to tech&amp;rsquo;s dysfunction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been happening for a while. It happened during the dot-com bubble. Naysayers were dismissed out of hand. It happened in 2004 when the foundation of modern tech&amp;rsquo;s toxic influence on culture, media, politics and society were first laid down with Web 2.0 and people started to notice the damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The effect of social media, the consolidation of media, the gig economy, we were warned about it all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The warnings weren&amp;rsquo;t even ignored. We don&amp;rsquo;t have the excuse of ignorance. Anybody who was paying any attention to tech knew about these warnings and actively argued against them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the tech punditry reacted with either outrage or just outright condescending dismissal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was pretty easy to fall in with the anger. All of your idols&amp;mdash;role models&amp;mdash;talked about Carr and his fellow critics either explicitly as adversaries, as charlatans, or as failures trying to blame others for their inadequacies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But they were right, weren&amp;rsquo;t they? I mean, once you step back and look at the big picture, you see that they were largely right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How come people like Kevin Kelly are still venerated as thinkers? Why were Carr and Lanier mocked and dismissed as burnt out charlatans until they actually burned out? Pretty much everything the former group said has been wrong or correct but harmful. Most of the critiques made by the latter hit the proverbial nail on the head. Even the ones they got wrong look reasonable with hindsight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The promoters of Web 2.0 venerate the amateur and distrust the professional. We see it in their unalloyed praise of Wikipedia, and we see it in their worship of open-source software and myriad other examples of democratic creativity. Perhaps nowhere, though, is their love of amateurism so apparent as in their promotion of blogging as an alternative to what they call &amp;ldquo;the mainstream media.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roughtype.com/?p=110&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The amorality of Web 2.0&lt;/em&gt;, Nicholas Carr&lt;/a&gt; (2005)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Web 2.0 is the preamble to the current rise of disinformation, extremism, and fascism. Much like the dot-com bubble was the preamble to the financial bubble that popped in 2008.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can draw a direct line between what tech made in 2004-2008 to the current state of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, we in tech and software development still venerate the tech elite, the billionaires, the VCs even though they have been wrong about everything that actually mattered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And venerate is the only word that accurately describes this worship. From a 2005 Tim O&amp;rsquo;Reilly bio:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Satisfaction also comes from O&amp;rsquo;Reilly&amp;rsquo;s continuing connection to his other late father, the toilet paper salesman-cum-guru who opened up mental vistas that only recently have reached full fruition in his student - now that the idea of collective consciousness is becoming manifest in the Internet. &amp;ldquo;The work with George was about the future and the potential of what it is to be human,&amp;rdquo; O&amp;rsquo;Reilly says. &amp;ldquo;But here we are. The Internet today is so much an echo of what we were talking about at [New Age HQ] Esalen in the &amp;lsquo;70s - except we didn&amp;rsquo;t know it would be technology-mediated.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Could it be that the Internet - or what O&amp;rsquo;Reilly calls Web 2.0 - is really the successor to the human potential movement?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wired.com/2005/10/oreilly/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Trend Spotter&lt;/em&gt;, Steven Levy&lt;/a&gt; (2005)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Salvation was at hand, and the critics threatened that rapture. The tech scene in 2004 onwards behaved much like the reactionary proto-fascists responded when Trump was elected: we were about to be saved, and &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; form of criticism threatened that salvation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In both cases, &amp;lsquo;we&amp;rsquo; meant &amp;lsquo;people who look like me&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even when the observations of these idols of tech were correct, they still utterly failed to consider the actual consequences of what they were observing until it was too late.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What we all failed to see was how much of this new world would be manufactured by users, not corporate interests. Amazon.com customers rushed with surprising speed and intelligence to write the reviews that made the site’s long-tail selection usable. Owners of Adobe, Apple, and most major software products offer help and advice on the developer’s forum Web pages, serving as high-quality customer support for new buyers. And in the greatest leverage of the common user, Google turns traffic and link patterns generated by 2 billion searches a month into the organizing intelligence for a new economy. This bottom-up takeover was not in anyone’s 10-year vision.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;No Web phenomenon is more confounding than blogging. Everything media experts knew about audiences – and they knew a lot – confirmed the focus group belief that audiences would never get off their butts and start making their own entertainment. Everyone knew writing and reading were dead; music was too much trouble to make when you could sit back and listen; video production was simply out of reach of amateurs. Blogs and other participant media would never happen, or if they happened they would not draw an audience, or if they drew an audience they would not matter. What a shock, then, to witness the near-instantaneous rise of 50 million blogs, with a new one appearing every two seconds. There – another new blog! One more person doing what AOL and ABC – and almost everyone else – expected only AOL and ABC to be doing. These user-created channels make no sense economically. Where are the time, energy, and resources coming from?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The audience.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wired.com/2005/08/tech/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;We Are the Web&lt;/em&gt;, Kevin Kelly&lt;/a&gt; (2005)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He was right about the popularisation of media production and writing. It became something everybody does. He was wrong about blogs, but that was a blind spot common to everybody at the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost. Nicholas Carr pointed out a few months later how much of the blogging/web media boom seemed to be cheap spam:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Writers are being solicited to churn out such content at dirt cheap rates. Gomes, for instance, signed up on the web to write fifty 500-word articles for $100 (that’s total, not per piece). Most of the writing, apparently, gets done in India and Eastern Europe, and much of it consists of mashing up, and distorting, work plagiarized from other, legitimate sites. Depending on the types of products or ads they’re selling, the site operators instruct the writers to slant the stories to their needs. Medical topics are particular favorites – and particularly subject to fakery and twisting.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roughtype.com/?p=268&#34;&gt;&lt;cite&gt;When information becomes “information”&lt;/cite&gt;, Nicholas Carr&lt;/a&gt; (2006)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kevin Kelly and his ilk were wrong about the likely &lt;em&gt;consequences&lt;/em&gt; of this process. Whereas Nicholas Carr, writing in response to Kevin Kelly&amp;rsquo;s vision:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And so, having gone on for so long, I at long last come to my point. The Internet is changing the economics of creative work – or, to put it more broadly, the economics of culture – and it’s doing it in a way that may well restrict rather than expand our choices. Wikipedia might be a pale shadow of the Britannica, but because it’s created by amateurs rather than professionals, it’s free. And free trumps quality all the time. So what happens to those poor saps who write encyclopedias for a living? They wither and die. The same thing happens when blogs and other free on-line content go up against old-fashioned newspapers and magazines. Of course the mainstream media sees the blogosphere as a competitor. It is a competitor. And, given the economics of the competition, it may well turn out to be a superior competitor. The layoffs we’ve recently seen at major newspapers may just be the beginning, and those layoffs should be cause not for self-satisfied snickering but for despair. Implicit in the ecstatic visions of Web 2.0 is the hegemony of the amateur. I for one can’t imagine anything more frightening.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roughtype.com/?p=110&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The amorality of Web 2.0&lt;/em&gt;, Nicholas Carr&lt;/a&gt; (2005)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The economics of web media ends up restricting choice. Most of what we read is now produced by amateurs or the financially independent elite. Want to learn about web development? Next to nothing that&amp;rsquo;s available is written by actual technical writers or experienced educational writers. Want to read about local politics, about what&amp;rsquo;s happening outside of a major metropolitan area? Good luck finding anything of substance. Instead of a newspaper in every town, we now have five major news outlets per country. If we&amp;rsquo;re lucky. Five major news outlet &lt;em&gt;per language&lt;/em&gt; if we&amp;rsquo;re unlucky. The rest of what passes as news are just opinion columnists and quick rewrites of wire service news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most companies, authors, individuals can&amp;rsquo;t subsist on free, even with advertising. The web is built on the backs of our free work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Om Malik, responding to and concurring with Carr&amp;rsquo;s amorality essay:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I wondered out loud, if this culture of participation was seemingly [helping] build businesses on our collective backs. So if we tag, bookmark or share, and help del.icio.us or Technorati or Yahoo become better commercial entities, aren’t we seemingly commoditizing our most valuable asset – time. We become the outsourced workforce, the collective, though it is still unclear what is the pay-off. While we may (or may not) gain something from the collective efforts, the odds are whatever “the collective efforts” are, they are going to boost the economic value of those entities. Will they share in their upside? Not likely!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gigaom.com/2005/10/18/web-20-the-community-the-commerce-conundrum/&#34;&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Web 2.0, Community &amp; the Commerce Conundrum&lt;/cite&gt;, Om Malik&lt;/a&gt; (2005)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m convinced this is one of the big reasons behind the current state of web development. Why CSS and platform APIs are so unpopular. Why JS payloads on sites seem to be growing exponentially and growing less and less usable on mobile phones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I got my start in web development, you could find several different detailed, well-written, well-structured book on every major part of the stack. You paid for it because the only alternative was trial and error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, web dev education &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; free web content and increasingly dominated by grifters, even offline. Even when web dev educational writing is being made sincerely and with ambition, it&amp;rsquo;s still predominantly amateurs, in the sense that it&amp;rsquo;s done as a sideline by people who aren&amp;rsquo;t experienced educators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/&#34;&gt;MDN&lt;/a&gt; is great, but it can&amp;rsquo;t compare with the depth you get with a detailed book on a single subject. How many today hate to use CSS because they learned it from free sources who keep reusing the same explanations and same metaphors they first read in books on CSS 1 and CSS 2? How many prefer React over DOM APIs primarily because Facebook can invest in documentation while MDN, the last bastion of platform documentation, cuts back on staff? Web dev education looks broken at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s even a Nicholas Carr post for that as well (though, language warning, I guess):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Although wikis and other Web 2.0 platforms for the creation of content are often described in purely egalitarian terms – as the products of communities of equals – that’s just a utopian fantasy. In fact, the quality of the product hinges not just, or even primarily, on the number of contributors. It also hinges on the talent of the contributors – or, more accurately, on the talent of every individual contributor. No matter how vast, a community of mediocrities will never be able to produce anything better than mediocre work. Indeed, I would argue that the talent of the contributors is in the end far more important to quality than is the number of contributors. Put 5,000 smart people to work on a wiki, and they’ll come up with something better than a wiki created by a million numbskulls.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roughtype.com/?p=346&#34;&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Web 2.0’s numbskull factor&lt;/cite&gt;, Nick Carr&lt;/a&gt; (2006)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carr and others, like Jaron Lanier, raised the alarm about where things were heading over fifteen years ago and their concerns have come true. They may have gotten some of the details wrong, but the overall picture? On the nose. Instead of decentralising, the atomising force that is the web subsequently led to a new, much greater, consolidation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I was talking about a few different things at the time I wrote “Digital Maoism.” One of them was the way that we were centralizing culture, even though the rhetoric was that we were distributing it. Before Wikipedia, I think it would have been viewed as being this horrible thing to say that there could only be one encyclopedia, and that there would be one dominant entry for a given topic. Instead, there were different encyclopedias. There would be variations not so much in what facts were presented, but in the way they were presented. That voice was a real thing.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;And then we moved to this idea that we have a single dominant encyclopedia that was supposed to be the truth for the global AI or something like that. But there’s something deeply pernicious about that. So we’re saying anybody can write for Wikipedia, so it’s, like, purely democratic and it’s this wonderful open thing, and yet the bizarreness is that that open democratic process is on the surface of something that struck me as being Maoist, which is that there’s this one point of view that’s then gonna be the official one.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Jarod Lanier speaking in: &lt;a href=&#34;https://nymag.com/intelligencer/2018/04/jaron-lanier-interview-on-what-went-wrong-with-the-internet.html&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘One Has This Feeling of Having Contributed to Something That’s Gone Very Wrong’&lt;/em&gt;, Noah Kulwin&lt;/a&gt; (2018)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some, like Jaron Lanier, changed sides once they began to see where things were going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which was in the early 2000s. Which was when the rest of the punditry should have seen the harm that was beginning to accumulate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t blame VCs or startup founders who got rich for conning us about the glorious future of the web. They are grifters—con artists—and when you fall for a scam, it&amp;rsquo;s on you to pick yourself up and learn from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We didn&amp;rsquo;t. We the developers who are the foot soldiers in the strip-mining that is modern tech keep picking ourselves up after every disaster, bubble pop, burn out, and keep helping the grifters grift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s partly because of intellectuals like Kevin Kelly, who never passed up on an opportunity to evangelise the web and tech, even though they didn&amp;rsquo;t stand to make millions off it like the hustlers. They kept building the web back up as a saviour after every collapse, every bubble pop, every scandal. Partly it&amp;rsquo;s on us for constantly venerating billionaires and wannabe billionaires for looting the society the rest of us live in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s time that we stop venerating the hustlers, the looters, the leaders of the tech-rapture cult, and realise, much like with the climate crisis, that things are actually, truly, quite horrible and that it&amp;rsquo;s on us to fix it before it ruins everything for the coming generations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have a clue. I just know that we&amp;rsquo;re at least fifteen years behind the curve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;further-nicholas-carr-reading&#34;&gt;Further Nicholas Carr reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He doesn&amp;rsquo;t get everything right, but even when he&amp;rsquo;s wrong, his observations tend to be interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Although the internet certainly enlarges the pool of media offerings, by radically driving down the cost of production and distribution, and thus extends the long tail, that doesn’t mean it will allow the smaller guys (or even the larger ones) to make more money – or any money, for that matter. The problem – assuming you think of it as a problem, which I do – lies, I think, in the basic economic model that is emerging for online media. Which is this: provide free access to the content, and make your money through advertising and, in particular, click-based advertising. With a few important exceptions, the paid-subscription model doesn’t work. By democratizing the production and distribution of media, the internet ensures that an overabundance of supply and the resulting competition will drive the price of most content down to its marginal production cost, which is zero.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roughtype.com/?p=406&#34;&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Where the money isn’t&lt;/cite&gt;, Nick Carr&lt;/a&gt; (2006)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The winner-takes-all nature of most web media business models means that subscription sites are almost certainly going to consolidate or, as with Patreon, end up being a closed loop of money: most of the subscribers are also publishers, the money gets pushed back and forth, ever-dwindling due to Patreon&amp;rsquo;s transaction cut.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We’re seeing what looks like the erosion of the American middle class and the rise of a new aristocracy, as a very thin slice of the population reaps an ever larger share of the bounties of Information Age capitalism. Generosity sounds lovely as an economic principle, and I suppose it can be lovely in reality, too – so long as you’re one of the chosen few who can afford to exchange precious gifts.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roughtype.com/?p=320&#34;&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Generous to a fault&lt;/cite&gt;, Nick Carr&lt;/a&gt; (2006)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yanis Varoufakis made much the same observation last month: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/techno-feudalism-replacing-market-capitalism-by-yanis-varoufakis-2021-06&#34;&gt;Techno-Feudalism Is Taking Over&lt;/a&gt;. Before and after takes on the rise of techno-feudalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roughtype.com/?p=36&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Juicing the web&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; points out, in 2005, that AJAX (the precursor to Single Page Apps) is key to the shift of software tools to the web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On building tech with poor data sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Entrepreneurs are launching all sorts of sites and services that are built on data that they’re siphoning out of third-party sites and databases. Sometimes, the secondhand data is good; sometimes, it’s not. The process of chopping up and bundling data from many different sources can, moreover, amplify inaccuracies. Combine bad data from two different sources and you may get bad data squared. Unfortunately, to the user, the inaccuracies are invisible.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roughtype.com/?p=253&#34;&gt;&lt;cite&gt;The truthiness of Web 2.0&lt;/cite&gt;, Nick Carr&lt;/a&gt; (2006)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On how the web promotes extremism and polarization:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s only natural to think that a revolutionary communications technology like the internet will help break down barriers between people and bring the world closer together. But that’s not the only scenario, or even the most likely one. The internet turns everything, from knowledge-gathering to community-building, into a series of tiny transactions – clicks – that are simple in isolation yet extraordinarily complicated in the aggregate. Research shows that very small biases, when magnified through thousands or millions or billions of choices, can turn into profound schisms. There’s reason to believe, or at least to fear, that this effect, inherent in large networks, may end up turning the internet into a polarizing force rather than a unifying one.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roughtype.com/?p=196&#34;&gt;&lt;cite&gt;
    Tribes of the internet
    &lt;/cite&gt;, Nick Carr&lt;/a&gt; (2005)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On how traditional software will get replaced with Software-as-a-Service (SaaS): &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roughtype.com/?p=83&#34;&gt;The slow death of traditional software&lt;/a&gt; (2005).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Open-Source Software bubble that is and the blogging bubble that was</title>
      <link>https://www.baldurbjarnason.com/2021/the-oss-bubble-and-the-blogging-bubble/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 May 2021 10:56:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.baldurbjarnason.com/2021/the-oss-bubble-and-the-blogging-bubble/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: until a couple of months ago, I was paid to work full-time on &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open-source_software&#34;&gt;Open-Source Software&lt;/a&gt; (OSS) software in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_educational_resources&#34;&gt;Open Educational Resources&lt;/a&gt; (OER) space. There&amp;rsquo;s a distinct possibility that I&amp;rsquo;m biased in some way as a result. There&amp;rsquo;s also the possibility that working in OSS and OER for over four years might mean that my opinions are backed by experience. You get to decide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-symptom&#34;&gt;The symptom&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://babel.dev/blog/2021/05/10/funding-update&#34;&gt;Babel is used by millions, so why are we running out of money?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This doesn&amp;rsquo;t surprise me. The purpose of the web software industry is to extract value out of Open-Source Software (OSS). Everything is built under the misconception that OSS is abundant, replaceable, and free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People don&amp;rsquo;t appreciate just how much web dev is about extracting value from OSS, both on individual and corporate levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make a native iOS app, and the only OSS you need to use is directly integrated into the OS, and a lot of it is maintained by Apple itself. Apple may use open-source font rendering libraries or SQLite, but you rarely have to deal with it yourself, as a developer, unless you want to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Web development? Everything is built or run directly on OSS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Almost everything we do in web development exists as a thin layer over open-source software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Servers, build tools, databases, ORMs, auth, client-side JS, web browser: we are all building on a vast ocean of OSS labour without paying back a fraction of the value we generate. It isn&amp;rsquo;t just big, direct dependencies like Babel that are suffering. The stuff your stuff is using&amp;mdash;the infrastructure code everything needs&amp;mdash;is surviving on sheer inertia as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s value extraction. Strip-mining if you want to hammer home the unsustainability. Looting if you want to emphasise the moral dimension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We don&amp;rsquo;t even know the extent of the problem. Has anybody looked into the sustainability of the npm ecosystem, for example? How much of it is backed by a sustainable business model or even any kind of ongoing revenue?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suspect that the sustainable fraction is tiny. At some point, something&amp;rsquo;s going to give. Something&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;already giving&lt;/em&gt;. We keep seeing projects like Babel: used by thousands; running on fumes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m reminded of the only real tech bubble I&amp;rsquo;ve personally witnessed: the rise and fall of blogging. They&amp;rsquo;re very different phenomena, but blogging and open-source are solid examples of big corporations strategically subsidising a complement to their core business with no care being paid to collateral damage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I was in university when the dot com bubble collapsed, so I missed that. And I was doing my PhD when Web 2.0 peaked. Somebody needs to write about the true history of the rise and fall of the blog as the dominant web paradigm as a lot of it seems to be forgotten or just plain misunderstood today.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of misconceptions about what exactly happened. People think that Google killed weblogs in 2013 when it discontinued Google Reader. Which isn&amp;rsquo;t entirely true. Google Reader was a murder weapon, not a victim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-blogging-bubble-and-its-modern-parallels&#34;&gt;The blogging bubble and its modern parallels&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google did kill weblogs, but that&amp;rsquo;s fair since they also created the weblog bubble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might not believe this if you weren&amp;rsquo;t there, but one of Google&amp;rsquo;s main problems, once they got going, was that there just wasn&amp;rsquo;t that much to see on the web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having a great search engine is kind of useless if, for example, somebody types in &amp;ldquo;how to take better landscape photographs,&amp;rdquo; and nobody online has an answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google Adwords changed all of that. That, as well as free weblog hosting, fuelled the blogging bubble. You wrote a blog using a weblog system that came with decent SEO baked in (semantic structure and cross-linking, that&amp;rsquo;s all you needed back then). Most of your traffic came from Google&amp;rsquo;s search results. All of your revenue came from Google&amp;rsquo;s Adwords. It became profitable to churn out indistinct pap that passed as informative to fill Google&amp;rsquo;s search engine results, so people did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The weblog ecosystem was built entirely around extracting value from Adwords. For a few, it was a springboard to launch something else. A few writing careers got off the ground. But the vast, vast majority was just Adwords. Weblogs as social media? A sideshow. Weblogs as a unique medium? Incidental.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even outfits with paid subscriptions, like MetaFilter, relied on Adwords and had to course-correct once Google popped that bubble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which they did because they had to: most of it was fraudulent. Fake clicks. Spam blogs. Link farms. Black hat SEO. The blogging economy was filled with bad practices all around. People today don&amp;rsquo;t appreciate just how rampant these practices were. Most of us didn&amp;rsquo;t notice because we were in our tiny corner, all reading the same few popular bloggers (an early version of the modern &amp;lsquo;influencer&amp;rsquo;). But outside of that corner, blogs were done for Google and paid for by Google. Outside of a small number of active commenters (many of whom were toxic as hell), the traffic these blogs had existed solely because it suited Google to give blogs a high &amp;lsquo;PageRank&amp;rsquo;. They had no meaningful community or engagement to call their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a few &lt;em&gt;years&lt;/em&gt; of buying into the hype, advertisers started to push back, forcing Google to clean up their index. That consisted of downplaying blogs and blog-like sites and purging spam-blogs and blog farms (many of which had been hosted on Google Blogger, natch).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blog gold rush ended. The tools surrounding it started dying, hastened by Google sucking the oxygen out of the software ecosystem by acquiring, offering for free, and then putting on life support the core tools in the ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FeedBurner and Google Reader were not victims of Google&amp;rsquo;s policies. They were the weapons Google used to ensure that the only player extracting value from blogging was &lt;em&gt;Google&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because people misunderstand what happened, they tend to take away the wrong lessons about what worked or didn&amp;rsquo;t work about blogging. They wrote off blogs as a genre of design: content, a sidebar with blog roll and categories, comments, and a casual style of writing. They ignored the tech that blogs were built on: RSS, easy-to-use CMSes, reverse-chronological listings mixed with categories and the like to highlight posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blogs, by the technical definition, are having a resurgence. Substack is a blogging system with convenient payment and email integration(RSS, reverse-chronological listing). As Jeremy Keith enjoys pointing out, Medium is Ev&amp;rsquo;s blog and offers RSS feeds and reverse-chronological listings for each guest author. Most mailing list platforms are either technically blogs (RSS plus a pleasant CMS) or integrate with blogs using RSS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time around, the audience seems, for the most part, to genuinely be invested in the blogs themselves. They aren&amp;rsquo;t being funnelled there by Google or Facebook because it&amp;rsquo;s strategically convenient for them, for the moment. Substack isn&amp;rsquo;t the only player in town, so we seem to be avoiding the monoculture pitfall. Blogging for an &lt;em&gt;earned&lt;/em&gt; audience is probably bigger than it has ever been before in the history of the web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The blogging bubble reminds me in many ways of the current state of web development:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have an economy that exists solely because big tech companies are pouring money into strategic complements to their products.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This money-hose distorts the economy in ways that kill off businesses and skew education and recruitment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Much like the blog farms of old, many companies get away with extractive, unsustainable, and generally awful practices because so many of their resources are in effect subsidised by Google, Facebook, or Microsoft.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most web software companies are built to quickly extract value from the underlying open-source layer. Ever wondered why management practices in web software are dominated by short term concerns that are self-destructive in the long term? Because managers know &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; they are supposed to do, even if they don&amp;rsquo;t exactly know why. Speed is of the essence because you aren&amp;rsquo;t doing anything unique. You aren&amp;rsquo;t creating tech of your own or building on a hard-earned understanding of the clientele. You are using your funding to race against others to see who manages to squeeze the most business out of the underlying OSS before the funding runs out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-willful-blindness&#34;&gt;The willful blindness&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people in the industry don&amp;rsquo;t realise that the web dev economy is primarily extractive. As with the earlier assumption that Google must be trying to keep Adwords clean and sustainable, there&amp;rsquo;s the assumption here that &lt;em&gt;somebody&lt;/em&gt; in tech must be making sure the work behind OSS is paid for. Or, almost as naively, they assume that it can all subsist as donationware.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People in web dev constantly assume that something somewhere must be paying for the OSS dependencies they use. This is why developers come in with the entitlement of a paying customer. The OSS maintainer is supposed to serve them with the enthusiasm of somebody being paid. Their worldview just doesn&amp;rsquo;t accommodate the idea that this is unpaid labour because then they&amp;rsquo;d have to start questioning the very sustainability of their own careers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-money-hose&#34;&gt;The money hose&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the misconceptions about OSS stem from the fact that the core of the ecosystem &lt;em&gt;is funded&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook is pouring money into the React sub-ecosystem, and Google keeps burning cash on the Chrome bonfire. Microsoft keeps funding developer infrastructure like Visual Studio Code, Typescript, npm, and GitHub. Those are just the most prominent examples. They all fund ton of other projects, either directly or indirectly, through a wage surplus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A surprising amount of OSS is made by former big tech developers. They can afford to subsist on meagre revenue—for a time—because their pay and stock options have left them free of debt and with well-stocked savings accounts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is much more common than you&amp;rsquo;d think. Scratch away at the surface of pretty much any active OSS project that has no discernible revenue, and you either get a burnout waiting to happen, or you&amp;rsquo;ll find a formerly well-paid dev coasting on savings. Many of the rest have solid VC funding. Though, VC funding always runs out at some point. The business fundamentals just aren&amp;rsquo;t there for open source when you have Google, Amazon, and the rest gatekeeping all of the value in the market. This is why the ecosystem is already beginning to pull apart at the seams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Microsoft&amp;hellip; Like I wrote above, MS is just &lt;em&gt;carpet-bombing&lt;/em&gt; the web developer community with open source software and OSS infrastructure. Typescript, Visual Studio Code, GitHub, npm, and so much more exist primarily because Microsoft executives believe this will lead to more business for Azure and other Microsoft offerings. In turn, most of the offerings on Azure (as with Amazon Web Services) are leveraging OSS to maximise the value of the platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the rest of the ecosystem—excluding the tiny fraction like SQLite who have few dependencies and sustainable revenue—exists as backsplash from those two projects. Node, Deno, Electron, most front end tooling, and so many web dev libraries only exist because of projects that Google and Facebook are funding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google, Facebook, and Microsoft are probably the biggest players using OSS this way, but they are not alone. Leveraging the positive externalities of OSS has been the go-to strategy for many big tech corporations for a while now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It isn&amp;rsquo;t just software: web dev education, training, and recruitment exist primarily to extract value from Facebook&amp;rsquo;s React or Google&amp;rsquo;s OSS projects. Very few of them invest in figuring out what sort of training will serve their students the best. The easiest thing to sell to both recruiters and students is the big framework on the block, so that&amp;rsquo;s what they sell and very little else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The extraction mentality is baked into the business. Which is sort of fine when you&amp;rsquo;re dealing with projects funded by mega-corporations but disastrous when applied to the unfunded or poorly funded rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The money hose, combined with free or subsidised services, is a control mechanism that lets big tech companies control the OSS ecosystem. Projects they want to promote will get the money spigot. Other projects, like MongoDB or Redis, get turned into commodities and resold as cheap services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most notably, projects that try to independently leverage open source to become fast-growing tech companies are disproportionally likely to be &amp;lsquo;embraced and extended&amp;rsquo; this way by AWS, Google Cloud, or Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s Azure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of us aren&amp;rsquo;t much better. The SaaS companies that funnel a bit of their revenue back to the OSS projects they&amp;rsquo;re building on are few and far between. The companies that maintain an OSS framework or library as a positive externality to their business are few and far between. VC-funded OSS companies are moonshots that tend to crash well before they get an opportunity to blow up in orbit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re honestly bloody bad at paying for the work of making software as an industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-deterioration-and-potential-collapse&#34;&gt;The deterioration and potential collapse&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then as now, every stepwise deterioration in the ecosystem is explained away. Back when the primacy of blogs was sliding, every time Google changed their algorithm to downplay blogs or updated their Adwords policies, you got thousands of responses &amp;lsquo;explaining&amp;rsquo; how this wasn&amp;rsquo;t the end of the world and here&amp;rsquo;s what you need to change to keep up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, legitimate blogs started dropping off the web, services began to shutter, and RSS feeds went dark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re starting to see the initial decay hit the parts of the web dev ecosystem that are the furthest away from the cheap money fountains Google and Facebook are providing. Core projects run out of money. Git commits stop. A dependency you use breaks when one of &lt;em&gt;its&lt;/em&gt; dependencies stops working, leading somebody to fork it with a quick fix or replacement dependency. Bandaid fixes to decaying OSS projects start to crop up in more and more places. We start to see blog posts saying that all we need to do is get enough people to donate money or pay for support. Everything will be fine. Just look at how OpenSSL got turned around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of which is bad enough but also misses the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weblogs were a strategic lever for Google. Funding them made sense at a time where they needed the web to have more content. When they didn&amp;rsquo;t need them&amp;mdash;when they stopped being a profitable lever&amp;mdash;they were discarded. And the ecosystem sunk fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open-source software is a strategic lever for big tech companies. They fund when it helps their core business and strip-mine projects when it doesn&amp;rsquo;t. Cloud hosting has, slowly, been ushering in an era of extraction, where tech companies specifically target serverside OSS projects that they can leverage with little investment. Broad sections of serverside software are woefully underfinanced. Many server frameworks in the node ecosystem, for example, coast along on burned-out maintainers and sheer bloody-mindedness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chrome and React are strategic levers for Google and Facebook. Electron, GitHub, Visual Studio Code, TypeScript, and npm are all potential strategic levers for Microsoft. V8, npm, React, Visual Studio Code, and Github: they are the foundation of modern web development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How confident are you that &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; of these projects will &lt;em&gt;remain&lt;/em&gt; strategic for the life of the web? Losing any one of them would knock the entire software economy to the ground. Are we so sure that nothings going to change for these companies?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Facebook as a business is, in my view, harmful for society in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which used to mark me as a contrary weirdo but is now the political consensus in many countries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple&amp;rsquo;s pro-privacy stance is manoeuvring Chrome into direct conflict with other parts of the Google behemoth. To remain competitive as a browser, Chrome must work against the interests of its owner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can argue whether there is any substance behind Apple&amp;rsquo;s privacy efforts or not. But it&amp;rsquo;s a highly effective strategy for striking at Google&amp;rsquo;s longstanding core strategy: using free products and OSS to bolster their web-based ad business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft is still in the progress of figuring out which of its acquired assets directly benefit its core businesses and which don&amp;rsquo;t. Their track record of embracing and extending and ruthless competition doesn&amp;rsquo;t inspire trust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re still going to see a tonne of projects burn out and die out. Diversification will mostly be a question of which flavour of V8 and what flavour of React-like front end framework you&amp;rsquo;re using. Everything else would slowly become a barren wasteland. But overall? It would survive. A bit boring but still alive. Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s OSS endeavours might suffer as npm and GitHub more and more become homes for dead and broken software, but the tools should still work, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happens if Facebook&amp;rsquo;s fortunes change? Or if its reputation becomes so bad that React ceases to be a good recruitment tool. Or, if the web dev training ecosystem shifts away from React because most of the time, it isn&amp;rsquo;t the right tool for the job unless you&amp;rsquo;re Facebook? What if Facebook&amp;rsquo;s management decides they can get most of the benefit they want from React without pouring money into React? Let the community coast on voluntary contributions for a while?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do we want to risk becoming a web development ecosystem that primarily exists as a subsidised complement to Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s Azure and, maybe, GitHub? (That&amp;rsquo;s assuming GitHub is a viable business in its own right.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are we all okay with the collateral damage of burning out the OSS ecosystem?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strategy isn&amp;rsquo;t permanent. It&amp;rsquo;s always a response to needs and to the surrounding landscape. If needs change or if the landscape changes, then the strategy has to change as well. It&amp;rsquo;s a cliche to say this, but change is constant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we want software development to last, then we need to work on our attitudes towards open-source and reconsider our reliance on software that, at the moment, happens to be strategically relevant to big tech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-price-were-paying&#34;&gt;The price we&amp;rsquo;re paying&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite everything I wrote above, this apocalyptic vision of potential collapse isn&amp;rsquo;t what worries me. The biggest problem I have with the status quo isn&amp;rsquo;t that it might be unstable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we learned from blogging is that we can rebuild. If the tech giants shift their attention away and the bubble bursts, the skills and knowledge will still be there. And rebuilding is often an opportunity to fix things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, instability doesn&amp;rsquo;t worry me. It&amp;rsquo;s just an inevitable part of working in an immature medium, dominated by immature mega-corporations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest problem&amp;mdash;and this isn&amp;rsquo;t limited to web development&amp;mdash;is how it has baked exploitation into the core worldview of so many people. We &lt;em&gt;use&lt;/em&gt; open-source software. We &lt;em&gt;get paid&lt;/em&gt; to use open-source software. Our employers benefit, but the money never trickles down—money &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; trickles down. This is fine when the project in question is directly funded by a tech multinational. Less so when the project is something specialised, a little bit niche, or inventive, and therefore not financed by a gigantic corporation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We train each other with a mindset to treat each other poorly and consider the people&amp;mdash;whose free work we are turning into money&amp;mdash;to be disposable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re working in an unstable industry, surviving at the whim of callous mega-corporations, and we spend our days treating people like shit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t feel proud when I look around at the web developer community and economy. More the other thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few bright spots. Interesting companies that build a lot of OSS while flying sustainably under the radar. Turns out you don&amp;rsquo;t need that many people to maintain open-source if you set strict boundaries and make sure all of the work is paid for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then you have companies like WordPress who have been around forever and form the backbone of the entire web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sustainable open-source looks &lt;em&gt;possible&lt;/em&gt; if you manage to balance looking uninteresting to big tech but interesting enough to generate revenue. As WordPress shows, you can get pretty big while remaining mostly uninteresting to the tech behemoths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a tricky needle to thread but seems to be entirely possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest threat, what kills off project after project, is scope creep (a universal problem for software development) and other developers who feel entitled to your time and work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twenty years ago, when I was doing my postgraduate studies at the University of the West of England, one of my mentors was Bob Hughes. He wrote the book Dust or Magic, an idiosyncratic study of what makes great interactive media great. It&amp;rsquo;s a lovely book that&amp;rsquo;s hard to find these days, and it led him to hold a couple of &lt;em&gt;Dust or Magic&lt;/em&gt; conferences in Oxford over a decade ago. Those two conferences are, to this day, the most engaging and inspiring conferences I&amp;rsquo;ve ever attended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He has done quite a few things since. Some activism. A bit of writing. &lt;a href=&#34;https://newint.org/books/new-internationalist/bleeding-edge&#34;&gt;Like an excellent book on the toxic nature of modern tech&lt;/a&gt;. (Highly recommended.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day, when I was still doing my Masters (ca. 2000), I ran into him in the courtyard at UWE&amp;rsquo;s Bower Ashton campus. I enthusiastically began to subject him to my latest enthusiasm as I&amp;rsquo;m wont to do. I spoke about this great thing called Free Software and how it would fundamentally change our relationship with technology: make tech free and fair. Free Software was going to make software a force for equality and progress!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash;While I&amp;rsquo;ve never been bright-eyed or bushy-tailed by nature, I&amp;rsquo;ve always had a strong tendency towards idealism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bob patiently listened to me, gave me the time to make my case and argue my point before sighing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Punctuation can&amp;rsquo;t really capture the way Bob speaks. The pauses and hesitations make his arguments feel like he&amp;rsquo;s leading you down a winding path, even though, at the end of it, you look back and see that you just went down a straight, narrow, and unmissable road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Capitalism will always find a way to exploit common resources. It&amp;rsquo;s just a matter of time.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;Loot&amp;rsquo; is a word that he used a lot at the time. It was the primary theme of the closing talk Bob held at the last &lt;em&gt;Dust or Magic&lt;/em&gt; conference he led.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our world is built on looting what others have to give—what we &lt;em&gt;make&lt;/em&gt; them give.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we&amp;rsquo;re fine with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re all fine with looting.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>You are what you do, not what you say or write</title>
      <link>https://www.baldurbjarnason.com/2021/you-are-what-you-do/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2021 12:56:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.baldurbjarnason.com/2021/you-are-what-you-do/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you follow the tech scene in any way, you will not have missed the ongoing self-immolation of the company Basecamp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, if you want to read an in-depth overview of what happened, Casey Newton has written two well-sourced reports on what happened, neither of which seems to be disputed in any meaningful way by any of the participants:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.platformer.news/p/-what-really-happened-at-basecamp&#34;&gt;What really happened at Basecamp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.platformer.news/p/-how-basecamp-blew-up&#34;&gt;How Basecamp blew up&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will delve into what seems to have happened towards the end of this post &lt;em&gt;but&lt;/em&gt; this crisis is interesting because it is a good case study of mismanagement, &lt;em&gt;even without knowing any of the internal details&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just based on what happened in public, the root cause of this crisis was always going to be mismanagement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-it-doesnt-really-matter-what-happened-inside-basecamp&#34;&gt;Why it doesn&amp;rsquo;t really matter what happened inside Basecamp&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowledge work requires trust. Software development requires more than other kinds. Basecamp&amp;rsquo;s new blog-announced policies were management publicly posting a declaration that they no longer trusted their staff. That made working there untenable. Irrespective of context or politics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The entire thing becomes even more damning once you take politics and context into consideration. Even without those details, the public actions of Basecamp&amp;rsquo;s management are evidence of severe dysfunction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t want to downplay what was happening or the authoritarianism that seems to be at play. But the policies themselves and how they were communicated are sufficient evidence of poor decision-making on their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The policies are openly hostile to the workforce. They amount to a declaration that the employees can&amp;rsquo;t be trusted to do their job without handholding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because from the perspective of management theory and practice, organisational psychology, and just plain business, it was an awful decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A blanket ban on political discussions where there hadn&amp;rsquo;t been one previously only makes sense if you don&amp;rsquo;t trust the judgement of your employees. They demonstrated that they didn&amp;rsquo;t trust the employees&#39; ability to productively discuss the topic at work &lt;em&gt;even when relevant to the task&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They stated that people would have to exert their own judgement as to whether it&amp;rsquo;s relevant or not. But given the other policies enacted, staff has no reason to assume that their opinions on the matter would be trusted. In fact, they have every reason to think the opposite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The processes at Basecamp are well documented (see the books &lt;em&gt;Shape Up&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Rework&lt;/em&gt;). Their software development is structured to both need and leverage trust to function. The policies were an overt announcement of mistrust. Unambiguously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People focus on the ill-advised topic ban and forget the dismantling of committees, abandoning 360 peer reviews, and the prohibition on reviewing management&amp;rsquo;s historical decisions. Changes as drastic as these mean there has been a rupture between staff and management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nobody really seems to notice that Basecamp went from ostensibly being an open and trusting workplace to lockdown in the space of a few days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They went from:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously feeling free to discuss contentious and complicated topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having considerable autonomy in terms of running several employee-led committees, including a diversity and integration committee that had a lot of support among staff&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reviews were 360 peer-led performance reviews&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going over and analysing management decisions—treating the bosses like a peer in a 360 review—seems to have been the norm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of that was taken away in what can only be understood as a declaration of no confidence, a policy change that the employees found out about it from a public blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t a case of a workplace narrowing down its internal topic guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Workplaces &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; have some guidelines for what is appropriate to discuss and what isn&amp;rsquo;t. Those should be written in collaboration with the employees. The organisation should work &lt;em&gt;together&lt;/em&gt; to figure out what works best for the particular work the company is doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Productive guidelines are never as broad as &amp;lsquo;no politics&amp;rsquo; because that guideline is so obviously unimplementable that it actually means &amp;lsquo;my politics.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The guidelines need to be specific. They need to establish boundaries that everybody is comfortable with. They need to allow for discussions that are necessary for the work and for the emotional health of the workplace. They need to clearly mark as off-limits those topics that harm the health of the workplace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is none of that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a hissy fit where a couple of founders completely overturned the culture they &lt;em&gt;themselves&lt;/em&gt; established over many years, all because they felt deeply uncomfortable about being challenged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even after the first couple of blog posts, they could have prevented all of the ensuing damage by apologising and committing themselves to create new guidelines in collaboration with the employees that reflected company consensus. But they didn&amp;rsquo;t do that because this wasn&amp;rsquo;t about establishing boundaries or establishing cultural norms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was about establishing complete control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most managers aren&amp;rsquo;t going to put themselves in this position because they aren&amp;rsquo;t authoritarian narcissists. A crisis like this at a mid-sized workplace can often be resolved by everybody talking together to establish reasonable boundaries. Occasionally with the help of an organisational psychologist. It gets fixed without the public tantrums or the excessive blog-hole-digging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Disclaimer: my dad is a retired organisational psychologist. This is the sort of work he used to do. 🙂)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When several employees publicly state: &amp;ldquo;I found out about this from Jason Fried&amp;rsquo;s public blog post&amp;rdquo;, then it&amp;rsquo;s unambiguously the CEO who&amp;rsquo;s at fault. He should have ensured that the decisions were adequately communicated to staff before making them public. You can make excuses for him, but, at best, these never rise above &amp;lsquo;whoops! he broke something&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He still broke something, didn&amp;rsquo;t apologise, and, as CEO, is ultimately responsible no matter what. He prioritised getting ahead of potential leaks over ensuring good internal communications. No matter how you slice that, that&amp;rsquo;s pretty irresponsible management right there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jason Fried&amp;rsquo;s and David Hansson&amp;rsquo;s public actions are damning enough on their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We don&amp;rsquo;t need to find out what happened because none of it would suddenly make their actions good management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either they badly mishandled one major crisis, or they&amp;rsquo;ve been mismanaging the company for months, if not years. The only way that their public actions last week weren&amp;rsquo;t incredibly poor decision-making is if the goal was to get rid of employees in a loud way to discourage specific types of applicants in the future. Keep the company lean and make sure only yes-people apply in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that was the goal, then it worked perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-seems-to-have-actually-happened&#34;&gt;What seems to have actually happened&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I wrote the following after more of the details of what happened had become public.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second report clears up a lot of the noise about what happened, but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t change any of what I wrote above. It only changed my opinion of Fried and Hansson: I now think they are even worse managers than I thought before. There was a possibility in my mind that they were intentionally pivoting the company&amp;rsquo;s internal culture into one that favoured white supremacy (just look at the type of media and commentators that came out strongly in favour of their decision). This would have made them detestable people who prioritised extremist politics over the smooth running of the company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it also would have meant that they weren&amp;rsquo;t incompetent managers, &lt;em&gt;per se&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, what seems to have happened according to the reports above (which you should read):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One of Fried and Hansson&amp;rsquo;s favourite employees had a history of posting extreme political views in internal discussions (the media outlet he was reported to have linked to is not &amp;lsquo;conservative&amp;rsquo;, it&amp;rsquo;s an extremist right-wing ultra-nationalist rag).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Somehow, comments by other employees who were pointing out that a separate instance of mockery could be a path towards normalising bigotry was what got labelled &amp;lsquo;political&amp;rsquo;&amp;mdash;not the favourite employee&amp;rsquo;s extremism.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The founders of Basecamp seem to have a pattern of authoritarian behaviour in their management style. Using the terminology of management theory: they defaulted to an authoritarian command-and-control style of management in all but a few specific circumstances, in contrast with how they present themselves to the outside in their books and blog posts. This seems to have been a long-standing pattern and is likely to be the root cause of the crisis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They attempted to use a command-and-control tactic when it started to look like the employees wanted to review long-standing behaviours of the founders and their favourite employee (who, remember, apparently had a pattern of posting extremist views):
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They began by &lt;em&gt;deleting nearly two decades of internal conversations&lt;/em&gt;, making it impossible to establish solid evidence of a pattern of behaviour. (&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s not the crime, it&amp;rsquo;s the cover-up.&amp;quot;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They then announced policies essentially forbidding employees from criticising management or their historical patterns of behaviour.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This announcement was made public to get ahead of leaks before they had made sure all of the employees had read it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This meant that a large part of their workforce found out about this wholesale declaration of no confidence &lt;em&gt;from the internet&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When this backfired, they &lt;em&gt;dug in&lt;/em&gt;: their authoritarian management tendencies are too ingrained to be changed at this point. They aren&amp;rsquo;t treating the company as a living organisation but instead as a playground for their enjoyment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then, after burning down most of their company to protect one high-profile manager, that manager resigns because they felt forced to suspend him, pending a review of past behaviour.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no interpretation of this sequence of events that makes Fried and Hansson good managers. The decisions they made public themselves are bad enough. If what Casey Newton has reported is true, then the company has a long-standing history of authoritarian management and a culture of tolerance for extremist, right-wing views.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is pretty much the opposite of the image that Basecamp&amp;rsquo;s founders have constructed of the company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;you-are-what-you-do-not-what-you-say-or-write&#34;&gt;You are what you do, not what you say or write&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is, unfortunately, somewhat of a pattern, especially in tech. People substitute good behaviour and practices with &lt;em&gt;talking about good behaviour&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Instead&lt;/em&gt; of writing good code, they talk about writing good code. &lt;em&gt;Instead&lt;/em&gt; of holding structured meetings, they write about holding structured meetings. &lt;em&gt;Instead&lt;/em&gt; of treating all of their coworkers fairly, they write about treating them fairly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This stems from a worldview that what makes something &amp;lsquo;good&amp;rsquo; is how it makes you look. If you believe that the ultimate point of good behaviour is a better standing among your peers, then you only need to present the image of good behaviour to get the benefit. Changing your behaviour becomes a waste of effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They may not even realise they are doing it. One issue we all encounter is that, while most people know how to do a good job, their circumstances or mindset prevent them from implementing that at work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This creates a painful cognitive dissonance (&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m good at my job but also can&amp;rsquo;t be good at my job&amp;rdquo;). The simplest way to solve that dissonance is to talk about doing the right thing because your mind often interprets talk as action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only other way to cut through this knot is to change the situation: fix your circumstances or change your mindset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both are very hard to do and may well be impossible, depending on your financial or family situation or other obligations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t think it&amp;rsquo;s fair to expect people to always follow through on what they know to be best practice. Circumstances vary. You should try, if possible, but no judgement if you can&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this should make us reconsider our relationship with the people whose advice and ideas we read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Idolising &amp;lsquo;thought-leaders&amp;rsquo;, putting those with a knack for being glib and charming up on a pedestal, uncritically mimicking what people &lt;em&gt;say&lt;/em&gt; they do, are all thoroughly bad ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People are what they do. You are what you do. Let your actions be informed by what you read and hear, but always apply ideas with a critical and experimental mindset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And always take the ideas of those whose publicly documented practices match what they say and recommend more seriously than the ideas of those whose practices don&amp;rsquo;t. We need to become better at distinguishing between those who speak from practice and those who are just performative social media influencers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>