<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</title>
    <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529</link>
    <description>_(**Note**: The first four posts in this thread have been moved from https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/what-would-a-fediverse-governance-body-look-like/1497)_

I&#39;d like to start at looking what triggered this topic, a [fedi discussion](https://mastodon.social/web/statuses/105876132191612591) with lotsa interesting background (started by me pointing to reasons why Signal chose to be centralized and [@rysiek](https://mastodon.social/@rysiek) following-up)

Some important points as I see them:

- Fediverse is evolving quite slowly, our greatest strength (decentralization) is our weakness too (fragmentation).
- Our developer base is quite small, and SocialCG / SocialHub has low activity. Time is our most precious commodity.
- Many open issues stay open, things drag on, onboarding is really bad, documentation is lagging, involvement is ad-hoc.

In theory **this is all fine**. After all, most devs are here for the fun, passion, and excitement to run cool FOSS projects.

But it also makes us weak in a rapidly evolving world of tech. There&#39;s a real danger we are outmanouvered, become irrelevant or even tombstoned in the long term.

I&#39;ll copy some text from https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/rationale-for-participation-in-socialhub/1486 now:

&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;My collapsed argument that AP/Fedi evolution too slow, making us weak and needing focal points of coordination (click to expand).&lt;/summary&gt;

On AP / Fedi itself I notice that - while its install base is healthy-ish - its dev community overall is very small and thus quite weak-ish in upholding innovation pace. And the fragmentation by which development takes place is hampering fedi + standards evolution, imho.

Though we are proponents of decentralized technology our community needs central focal points to coordinate, where &quot;the family&quot; comes together, so to say. In this we only really have SocialCG and SocialHub (plus #social irc channel, and some matrix rooms, but they are less effective for knowledge gathering and coordination). A metric ton of useful developer information goes lost each day, because it happens on isolated islands and others aren&#39;t aware. The onboarding experience for new devs that want their apps to federate and make sense of the technology is horrible.

And as a result AP / Fediverse innovation &amp; evolution speed is lagging imho, when compared to other decentralized technologies. Even though we have truly production-ready platforms, tested to reality, slowly other tech may become the more attractive candidates. Solid project, though doing zero community-building and having no apps in production is 3x as large as SocialHub, and SAFE community is 16x as large, IPFS 10x exceeds our little group.

There was excitement and trepidation about Jack Dorsey&#39;s Bluesky report. But the questions are a) if they&#39;d choose AP could we handle it and b) if they&#39;d choose another tech could we handle it? We should not become irrelevant, folks. We want to lobby the EU to become a recognized interop standard, but we currently simply have no good story.  Finally I wan to once more point to https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/are-we-ready-for-the-threats-to-the-fediverse-and-decentralization-movement/810

&lt;/details&gt;

## Community engagement

The above leads me to conclude that we need more _community engagement_:

:loudspeaker: &amp;nbsp; **We urgently need a stronger SocialHub to reinforce the ActivityPub ecosystem !**

The problem with this is that rallying of the community, advocating, housekeeping (besides in general being an unthankful job) takes really a humongous amount of time! And here it was raised that:

&gt; Maybe the community needs a **donation-funded foundation** that enables people to spend more time on these things. Most devs lack bandwidth. Such foundation could have very exciting way in which it is set up, i.e. as a real **innovation center** that truly involves people from all walks of life, and stimulates to think about tech differently.

Rysiekúr then brought the discussion to our [Fediverse Policy Special Interest Group](https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/c/meeting/fediverse-policy/59) (where things stalled after 1st meetups) with:

&gt; How do we get policymakers etc. to know about fediverse and treat fediverse seriously? [..] the pitch to users, developers, mastohosters and other fedifolk would be:
&gt; 
&gt;&gt; Important fedi-affecting legislation is being passed or discussed:
&gt;&gt;  - implementation of the Copyright Directive
&gt; &gt; - discussion on Digital Services Act and Digital Markets Act

Ending the argument by stating:

&gt; :speaking_head: &amp;nbsp; **Fediverse needs to have a loud, well-resourced voice.**

My argument on this point is that our Interoperability &#39;sales pitch&#39; to e.g. politicians is also quite weak:

- The good part: We have 2 great W3C Recommendations with AS/AP that build on other standards!
- Then we have some de-facto standards, where you have to figure out how they are implemented across the board.
- Then you&#39;d have to find out all the hidden complexities of federation by literally digging through code bases and issue trackers!
- Then we have no good places where to ask for support, no process guidance, a very early-days FEP process, etc.
- And most of our interop experiences are limited to a Microblogging domain.

Interoperability constitutes a complete package, that just doesn&#39;t exist at the moment.

## Fediverse foundation

&quot;We need a foundation, you say?&quot;. Yes, I think so. The &quot;governance&quot; body - even though in scare quotes - is a bit of a formal start.

&gt; From The Free Dictionary: [**Foundation**](https://www.thefreedictionary.com/foundation)
&gt; - that on which something is founded; basis
&gt; - the base on which something stands
&gt; - an institution supported by an endowment, often one that provides funds for charities, research, etc
&gt; - the charter incorporating or establishing a society or institution and the statutes or rules governing its affairs

I think its main tasks should be:

1. Organizer of &#39;focal points&#39; where community comes together, coordinates and becomes stronger (e.g. by rallying, advocacy).
2. Presenting a unified face, our &#39;official&#39; front office to the outside world.
3. Be a collector and distributor of funds to any people playing active roles in evolving the fediverse.

This foundation would be really something that belongs to all of us, representing and defending the fediverse&#39;s interests. It needs not have a very formal organization structure / governance model.

- It wouldn&#39;t be authoritative in tech decisions (SocialCG + SocialHub are for that).
- Certainly not have Presidents and Board of Directors and all that jazz.
- It would not be co-opted by accepting big tech money.
- It&#39;d be totally transparent in how it operates, and where funds are spent.

Maybe some people heavily involved on a daily basis may earn some sort of modest income from their efforts. Other than that:

- The foundation might crowdsource their activities
- Activities are prioritized based on their merits to the community
- A bounty model of funding might serve to reward those carrying them out

## Humane technology

_(**Note**: This was originally posted [here](https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/what-would-a-fediverse-governance-body-look-like/1497/17?u=aschrijver))_

I have another discussion going with members of the Humane Tech Community about [&quot;What makes a Humane Technologist?&quot;](https://community.humanetech.com/t/what-makes-a-humane-technologist/5174) that is quite interesting and has relevancy to how a foundation can position itself:

- While [pondering fedi slogans](https://mastodon.social/@humanetech/105492005146865341) I think _&quot;Social Media Reimagined&quot;_ can be a true paradigm to follow, and a rallying cry too.
- With that Fediverse can be a veritable playground, makers space and innovation labs for _would-be_ humane technologists.
- As it evolves around its community values and culture, embracing best practices, it&#39;ll be an _exemplar of humane technology_.</description>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Jun 2021 09:28:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <category>Fediverse Futures</category>
    <atom:link href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
        <title>Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[hamishcampbell]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="aschrijver" data-post="34" data-topic="1529">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/aschrijver/40/278_2.png" class="avatar"> aschrijver:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Without involvement there’s nothing to govern, no ‘power’ to distribute democratically.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Power comes from power, It’s something you TAKE/build and in the best outcome share,  it is never given to you.</p>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Private_property" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Private property - Wikipedia</a> was invented in a mythical past when someone with a big club drew a line in the sand and said to the social group step over that, and I kill you.</p>
<p>Notice this is not the foundation of the fediverse, we are base on an open flowing social web and our lines in the sand are “blowing in the wind”. Yes, lots of people do not understand this.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/36">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/36</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jun 2021 07:36:55 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1529-36</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529.rss">Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[hamishcampbell]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>“The is such a thing as society” we need to build our tools for this anti “common sense” statement.</p>
<p>The advantage of “governance” of the fediverse (which it needs if it is to become a part of our <span class="hashtag">#openweb</span> based society that is essential for social change/challenge in the era of <span class="hashtag">#climatechaos</span>) is that the is non, this is a good thing.</p>
<p>The Fediverse comes from the “cats” of libertarianism and to a lesser extent anarchism without the (O)</p>
<p>In this, we don’t HAVE to think how it fits into current working practices and current economics. Rather, people PUSHING these “common sense” solutions to the fediverse “governance” problems are a part of the problem, not a solution that might work.</p>
<p>To be “native” to the fediverse we need to use code to build “society”.  <a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529"> Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment </a> has to be anti “common sense” as the fediverse  itself is.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/35">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/35</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jun 2021 07:17:09 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1529-35</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529.rss">Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="mariha" data-post="33" data-topic="1529">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/mariha/40/1133_2.png" class="avatar"> mariha:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Enjoy!</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Thanks a lot for posting, <a class="mention" href="/u/mariha">@mariha</a>, I did enjoy reading them. A lot of aspects are very recognizable and are at play in some form or other in most IT companies. In companies I’ve worked for in the past there are two specifically that were in opposite extremes of Autonomy and Inclusiveness:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>The first one was where the founders developed the initial prototype and based on that thought they were most in-the-know of all technical ins and outs as the company grew, and that ‘IT was easy’. They dictated product direction and Marketing was at their level, kept away from devs, and product features sold before they existed. That was, as you can imagine, highly frustrating.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The other company was marvelous. With hundreds of employees they truly retained ‘startup culture’, everyone tech-savvy and with business accumen where it was needed. More than 60 nationalities intermingling, truly diverse, everyone highly autonomous in a flat organization structure (tribes + squads in a spotify engineering culture). Highly agile.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>This last organization, it seems to me, comes really close to what you were proposing. Yet here new challenges arose, and these challenges are also relatable (in a way) to what SocialHub faces currently. Some characteristics at play there:</p>
<ul>
<li>GOOD: Very autonomous; low ceremony; informal and social interaction, leading to highly productive teams.</li>
<li>HARD: How to keep overview, the grander picture: a comprehensive product portfolio</li>
<li>HARD: Balance between informal + formal procedures, and how that impacts organization + culture.</li>
<li>HARD: Providing incentives to inform oneself (reserve time) to know what others are doing.</li>
</ul>
<p>Some real challenges we bumped into:</p>
<ul>
<li>Keeping things very informal works best to a certain extent, until teams e.g. start to diverge and no longer feel the need attend sprint reviews, read retrospectives of other teams.</li>
<li>Keeping each other informed about knowledge and insights, decisions, gets ever harder. Part of our Definition of Done of stories and epics included having minimal level of documentation, but bringing this together and have others read it was another story.</li>
<li>We transitioned to a microservices architecture, and architects became like Priests while devs were Atheists, unwilling to read the Bible. Everyone was a bit too independent.</li>
</ul>
<p>If we project this on SocialHub community as if it were a business, then:</p>
<ul>
<li>Autonomy is total. There is no boss, and there is no common direction from the perspective of team (federated project) deliverables.</li>
<li>With all FOSS projects there are much more ad-hoc roadmaps and short-term needs wrt AP are fulfilled. There’s little incentive to invest in the future and spend time in a community that is not directly project-related.</li>
<li>When investing time at SocialHub, project devs like to spend it mostly on technical stuff, much less on ‘brainstorming the future’ and even less doing the community chores.</li>
<li>If other people <em>are</em> doing community chores, they still need active involvement of devs for them to be relevant at all. Without feedback and consent community volunteers will meld away.</li>
</ul>
<p>Incentives are key.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em><strong>Why should one spend time at SocialHub at all? What is in it for me? What’s the win-win I get for my project?</strong></em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>In theory it is simple:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em><strong>If the tech foundation, AS/AP et al, stops evolving, then it will wither and eventually become irrelevant. And with that probably dev projects will suffer too.</strong></em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>But in practice asking people to be involved with the community is similar to asking to care for the environment: we all know it is going to hell, but do not adjust our lifestyle to extent we should.</p>
<p>Note that a governance model, that is discussed on this forum in a somewhat different context, is also no solution. Without involvement there’s nothing to govern, no ‘power’ to distribute democratically.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/34">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/34</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jun 2021 05:09:56 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1529-34</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529.rss">Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[mariha]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I think best what I can do is to just link here some of my docs:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1V94wJFu-LZRkqSHXlBiOGNaqc74uV1T-lRzFiBfK-yM/edit" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Dev culture fix</a><br>
It contains some of my observations, distilled as if it was not me taking part in them. If it contains names of some of my upper managers it is just to add context, I don’t write anything personal about anyone.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/19-a4qYjqXTb8cV_-C0X39KC5zI0C7nLJpwZQJ7MDa5Y/edit" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Cloud Object Storage<br>
change strategy<br>
grassroots proposal</a><br>
On page 7-8 have a proposition of solution - team structure - that may be (or not) most interesting to you. It was a solution as I saw it then and there, I don’t think of it as the ultimate, universal or final solution. I was heavily challenged all the way as I tried to explain my perspective and ideas so it may seem overly explanatory.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Together, they are a record of some of the efforts I made to make the world around me more that I could last there. Now it seems funny how serous I was about it.</p>
<p>You can comment on them if you’d like to.</p>
<p>They are based on some very personal experiences - though not described here and everything is written as impersonal as I could. I wanted to sound professional <img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/images/emoji/twitter/wink.png?v=9" title=":wink:" class="emoji" alt=":wink:"> I kind of practiced participatory observation at the time.</p>
<p>Enjoy!<br>
I am especially proud of the apx B, proposal of improvement, that almost whole engineering team supported.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/33">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/33</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jun 2021 02:09:15 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1529-33</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529.rss">Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[how]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Did you try the ‘Poll’ option from the composer?</p>
<p>I usually tend to avoid voting as it often shortcuts a proper discussion to reach consensus or at least to explore the complexity of a given issue. This is why I don’t like things like Loomio or Liquid Democracy.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/32">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/32</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2021 13:05:14 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1529-32</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529.rss">Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[mariha]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>No preference for the voting tool. I think voting in general is very interesting and grateful domain to work on and craft tools.</p>
<p>Ukuvota has great rationale in the manual.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/31">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/31</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 07:13:25 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1529-31</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529.rss">Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Yes, I think both <a class="mention" href="/u/hamishcampbell">@hamishcampbell</a> and me are interested to get any feedback you have on the subject…</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/30">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/30</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 07:02:31 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1529-30</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529.rss">Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[mariha]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>As I read them right now I think they are very good points. I remember that when I read the text first time I wasn’t convinced but then re-read it and thought it was very good, though that something was missing (to built an inclusive culture).</p>
<p>I have some notes from the times it was very relevant to me, if you were interested I could dig into them and try to find out what I thought.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/29">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/29</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 06:55:46 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1529-29</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529.rss">Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="mariha" data-post="26" data-topic="1529">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/mariha/40/1133_2.png" class="avatar"> mariha:</div>
<blockquote>
<p><em>The tyranny of structurelessness</em> comes to my mind. Not sure if I agreed with proposed solutions though.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>PS. They are quoted here: <a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/what-would-a-fediverse-governance-body-look-like/1497/79" class="inline-onebox">What would a fediverse "governance" body look like? - #79 by aschrijver</a></p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="mariha" data-post="27" data-topic="1529">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/mariha/40/1133_2.png" class="avatar"> mariha:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Loosely related, I found recently <a href="https://ukuvota.world/#/">Ukuvota</a> which is a tool to facilitate cooperative decision making for collectives.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Interesting tool, thank you.<br>
In an recent SocialCG <a class="mention" href="/u/bengo">@bengo</a> mentioned Loomio and support stacked ranked voting: <a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/2021-04-23-social-cg-meeting/1621/25" class="inline-onebox">2021-04-23 Social CG meeting - #25 by bengo</a> (I was in favor of trying to use what this forum offers).</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/28">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/28</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jun 2021 04:56:34 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1529-28</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529.rss">Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[mariha]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Very interesting discussion. It actually made me feel like at home <img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/images/emoji/twitter/upside_down_face.png?v=9" title=":upside_down_face:" class="emoji" alt=":upside_down_face:"></p>
<p>Loosely related, I found recently <a href="https://ukuvota.world/#/" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Ukuvota</a> which is a tool to facilitate cooperative decision making for collectives. The <em>Manual</em> is worth reading, imho.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/27">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/27</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 23:33:50 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1529-27</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529.rss">Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[mariha]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I could sign with both hands under this:</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="calummackervoy" data-post="4" data-topic="1529">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/calummackervoy/40/427_2.png" class="avatar"> calummackervoy:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>when you don’t formalise or address power dynamics in an organisation, they still exist but they’re not clear. I think that it can end up being <strong>less</strong> open/decentralised without formalisation</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p><em>The tyranny of structurelessness</em> comes to my mind. Not sure if I agreed with proposed solutions though.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/26">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/26</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 23:32:27 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1529-26</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529.rss">Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[hamishcampbell]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Lets set up a BBB on this after soon after these current events.</p>
<p>Am  working on fascinating stuff that comes for 30 years of actually working in and with radically decentralized networks. we do have working solutions to meany issues - the challenge is turning them into code and scaling them.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/25">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/25</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 18 Apr 2021 16:59:36 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1529-25</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529.rss">Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Results of <a href="https://mastodon.social/web/statuses/106046277371635193">the poll</a> are in. Not too many respondents (47 in all):</p>
<ul>
<li>
<strong>70%</strong> are in favor of fostering strong community.</li>
<li>
<strong>30%</strong> think things are fine as they currently are.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Update</strong>: Note that in terms of engagement 24% of our user base (107 out of 443) have visited the forum in the last 30 days (i.e. since <a class="mention" href="/u/how">@how</a> announced the EC event). Not a bad number.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/24">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/24</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 18 Apr 2021 11:28:31 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1529-24</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529.rss">Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[hamishcampbell]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>We live in oligarchy.</p>
<p>"Democracy arose from the idea that those who are equal in any respect are equal absolutely. All are alike free, therefore they claim that all are free absolutely… The next is when the democrats, on the grounds that they are all equal, claim equal participation in everything.</p>
<p>It is accepted as democratic when public offices are allocated by lot; and as oligarchic when they are filled by election."</p>
<aside class="onebox wikipedia">
  <header class="source">
      <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iron_law_of_oligarchy" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">en.wikipedia.org</a>
  </header>
  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:220/293;"><img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/original/1X/2d32dd7baac8f0120e420c3acf008ac2da3fca55.jpeg" class="thumbnail" width="220" height="293"></div>

<h3><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iron_law_of_oligarchy" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Iron law of oligarchy</a></h3>

<p>
 The iron law of oligarchy is a political theory first developed by the German sociologist Robert Michels in his 1911 book, Political Parties. It asserts that rule by an elite, or oligarchy, is inevitable as an "iron law" within any democratic organization as part of the "tactical and technical necessities" of organization.
 Michels's theory states that all complex organizations, regardless of how democratic they are when started, eventually develop into oligarchies. Michels observed that since ...</p>

  </article>
  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>
  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>The “liberal fig leaf” you put in front of the foundation will fall off the first time the wind blows.</p>
<p>Yes it is easy to run down this hill, yes you can force this into place, few people will try and stop you.</p>
<p>But before you do this please think - Do we in the fedivers want to live in oligarchy or are we actually building something different.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/23">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/23</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2021 09:32:45 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1529-23</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529.rss">Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[hamishcampbell]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>This kinda thinking generally wins in the end as <span class="hashtag">#mainstreaming</span> is a down hill run - we need a stop running down this hill, really just stop for a bit to take a breath. Take a moment, contemplate, who are we empowering?</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/22">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/22</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2021 09:21:24 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1529-22</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529.rss">Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>As a way of thinking about community I like “Community Digital Garden” as explained in this IndieHackers post:</p>
<blockquote>
<h2>
<a name="community-digital-gardenhttpswwwindiehackerscompostbuilding-a-community-digital-garden-7e941d107c" class="anchor" href="#community-digital-gardenhttpswwwindiehackerscompostbuilding-a-community-digital-garden-7e941d107c"></a><a href="https://www.indiehackers.com/post/building-a-community-digital-garden-7e941d107c">Community Digital Garden</a>
</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.indiehackers.com/post/building-a-community-digital-garden-7e941d107c"><img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/original/1X/edfe82b368ce48c6e4a2145203636bb32fde41f7.png" alt="Community process cycle" data-base62-sha1="xXorHDjPnMFP4WMfAoFZrIz5EPR" width="690" height="388"></a></p>
<p>When I think about what is needed to maintain a community digital garden, I think of these things:</p>
<ul>
<li>the need for curation: the world moves fast, there needs to be a way to constantly stay on top of what is happening in your industry</li>
<li>the need for expertise: we need to be constantly tapping into people and their knowledge</li>
<li>the need for a process: just like a business, a community digital garden will die a death if there isn’t some kind of process to keep it in place.</li>
<li>and of course, the need to build community around all of these things</li>
</ul>
<p>Some community garden thoughts that spring to mind:</p>
<ul>
<li>When you build a community it is about growing together.</li>
<li>Things will look simple and clean to begin with, but can quickly become messy and disorganized.</li>
<li>When building a community it is easy to fall into the trap of getting measured by the number of posts, comments, or views, rather than the combined and potential value</li>
<li>It’s important to look at the long term value of content and what it means to your community</li>
<li>Members can easily default to (lazily) checking and posting from the homepage or forum, over taking time to search and discover</li>
<li>Educating your community about where you are heading is probably key to making it work as they can then hopefully align their actions to help you</li>
<li>It doesn’t need to mean that everyone has access to add or edit everything, it’s more about having some kind of commitment to creating continual value based on the contributions from the community</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>The foundation team addresses these things and would take care that the cycle runs smoothly.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/21">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/21</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2021 07:10:17 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1529-21</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529.rss">Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <h1>
<a name="fedi-poll-active-community-engagement-yes-nohttpsmastodonsocialwebstatuses106046277371635193" class="anchor" href="#fedi-poll-active-community-engagement-yes-nohttpsmastodonsocialwebstatuses106046277371635193"></a><a href="https://mastodon.social/web/statuses/106046277371635193">Fedi Poll: Active community engagement Yes / No</a>
</h1>
<p>I sent a poll to fediverse. It will still run for 5 days and has 44 responses thus far:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><a href="https://mastodon.social/tags/decentralization">#decentralization</a> are key success factors of <a href="https://mastodon.social/tags/fediverse">#fediverse</a> … but they also come with weaknesses.</p>
<p>Fedi is still a brittle flower, and the <a href="https://mastodon.social/tags/activitypub">#activitypub</a> techbase it stands on is developed ad-hoc. Fragmented across projects &amp; groups we create custom app extensions. <a href="https://mastodon.social/tags/interoperability">#interoperability</a> is on case-by-case basis, with few deep integrations across different app domains.</p>
<p>We must foster more cooperation, inclusive and growing community, advocacy at <a href="https://mastodon.social/tags/SocialHub">#SocialHub</a> so we can go next-level.</p>
<hr>
<ul>
<li>
<p><span class="chcklst-box fa fa-square-o fa-fw"></span>   I agree. Strong community creates strong ecosystem</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><span class="chcklst-box fa fa-square-o fa-fw"></span>   It is fine as it is. Things move at their own pace</p>
</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>Will update the results here, once the poll is closed.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/20">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/20</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2021 05:22:29 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1529-20</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529.rss">Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Wonderful, I love your feedback, <a class="mention" href="/u/natacha">@natacha</a>. It is indeed a lot of my posts here, as I am sketching my thoughts to other SocialHub members. And in hopes of getting responses back, so… yours is very welcome.</p>
<p>I see this as start of a long-running process to collect the broad input that is indeed needed. Besides here, I’ve sent various toots on fedi,  and currently <a href="https://mastodon.social/web/statuses/106046277371635193">running a poll</a>. I will continue to inform fedi like that, among others.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="natacha" data-post="18" data-topic="1529">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8491ac/40.png" class="avatar"> natacha:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I understand this is second degree however I still I think it is a very strange assumption, first you assume that all people here are “devs” whatever that means.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Please take my assumptions with a grain of salt. They are meant to get a discussion going. The SocialHub has a heavy technical focus (e.g. one of my posts got response from another member that it was not technical enough for this forum). Also SocialCG meetups, while “everyone is welcome to participate” often have such high technical level, that I - as software developer - feel intimidated to raise my voice. I encounter this overly technical focus everywhere, also beyond SocialHub.</p>
<p>Since some time I am advocating to make this community more inclusive for people with a broad range of skills, expertise levels and backgrounds. And to combine our efforts in more holistic approach to fedi innovation. There is a lot of potential that remains untapped. So I started the <a class="hashtag" href="/c/fediversity/fediverse-futures/58">#<span>fediversity:fediverse-futures</span></a> which I am also promoting on fedi and <a href="https://lemmy.ml/c/fediversefutures">recently on Lemmy</a> too.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="natacha" data-post="18" data-topic="1529">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8491ac/40.png" class="avatar"> natacha:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Well not sure what you mean by this</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>All the things that require community activity progress very slowly or stall altogether, due mostly I think by lack of time by those involved. Numerous threads in this forum are inconclusive, with no satisfying outcome or follow-up. Open issues in the spec repo’s remain unaddressed. Meanwhile everyone is furthering their own apps, filling in the blanks in custom ways. It might not be bad, because at least there’s progress, but things can be so much more streamlined. And there’s a win-win for projects if they do so. Right now imho (may be just my impression) the fedi technology base is more diverging and fragmenting rather than converging on a common direction.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="natacha" data-post="18" data-topic="1529">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8491ac/40.png" class="avatar"> natacha:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Again I do not see this as a problem we have a lot running and what seems to be more needed as you also rightly say is to understand how to build meaningful community organisation.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>“innovation pace” was probably badly phrased. There’s no need for speed, but for streamlining, not <em>wasting</em> time unnecessary (preferably win time via synergy), and - importantly “we have a lot running” and what we already have is very hard and complex for newcomers to master. If the onboarding experience were better, we’d get a lot more helping hands.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="natacha" data-post="18" data-topic="1529">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8491ac/40.png" class="avatar"> natacha:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Foundation is indeed a good idea, then it should be much larger then only encompassing the developers universe</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>In my proposal the goal is healthy evolution of the entire technology base on which the Fediverse stands. I see SocialHub as a community of technologists, which is much broader indeed than “devs”. As I see it: Everyone involved anywhere in the software / project / product development cycle in broadest sense, including those that advocate the technology.</p>
<p>The foundation supports SocialHub… ‘a foundation to a tech foundation’.</p>
<p>The community might be even broader positioned and also address socio-cultural and political etc. concerns, be a representative for entire fedi. But I’d argue against that, as that is just too much (at <a href="https://community.humanetech.com">Humane Tech Community</a> which I founded and still facilitate, a too broad audience was what made community engagement nigh impossible).</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/19">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/19</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2021 12:34:59 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1529-19</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529.rss">Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[natacha]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>nice discussion, I only wanted to add a fez notes, first while I really like the idea of a foundation, I think any discussion of it should be happening collectively and in this thread I mainly see the contribution of one person. To have any validity this idea should have more input, as chances are that many preople here have a lot of experience in groups and knowledge about organisational models.</p>
<p>Secondly my feeling is there are a lot of assumptions this post is starting from and I do not see them as obvious:</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="aschrijver" data-post="1" data-topic="1529">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/aschrijver/40/278_2.png" class="avatar"> aschrijver:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>In theory <strong>this is all fine</strong> . After all, most devs are here for the fun, passion, and excitement to run cool FOSS projects.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I understand this is second degree however I still I think it is a very strange assumption, first you assume that all people here are “devs” whatever that means.<br>
Secondly you assume that people face up saying they  do not have a long term professional plan within this community, I did not see this happening around here quite the contrary.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="aschrijver" data-post="1" data-topic="1529">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/aschrijver/40/278_2.png" class="avatar"> aschrijver:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>The problem with this is that rallying of the community, advocating, housekeeping (besides in general being an unthankful job) takes really a humongous amount of time!</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Well not sure what you mean by this but certainly there is absolutely no room in actual funding schemes for community organisation within AP, we probably should be looking fro these. Foundation is indeed a good idea, then it should be much larger then only encompassing the developers universe, and the first conversation here should be: with whom do we want to work.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="aschrijver" data-post="1" data-topic="1529">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/aschrijver/40/278_2.png" class="avatar"> aschrijver:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>quite weak-ish in upholding innovation pace</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Again I do not see this as a problem we have a lot running and what seems to be more needed as you also rightly say is to understand how to build meaningful community organisation.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="how" data-post="16" data-topic="1529">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/how/40/94_2.png" class="avatar"> how:</div>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>What would make this community inviting to oppressed groups, that would empower them?</strong></p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Those groups are the only ones who have the answer and they already have community organisation systems. So best is to take from our time to ask them, rather then take from their time to ask them to come to us.<br>
To understand what is needed by communities developers need to step out from their comfort zones, stop modelling what they think people need, and actively organize to inquire  about what communities really need.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/18">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/18</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2021 11:35:05 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1529-18</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529.rss">Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="how" data-post="16" data-topic="1529">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/how/40/94_2.png" class="avatar"> how:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>IMO this is where we’re currently failing. Intead of focusing on the self-reflecting circle of developers, who are already sufficiently diverse and not aligned – everybody seems to have taken a part of the territory in the form of apps (pictures, videos, links, etc.) and converging towards my-app-is-doing-it-all</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p><img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/images/emoji/twitter/100.png?v=9" title=":100:" class="emoji only-emoji" alt=":100:"></p>
<p>+100 here. My perception is that most ppl see the community forum here as a place where sometimes an interesting question comes in, or a nice event is organised, but not as the <strong>essential place where we work towards the next-gen versions of the technology + standards that all federated apps are ultimately standing on</strong>, and there’s a blindness to the fact that <strong>active participation here is ultimately a win-win for everyone</strong>, including for your own project.</p>
<p>Other than that I, of course, wholly agree that we should strive to empower any oppressed group. But in general I’d say this means <strong>we should be open and embracing to anyone</strong> and encourage them to participate, no matter what their background is (as long as they are adhering to our code of ethics policy, being the only condition).</p>
<p>We are a <em>humane technology</em> group, as I see it. So when it comes to oppressed groups we can specifically address topics to solving problems these groups have to deal with. And we should very explicitly <strong>advocate for oppressed groups and people to join our community</strong>. Joining should be in their interest, and after all they know the problem space best.</p>
<p>Problems like: how can we avoid toxicity to arise, how can we suppress it, how can we protect people from it. But also: how can we facilitate people that are not as highly educated, are lacking financial means to e.g. self-host infrastructure, help them set up organization and target non-English speaking regions of the world. And too: Help those that do not have the same freedoms we have, e.g. living in authoritarian regimes, or cultures where their being different is frowned upon. Etcetera.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/17">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/17</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 09 Apr 2021 07:58:38 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1529-17</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529.rss">Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[how]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="hamishcampbell" data-post="14" data-topic="1529">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/hamishcampbell/40/284_2.png" class="avatar"> hamishcampbell:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Q. who are we empowing with this body - no smoke please.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>IMO this is where we’re currently failing. Intead of focusing on the self-reflecting circle of developers, who are already sufficiently diverse and not aligned – everybody seems to have taken a part of the territory in the form of apps (pictures, videos, links, etc.) and converging towards my-app-is-doing-it-all, instead, we should look in the mirror and figure that most of the people here are white males sitting in comfortable chairs ; and do something to change this. We already started by inviting non-technicians (related to academy or policy) but it is very insufficient. <strong>What would make this community inviting to oppressed groups, that would empower them?</strong> This is the main issue I’m trying to figure out if I really want to bring a satisfactory response to this question.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group quote-modified" data-username="hamishcampbell" data-post="14" data-topic="1529">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/hamishcampbell/40/284_2.png" class="avatar"> hamishcampbell:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Q. blowing smoke over a process to get it to happen has bad outcomes, what ideas to get this to happen in pla[i]n site?</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Ongoing conversation is crucial to this process, isn’t it?</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/16">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/16</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 09 Apr 2021 07:30:52 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1529-16</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529.rss">Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="hamishcampbell" data-post="14" data-topic="1529">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/hamishcampbell/40/284_2.png" class="avatar"> hamishcampbell:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>“I intentionally limited the Foundation concept to SocialHub only” good move, but you know that if this works it will grow to become a governance body for the <span class="hashtag">#fedivers</span>, so we are talking about the same thing.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Not really, and there’s no smoke. I am a suggesting <em>a foundation to SocialHub</em>, nothing more nothing less. So consider this bulb:</p>
<div align="center">
<p><div class="lightbox-wrapper"><a class="lightbox" href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/original/1X/e55f9157e5de4b7e139d61e0500138f9b0259665.gif" data-download-href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/e55f9157e5de4b7e139d61e0500138f9b0259665" title="Light-Bulb-PNG-File"><img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/optimized/1X/e55f9157e5de4b7e139d61e0500138f9b0259665_2_187x250.gif" alt="Light-Bulb-PNG-File" data-base62-sha1="wJ85O8lvB7XoM6IPjvqEVlKYzxX" width="187" height="250" srcset="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/optimized/1X/e55f9157e5de4b7e139d61e0500138f9b0259665_2_187x250.gif, https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/optimized/1X/e55f9157e5de4b7e139d61e0500138f9b0259665_2_280x375.gif 1.5x, https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/optimized/1X/e55f9157e5de4b7e139d61e0500138f9b0259665_2_374x500.gif 2x" data-small-upload="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/optimized/1X/e55f9157e5de4b7e139d61e0500138f9b0259665_2_10x10.png"><div class="meta">
<svg class="fa d-icon d-icon-far-image svg-icon" aria-hidden="true"><use xlink:href="#far-image"></use></svg><span class="filename">Light-Bulb-PNG-File</span><span class="informations">450×600 60.6 KB</span><svg class="fa d-icon d-icon-discourse-expand svg-icon" aria-hidden="true"><use xlink:href="#discourse-expand"></use></svg>
</div></a></div></p>
</div>
<ul>
<li>The anode at the bottom is the Foundation</li>
<li>It feeds energy into the next ‘layer’, the SocialHub community</li>
<li>SocialHub members with knowledge gained through their collaboration, shine brilliant light into the Fedi through their apps.</li>
</ul>
<p>There’s no direct influence on the fedi. Want to benefit from the foundation? Please join SocialHub and participate.</p>
<p>On Q1: We empower the devs directly. This forum contains tons of never addressed open issues, as no one has time for them. Meanwhile everyone goes their own way in their own issue tracker, and whatever chat app they use. The standardization track grinds <em>really</em> slowly, community doesn’t grow, new devs have a horrible time, and even existing devs are wasting time reinventing wheels (looking in other codebases, for instance).</p>
<p>On Q2: This whole conversation is already happening in plain site, and I am tooting about it. The foundation itself can also operate fully in the open. I don’t see a reason why there should be hidden agenda’s. Though maybe some things are trust-level-2 membership-only, just as they are now on this forum (i.e. the Wellbeing group access).</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/15">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/15</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 31 Mar 2021 13:28:26 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1529-15</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529.rss">Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[hamishcampbell]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>This is both a step in a grassroots direction and some waving of  smoke and mirrors <img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/images/emoji/twitter/slight_smile.png?v=9" title=":slight_smile:" class="emoji" alt=":slight_smile:"></p>
<p>“I intentionally limited the Foundation concept to SocialHub only” good move, but you know that if this works it will grow to become a governance body for the <span class="hashtag">#fedivers</span>, so we are talking about the same thing. The act of blowing smoke over this has a BAD HISTORY and bad outcomes, so best to say clearly what the agender is.</p>
<p>Q. who are we empowing with this body - no smoke please.<br>
Q. blowing smoke over a process to get it to happen has bad outcomes, what ideas to get this to happen in plan site?</p>
<p>Are some starting issues</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/14">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/14</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 31 Mar 2021 12:22:02 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1529-14</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529.rss">Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>If I interpret things correctly, then in your first article you are saying that:</p>
<ul>
<li>Fedi is at heart an anarchist project (I prefer to say “truly grassroots”, is more broad, less politically charged)</li>
<li>There are issues + there’s always a precarious balance between moving towards capitalism vs. (anarchist-flavored) socialism.</li>
<li>We lack firm socialist roots in SocialHub, where we just have a very loose structure and group of people.</li>
</ul>
<p>Though I prefer not packaging in all the loaded political terminology, I agree with this in general.</p>
<p>In the second article you talk about the <em>horizontal globalisation movement</em> -  a term I wasn’t familiar with - which I translate into encouragement and establishmentof healthy global and flat organization structures, as referred to above, with many groups involved and influencing decision-making based on strong democratic principles.</p>
<p>Very much agree with such movement. I think doing this right is sorely needed. Right now the world is full of groups doing really good things, but utterly fragmented and divided. New mechanisms that act as a binding force and unite people based on principles mutualism and synergy must be discovered and propagated (note that I am myself working on such things with <a href="https://innercircles.community">innercircles</a> which in its core is a life philosophy).</p>
<p>You then continue in the article to conclude that - while initially on a good track - things went wrong with horizontal globalisation, because:</p>
<ul>
<li>The bad parts of human nature kicked in (a very generalized summary I made from the bullet points).</li>
<li>And to such extent (domination, authoritarian control) that it thwarted and sabotaged the entire process.</li>
</ul>
<p>I hope my interpretation is more or less on the spot. I’ll muse a bit on it in context of this topic…</p>
<hr>
<p>These dangers always exist, cannot be taken away. Instead they must be mitigated and not allowed to become dominant factors. I very much believe in the concept of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mutualism_(economic_theory)"><strong>mutualism</strong></a> here, and the win-wins they lead to and the opportunity to create <em>additional</em> synergy flows from mutualist relationships. In innercircles there’s a concept of continual maximization of synergy through mutualism in a virtuous cycle.</p>
<p>In that process the mechanism is such that, if parties act in self-interested ways, they place themselves outside of this loop, and naturally become less interesting to cooperate with. It is quite okay if they do so, its their own free choice, but they’ll miss out on their own opportunities. Opportunities, after all, are the ones you shape yourself. Also - when you scale such system globally - there are always enough other parties to choose from that <em>do</em> believe in mutualism and act accordingly.</p>
<p>I intentionally limited the Foundation concept to SocialHub only. Looking at the <a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/socialhub-and-spiral-island-a-fediverse-foundation-analogy/1543">Spiral Island</a> analogy, we are a very small group of island inhabitants, and our island is tiny. When we walk on it everything bounces and moves below our feet, and occasionally we get wet shoes. But our building tasks are quite manageable, and along the way we can experiment what works and what not. Failures are only learning experiences to do things better the next time.</p>
<p>With the current - too low - activity within the community, I feel that most AP devs and others interested in healthy fedi evolution, don’t grasp the importance of the analogy. That it is in their own interest to spend time at SocialHub, and that everything we do here, leads to direct mutualistic advantage further on.</p>
<p>This idea is what we must promote, and what imho should be one of the tasks of the Foundation itself. Not doing so will eventually and inevitably lead to the creation of many islands, not connected together, and just as fragmented and lonely any good initiative I mentioned above.</p>
<p>With mutualism central, ‘governance’ becomes easier and it is is in the realm of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Consensus_decision-making">consensus decision-making</a>.</p>
<p>Note, btw, that all these concepts are important for innercircles too, and I am looking for these concepts to be glued into federated, humane technology apps, to allow them to scale. My efforts with <a class="hashtag" href="/c/fediversity/fediverse-futures/58">#<span>fediversity:fediverse-futures</span></a> e.g. the <a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353">“Community Has No Boundary”</a> paradigm, are part of furthering my ideas.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/13">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/13</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 31 Mar 2021 08:41:45 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1529-13</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529.rss">Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[how]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Link is dead to your article?</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/12">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529/12</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 30 Mar 2021 18:05:59 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1529-12</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/organizing-for-socialhub-community-empowerment/1529.rss">Organizing for SocialHub Community Empowerment</source>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
