<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</title>
    <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765</link>
    <description>![pexels-tim-douglas-6205480|690x459, 100%](upload://cF34PtaaFx9qzC7nor4f4NGw7L4.jpeg) 

I outlined the reasons in my into post https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hello-from-hospitality-exchange-community-devs/1764

The idea is drafted here: https://github.com/mariha/federated-trustroots/discussions/3

I&#39;d like to discuss the idea and possibly get some help in the direction where to go next. In particular, I am not sure if ActivityPub is what we should use to implement our federation. We are not social media platforms.

&lt;small&gt;_(Photo by **[Tim Douglas](https://www.pexels.com/@tim-douglas?utm_content=attributionCopyText&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_source=pexels)** from **[Pexels](https://www.pexels.com/photo/lady-standing-in-cafeteria-and-demonstrating-sign-open-6205480/?utm_content=attributionCopyText&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_source=pexels)**)_&lt;/small&gt;</description>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2021 08:25:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <category>Fediverse Futures</category>
    <atom:link href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
        <title>Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[hamishcampbell]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>How to move away from the churn.</p>
<p>"A river that needs crossing political and tech – On the political side, there is arrogance and ignorance, on the geek side there is naivety and over complexity</p>
<p>All code is ideology solidified into action – most contemporary code is capitalism, this is hardly a surprise if you think about this for a moment. Yes you can try and act on any ideology on top of this code but the outcome and assumptions are preprogramed… cant find any good links on this."</p>
<p>The gift economy goes way back to the beginning of human history.  The problem we face is that most of our <span class="hashtag">#geekproblem</span> crew code for capitalism even when they are agenst capitalism “naivety and over complexity”</p>
<p>This is a poverty that leads directly to the high churn in alt-tech. We have to stop adding more tech-shit to the pile, which means challenging our own assumptions aspersherly of people who come up with “<strong>new</strong>” ideas as 99% of the time these are <strong>not new</strong> and are just churning old failed models. Its beyond boring, and It’s going to lead to millions of us dying and billions of us being displaced in the next 100 years <span class="hashtag">#XR</span></p>
<p>We need to stop churning and start digging, compost the tech crap, plant seeds in the rich soil of this compost and grow a natural, humane, forest to live our lives in.</p>
<p>We need to do this today, next week, and all next year. Yes its work.</p>
<p>There are 20 years of thinking on this here <a href="http://hamishcampbell.com" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">http://hamishcampbell.com</a> with some paths out of this mess.</p>
<p>AP is a excellent way of meadating this issue, but most of the current codebases cannot be refacted with this at its core, the resources and skills are just not there.  Maybe something like <a href="https://github.com/forgefed/forgefed" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">forgefed</a>,  can bolted onto the existing codebase till the focus and energy can be found to do versions as a part of the fedivers.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/31">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/31</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2021 08:15:24 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1765-31</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765.rss">Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[mariha]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Sounds really really good, <a class="mention" href="/u/aschrijver">@aschrijver</a>! The whole project but in particular these points seems so relevant at the moment:</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="aschrijver" data-post="27" data-topic="1765">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/aschrijver/40/278_2.png" class="avatar"> aschrijver:</div>
<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>Service modules are dynamically pluggable at runtime.</li>
<li>Service modules are polyglot, can be written in many languages.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>when discussion here and so often with other projects goes into choice between two or more general purpose languages where both are good to do the job and it’s really a matter of individual preferences with a consequence of excluding from participation people with other then chosen tech stack experience. Did I already mention that I hate monoliths?</p>
<p>I’d be in, either for hospex (depends on others) or my tools and slow-travelers gear sharing projects.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/30">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/30</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2021 06:57:31 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1765-30</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765.rss">Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>The nice and very precious thing in the hospitality exchange and sharing communities is how their participants have experienced human nature. And the truly good parts of it, for that matter. I often say that we are increasingly living in a “distrust-first” society, and hypercapitalism breeds ever more of that distrust. The web with traditional social media (based on wrong incentives and business models) and flood of globalized news content (where negative news sells best) serves to tremendously accelerate the erosion of Trust.</p>
<p>Here I think that there is a big opportunity by bringing hospitality and sharing domains to the fediverse, as it will serve to further strenghten our culture. The platforms created here can be exemplars, where good vibes and proper human values rub off on fedizens, and help the virtuous cycle that uplifts culture ever further.  I just copied an article I wrote some time ago with more background on Trust vs. Distrust as I see it: <a href="https://community.humanetech.com/t/the-benefits-of-trusting-people-first/5226" class="inline-onebox">The Benefits of Trusting People First - Social - Humane Tech Community</a> (relates to how I see <a href="https://community.humanetech.com/t/what-makes-a-humane-technologist/5174/3">Humanity as the key factor to create humane technology</a>).</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/29">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/29</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2021 06:43:52 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1765-29</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765.rss">Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[mariha]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="hamishcampbell" data-post="24" data-topic="1765">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/hamishcampbell/40/284_2.png" class="avatar"> hamishcampbell:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I have been using these form the early days, spending meany years Hitchicking around the world “the hospitality” of strangers is the norm for this pre web world is something we need to think about when building new tech tools to model ancient human traditions (have a MA dissertation on hitchhiking some were)</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Nice! I used hitchhiking to get to highschool every morning 20 years ago, train schedules have never been my thing.</p>
<p>Same, was hosted so many times by strangers when traveling the world by bike. Central Asia/Middle East people are the most incredibly hospitable, it’s such a pity that after wars in Afghanistan and Iraq people in that whole region are seen as hostile. I haven’t thought about hospitality (or luck of it) as a pre/post web issue, for me it was more that in the countries where there is no good governance and infrastructure serving people needs, there is no other choice than to lean on other people and as a result there is much more solidarity among people and in general they support each other as much as they can. Need to think about tech role in it, very interesting thought with potentially far reaching consequences/opportunities. Probably worth it’s own conversation separate from this one.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/28">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/28</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2021 06:13:32 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1765-28</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765.rss">Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I have a project (mentioned above) I’m planning that has plugins, called Service Modules, as a central concept: <a href="https://codeberg.org/fullcircle/groundwork-matters">Groundwork</a>. The idea is to explore some interesting features:</p>
<ul>
<li>Service modules are dynamically pluggable at runtime.</li>
<li>Service modules are polyglot, can be written in many languages.</li>
<li>Service modules are ideal for providing domain-specific extensions (using Linked Data aspects of AP spec)</li>
<li>The <em>process</em> of developing interoperable code itself will be explored to ease app development.</li>
</ul>
<p>When launching this project I’d like to do that with a group of people similarly interested in having solid foundations of any federated app (auth/authz, user management, core federation mechanisms, etc.) - the common denominator - unified in an active and healthy FOSS project where many contributors expand and improve its base. Service modules that anyone creates on top of Groundwork will become available as library building block to other devs.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/27">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/27</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2021 05:29:26 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1765-27</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765.rss">Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[mariha]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Interesting, thanks for sharing!</p>
<p>WelcomeToMyGarden moves to TypeScript too.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>As an aside: On the point of local-only posts, is it not possible to leave that to each project?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Good point, thx!</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/26">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/26</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2021 05:18:14 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1765-26</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765.rss">Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[weex]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Following on the plugin idea from above, today I learned PeerTube supports plugins. It’s written in TypeScript which is similar to Trustroots’ Javascript so may be helpful as a reference implementation.</p>
<p>Here’s the doc on their plugins API: <a href="https://docs.joinpeertube.org/api-plugins" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">PeerTube Plugins API documentation</a></p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/25">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/25</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jun 2021 21:55:10 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1765-25</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765.rss">Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[hamishcampbell]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>The hospitality exchange WWW projects are good examples “native” <span class="hashtag">#openweb</span> projects.</p>
<p>I have been using these form the early days, spending meany years Hitchicking around the world “the hospitality” of strangers is the norm for this pre web world is something we need to think about when building new tech tools to model ancient human traditions (have a MA dissertation on hitchhiking some were)</p>
<p>Couch-surfing has a VERY interesting social tech history that we can learn from.</p>
<p>The newer networks have much to say about the <span class="hashtag">#geekproblem</span> and the strong tendency to self ghetto our own projects.</p>
<p>I think AP is a good way out of these two issues. NOTE we are fixing a social problem, good to notice we are not fixing a technical problem with AP here <img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/images/emoji/twitter/slight_smile.png?v=9" title=":slight_smile:" class="emoji" alt=":slight_smile:"></p>
<p><img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/original/2X/9/9a8a815173f2e5fa773a750135cb0f7b80e2c74d.png" alt="" data-base62-sha1="m38h8kWeoouzW19g0tXlRh18FGd" width="300" height="268"></p>
<p>If you are only thinking of fixing a tech problem with AP It’s likely not to have a good outcome.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/24">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/24</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jun 2021 09:11:20 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1765-24</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765.rss">Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[weex]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>This is such a fascinating effort and I’m glad to be here as it’s getting started, with so much feedback coming from the SocialHub community. A lot of links have been provided which should make for some good reading.</p>
<p>On the technical side of AP-enablement, I see tremendous value in two approaches.</p>
<ol>
<li>Delegating everything AP-specific to an external tool. GoFed is mentioned and ontologies which is frankly awesome. Potentially another hidden gem of the fediverse.</li>
<li>For any systems that wish to implement AP, to try to do so as a plugin. The nice thing about plugins is they let core developers  stay focused while instances can diversify and test out features more easily.</li>
</ol>
<p>As an aside: On the point of local-only posts, is it not possible to leave that to each project? Certainly a project can have some internal flags on their objects that say, “don’t send this over the AP wire,” so it’s never becomes an AP concern.</p>
<p>-David</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/23">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/23</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jun 2021 04:16:59 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1765-23</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765.rss">Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[mariha]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>We don’t have yet, it would be very nice though.</p>
<p>In FB groups for WS and some other travelers related and even the one that I moderate for Open alternative to WS people ask this questions every now and then. It’s rather annoying because it’s irrelevant to 99.9% of people (120K members for example) and the chances to find anyone, who lives in a bike-driving distance and is part of the group and is online and willing to host are pretty low I’d say.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/22">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/22</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 07:39:24 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1765-22</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765.rss">Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="mariha" data-post="19" data-topic="1765">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/mariha/40/1133_2.png" class="avatar"> mariha:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>Other interesting idea that we discussed with <a class="mention" href="/u/nicksellen">@nicksellen</a> elsewhere would be local only posting in geographical sense.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Do you already have similar functionality in current platform, that are based on geographic location? In ActivityStreams you have the <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/activitystreams-vocabulary/#dfn-place"><code>as:Place</code></a> object that allows specifying coordinates, usable maybe for filtering, and one might have some address-related fields attached to their <code>as:Person</code> or <code>as:Profile</code> (maybe using <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/vcard-rdf/#d4e1292"><code>vcard:Address</code></a> which is <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/activitystreams-core/#actors">recommended</a> for such extension). I don’t know if / how other federated apps have support similar information.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/21">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/21</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 05:14:13 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1765-21</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765.rss">Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[mariha]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p><a class="mention" href="/u/cjs">@cjs</a> thanks for writing this! I looked at your projects quickly and it seems very useful, and very well thought! Sorry for not answering earlier. I think I just need to understand the ActivityPub and ActivityStream themselves better before jumping into implementations, would be happy to chat with you later when I have some concrete questions, but go-fed and goToSocial are definitely worth considering, as a prototype and going forward.</p>
<p>Otherwise I considered either (a) <a href="https://github.com/immers-space/activitypub-express" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">ActivityPub-express</a>, a JavaScript implementation of AP as most of the platforms are written in JS and to start by federating two instances of Trustroots with each other or (b) to just organically add feature by feature:</p>
<ol>
<li>cross-platform-authentication,</li>
<li>import/export of data,</li>
<li>clustered users from the other platform visible on a map</li>
</ol>
<p>to the Trustroots - BeWelcome federation (what tech leads from both communities thought was worth doing anyways).</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/20">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/20</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 05:12:43 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1765-20</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765.rss">Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[mariha]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Local only (infrastructure-wise) posting is an interesting idea. I guess this way we could handle one-on-one message exchange within a local community as well as broader discussions in the community (afaik none of the hospex platforms has it right now, WS has external forum and TR has something similar for circles on the roadmap).</p>
<p>Other interesting idea that we discussed with <a class="mention" href="/u/nicksellen">@nicksellen</a> elsewhere would be local only posting in geographical sense. This would allow to make indirect hosting requests, something like:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I am arriving to the city and I broadcast a message: <em>Who can host me?</em><br>
Everyone in the area can see it and someone answers: <em>Come over to my home, we’ll be waiting this evening for you!</em><br>
without any upfront planning and commitments.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That would be great! There is a lot of uncertainty when traveling by bike, I hardly ever plan ahead of time, I think only when I have to make to the airport/train station to go back home and I consider it hard inconvenience. Out of 3 weeks trip half is pure pleasure of going anywhere I want and second half or at least 1/3 feels like rushing to get back at time.</p>
<p>Maybe that’s also why I hardly ever used WS as a guest. And most people who stayed with me were either starting or finishing their trips (my home was in a 1-2 hours ride from the airport in both places where I hosted)</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/19">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/19</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 04:37:52 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1765-19</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765.rss">Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p><a class="mention" href="/u/nicksellen">@nicksellen</a> it might be interesting to look into what <a class="mention" href="/u/darius">@darius</a> is doing with Friend Camp and Hometown, mentioned in <a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/standardizing-on-a-common-community-domain-as-ap-extension/1353/22" class="inline-onebox">Standardizing on a common Community domain as AP extension? - #22 by aschrijver</a></p>
<p>One thing that Hometown provides is <a href="https://github.com/hometown-fork/hometown/wiki/Local-only-posting">Local-Only Posting</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Mastodon right now is designed to get your messages out to the entire fediverse. This is great, but there is a huge need for more private communities. And in a federated network I think it makes the most sense for your home server to be that community (hence “Hometown”).</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Another new federated app under development, <a href="https://github.com/superseriousbusiness/gotosocial">GoToSocial</a> (based on <a class="hashtag" href="/c/software/go-fed/18">#<span>software:go-fed</span></a>) is having local-only posting on the wishlist. Interestingly GoToSocial is headless (no frontend, API-only) which lends itself well to tailor custom UI’s on top. The developer is in the <a href="https://matrix.to/#/#go-fed:feneas.org" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Go-Fed Matrix Chatroom</a>.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/18">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/18</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jun 2021 06:21:31 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1765-18</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765.rss">Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>3 posts were merged into an existing topic: <a href="/t/proposal-new-top-level-forum-section-for-domains/1797/13">Proposal: New top-level forum section for Domains</a></p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/15">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/15</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 13:41:30 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1765-15</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765.rss">Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[nicksellen]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>One topic I’m curious about is security/privacy and safety needs.</p>
<p>On the twitter-like part of the fediverse, the feeling seems you would only really trust it for semi-public discussion. The privacy controls are not intended to be hard safety barriers, but best-effort. At least from a user perspective it seems wise to treat it in this way, and use other platforms where secure communication is needed.</p>
<p>But for hospitality exchange this aspect is a bit different. A few thoughts:</p>
<ol>
<li>messages sent within a node should never have a way to leave that node</li>
<li>the safety-team on a given node might need access to the messages (hospex safety issues can be serious, involve the law, and be physical in nature)</li>
<li>in practise, the server admin will probably always be able to read all messages, and the users should hopefully feel comfortable to trust the node operators</li>
<li>malicious/hostile nodes should not be able to fake anything… personally I’m into allowlist-only federation to maximise trust, even if it means slower network growth, and nodes should be authenticated somehow</li>
</ol>
<p>(by node, I mean an instance of some hospex-like activitypub server)</p>
<p>I don’t really know how this stuff is handled in the fediverse, but I think the way it works out on mastodon et al. is not sufficient for hospex safety needs. In all cases, I believe the users really need to be able to give their <em>truly informed</em> consent regarding their own safety needs.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/17">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/17</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 10:34:59 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1765-17</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765.rss">Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[hamishcampbell]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>That sounds like a plan, that we need to bring to every problem <img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/images/emoji/twitter/slight_smile.png?v=9" title=":slight_smile:" class="emoji" alt=":slight_smile:"></p>
<p>Interesting to read <a href="https://www.bevolunteer.org/about-bevolunteer/history/" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://www.bevolunteer.org/about-bevolunteer/history/</a> this is a common history to alt-groups/projects in part it’s the <span class="hashtag">#geekproblem</span> in part something every left wing project has to work to overcome.</p>
<p>Thinking <a class="hashtag" href="/c/activitypub/5">#<span>activitypub</span></a> is a good fix as it mediates the “diversity of tactics” that is core to the spiky/fluff debate that I touch on here <a href="http://hamishcampbell.com/2021/05/28/we-live-in-a-world-full-of-monsters-dressed-in-fluffy-clothes/" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">http://hamishcampbell.com/2021/05/28/we-live-in-a-world-full-of-monsters-dressed-in-fluffy-clothes/</a></p>
<p>Worth a look at this one on the same subject <a href="http://hamishcampbell.com/2021/05/08/there-are-circals-in-protest-and-most-alternative-grassroots-movements/" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">http://hamishcampbell.com/2021/05/08/there-are-circals-in-protest-and-most-alternative-grassroots-movements/</a></p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/14">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/14</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 28 May 2021 11:09:15 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1765-14</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765.rss">Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[mariha]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Hi <a class="mention" href="/u/natacha">@natacha</a>!</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="natacha" data-post="12" data-topic="1765">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8491ac/40.png" class="avatar"> natacha:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>there are indeed more platforms then what I imagined, and none have a clear identity</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>BeVolunteer, an organization behind BeWelcome gives <a href="https://www.bevolunteer.org/about-bevolunteer/history/" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">an interesting historical context of how hospex landscape was (r)evolving</a>. Except a few (Servas, CouchSurfing, WarmShowers, WelcomeToMyGarden?), looks like new platforms were basically built because of disagreements of how the old ones were governed (Servas -&gt;? Hospitality Club, HC → BeWelcome, BW+CS → TrustRoots, CS → Couchers, WS → CyclePlanet), not because they had any distinctive identity aspects in mind.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="natacha" data-post="12" data-topic="1765">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/letter_avatar_proxy/v4/letter/n/8491ac/40.png" class="avatar"> natacha:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>federating would certainly help this bringing access to all information relieves the burden on any platform to fulfill all needs, I imagine it would diminish the competion between platforms.<br>
In consequence the different platforms could develop their specific identity , they would not fear of missing out since other needs would be covered by other platforms. One could then imagine platforms in other languages than English or dedicated to certain life choices (think of ecology or veganism).</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I hope this is the future we are heading to <img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/images/emoji/twitter/green_heart.png?v=9" title=":green_heart:" class="emoji" alt=":green_heart:">  Thanks for outlining it, very well said!</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/13">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/13</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 28 May 2021 10:01:36 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1765-13</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765.rss">Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[natacha]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Great that you come up here <a class="mention" href="/u/mariha">@mariha</a></p>
<p>From your links I realize there are indeed more platforms then what I imagined, and none have a clear identity so I can imagine the conversations between users idefinitely explaining why they prefer this or that platform.<br>
Indeed federating would certainly help this  bringing access to all information relieves the burden on any platform to fulfill all needs, I imagine it would diminish the competion between platforms.<br>
In consequence the different platforms could develop their specific identity , they would not fear of missing out since other needs would be covered by other platforms. One could then imagine platforms in other languages than English or dedicated to certain life choices (think of ecology or veganism).</p>
<p>I can imagine AP could help a lot regarding safety issues as users could share their profile accross different AP platforms therefore they become more accountable as they would not want to harm their reputation on other social media if they abuse a couch surfing situation.</p>
<aside class="quote no-group" data-username="mariha" data-post="6" data-topic="1765">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/mariha/40/1133_2.png" class="avatar"> mariha:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>my relationship with humanity is a difficult one. I’ve been focusing mostly on minimizing human impact on the rest of the nature most recently…</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Same thing here, relation to humanity and to humanism as a historical universalism is very difficult, but indeed this is a side note.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/12">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/12</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2021 16:55:43 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1765-12</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765.rss">Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[mariha]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>this is awesome, thanks <a class="mention" href="/u/aschrijver">@aschrijver</a>!</p>
<p>FYI, for instant messaging (coordination) we use:</p>
<ul>
<li>telegram: <a href="https://t.me/joinchat/bSRAq8EqivM4ZmZi" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Telegram: Join Group Chat</a>
</li>
<li>matrix: <a href="https://matrix.to/#/#hospex:matrix.org" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://matrix.to/#/#hospex:matrix.org</a>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Both rooms are mirrored.  You are more then welcome to join!</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/11">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/11</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2021 16:27:45 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1765-11</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765.rss">Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I create a Lemmy post related to this topic:</p>
<aside class="onebox allowlistedgeneric">
  <header class="source">
      <img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/optimized/1X/55b71e37b7983e7a2cc4bd3516669493a331dd03_2_500x500.webp" class="site-icon" width="500" height="500" srcset="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/optimized/1X/55b71e37b7983e7a2cc4bd3516669493a331dd03_2_500x500.webp, https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/optimized/1X/55b71e37b7983e7a2cc4bd3516669493a331dd03_2_750x750.webp 1.5x, https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/optimized/1X/55b71e37b7983e7a2cc4bd3516669493a331dd03_2_1000x1000.webp 2x" data-small-upload="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/optimized/1X/55b71e37b7983e7a2cc4bd3516669493a331dd03_2_10x10.png">
      <a href="https://lemmy.ml/post/66076" target="_blank" rel="noopener">lemmy.ml</a>
  </header>
  <article class="onebox-body">
    <div class="aspect-image" style="--aspect-ratio:690/459;"><img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/optimized/2X/5/58bdfe7e164ff3423e9b05d67096b537145cc382_2_690x459.jpeg" class="thumbnail" width="690" height="459" srcset="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/optimized/2X/5/58bdfe7e164ff3423e9b05d67096b537145cc382_2_690x459.jpeg, https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/original/2X/5/58bdfe7e164ff3423e9b05d67096b537145cc382.jpeg 1.5x, https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/original/2X/5/58bdfe7e164ff3423e9b05d67096b537145cc382.jpeg 2x" data-small-upload="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/optimized/2X/5/58bdfe7e164ff3423e9b05d67096b537145cc382_2_10x10.png"></div>

<h3><a href="https://lemmy.ml/post/66076" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Brainstorming for Hospitality Exchange Community on the Fediverse - Lemmy</a></h3>

<p>## Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse
…</p>


  </article>
  <div class="onebox-metadata">
    
    
  </div>
  <div style="clear: both"></div>
</aside>

<p>(<a class="mention" href="/u/mariha">@mariha</a> I added a picture to your first post, so that that displays when sharing the link… hope you don’t mind. If you do, then I’ll reverse)</p>
<p><strong>Update</strong>: Announced the Lemmy post in: <a href="https://mastodon.social/@humanetech/106289063521346724" class="inline-onebox">Humane Tech Now: "Since a number of great project in the Hospitalit…" - Mastodon</a></p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/10">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/10</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2021 07:43:06 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1765-10</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765.rss">Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[cjs]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="nicksellen" data-post="8" data-topic="1765">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/nicksellen/40/1175_2.png" class="avatar"> nicksellen:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I’m curious if there is any tooling for building activity pub ontologies, or whatever, to help express possibilities? Although I most highly value chat (voice/video) in addition to written “backup”, and more concrete exploration, shortly followed by working code</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Hey, sorry for being late to the thread. I’ll admit i didn’t have the chance to fully grok everything, but was connected to this particular bullet point from <a class="mention" href="/u/aschrijver">@aschrijver</a> . I hope my butt-in isn’t viewed as a derail.</p>
<p>There is the concrete option of using go-fed for this.  Go-fed is a suite of libraries that implements ActivityPub in a ontology-friendly way in Golang. &lt;/elevator pitch&gt;</p>
<p>What that means concretely is, one could:</p>
<ol>
<li>Write an OWL file of a new ActivityStreams based ontology (<a href="https://github.com/go-fed/activity/blob/e0de0863dcc1f6b7f42fdfaca8eec6aae001bb86/astool/forgefed.jsonld" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">ForgeFed ex</a>)</li>
<li>Use the go-fed <code>astool</code> to code generate the ActivityStreams implementation in golang</li>
<li>Use the <code>activity</code> or <code>apcore</code> libraries, or <a href="https://github.com/superseriousbusiness/gotosocial" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">GoToSocial</a> (I’m unaffiliated with that project) to rapidly prototype federating with that ontology via ActivityPub.</li>
</ol>
<p>I’m happy to dive into more detail, but just wanted to provide a concrete engineering option.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/9">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/9</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 22 May 2021 15:10:09 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1765-9</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765.rss">Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[nicksellen]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Thanks for <a class="mention" href="/u/mariha">@mariha</a> for coherently expressing this idea <img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/images/emoji/twitter/+1.png?v=9" title=":+1:" class="emoji" alt=":+1:"> (me having written some rambles to her about this idea too). And <a class="mention" href="/u/aschrijver">@aschrijver</a> and <a class="mention" href="/u/how">@how</a> for their validating enthusiasm <img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/images/emoji/twitter/grinning_face_with_smiling_eyes.png?v=9" title=":grinning_face_with_smiling_eyes:" class="emoji" alt=":grinning_face_with_smiling_eyes:">.</p>
<p>(I wrote about my background in <a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hello-from-a-community-software-dev/1791">my welcome post</a>).</p>
<p>I would like to support this initiative in a low-key kind of way, and have been chatting with <a class="mention" href="/u/mariha">@mariha</a> about it more informally too. Maybe if a few people wave around enough enthusiasm at some point some code arrives!</p>
<p>I’ll (ab)use the apparant tolerance for long wordy posts here, with my own long wordy post!</p>
<h2>
<a name="background-context-pondering-1" class="anchor" href="#background-context-pondering-1"></a>Background context pondering</h2>
<p>Governance has been a challenging and fascinating topic for me in all the grassroots community software projects I’ve worked on, and I’ve come to see the value of autonomous independent nodes, organising as they wish, but able to opt in (and out) of bigger wholes as desired.</p>
<p>In <a href="https://karrot.world" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://karrot.world</a> we approach this by each group on the platform being independent rather than by tech-based federation (as most of the groups would not be able to run an instance), but would potentially like to do that too later.</p>
<p>For me personally, the fediverse (by which I mostly mean mastodon) is really working (an “alternative” platform that is not entirely full of discussions about the platform itself <img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/images/emoji/twitter/wink.png?v=9" title=":wink:" class="emoji" alt=":wink:"> ) - and I love the properties of:</p>
<ul>
<li>can share software platform (e.g. mastodon) (as software is hard to develop)</li>
<li>can run instances independently with own governance mechanisms</li>
<li>can opt-in/out of federation with other instances</li>
<li>can interoperate with other software too (client+server)</li>
</ul>
<p>For hospex these things seem potentially very exciting .</p>
<ol>
<li>
<strong>the challenges of building software platforms</strong> - each new hospex community puts together an exciting new shiny tech platform, only to struggle some years later when it’s not cool tech any more, and the kind of work required has become a chore, leaving burnt out grumpy developers left and a pile of tech debt, … or commercial sell out of the community (who are the people that actually made the platform useful).</li>
<li>
<strong>critical mass issues</strong> - each hospex platform struggles to get enough people to join, and people get tired of having too many accounts on too many platforms that have too few other people on, federation can solve some of this</li>
<li>
<strong>community self-governance</strong> - with only a handful of platforms available to choose from, the governance of those is usually left to the usual type, who already hold some kind of power in society, building tools that allow groups of people to govern themselves addresses some of that</li>
</ol>
<p>Mastodon allows 100s (1000s?) of communities to exist independently yet speak to each other, I’d love to see 100s or 1000s of hospex platforms that can cater to peoples needs more independently, yet still allow cross-communication. Safety is huge topic in hospex as peoples physically safety is really on the line -  I’d love people to be able to choose their community of trust and federation options to meet their own definitions of safety.</p>
<p>There is still a very tricky centralization problem of the governance of the protocols and the development of each tech platform (developers not generally representing or understanding the needs of the communities very well), and for that I really enjoy things like the <a href="https://designjustice.org/read-the-principles" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">design justice principles</a>.</p>
<h2>
<a name="slightly-more-concrete-stuff-2" class="anchor" href="#slightly-more-concrete-stuff-2"></a>(Slightly) more concrete stuff</h2>
<p>I don’t know so much about activity pub, but the challenge to me seems how to express the activities of hospex in the language of activity pub / activity streams / etc. Most thoughts about how it should work will encode or embed various cultural/value assumptions, so seems wise to make these explicit.</p>
<p>A few examples:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<strong>hosting requests with arrival/departure dates</strong> (like airbnb), encodes a transactional consumerist perspective that communities that value connection might want to avoid</li>
<li>
<strong>trip itineraries</strong> (like couchsurfing) presupposes a planned kind of travel, whereas some communities would emphasis more spontaneous travel</li>
<li>
<strong>review/reference features</strong> (like many things) have their own complex set of dynamics… (reluctance to leave negative reviews)</li>
</ul>
<p>My personal hospex cultural preferences are for a kind of spontaneous / short term (0-24 hours) messaging-based  communication within a small community of very aligned people, for brief stays as I travel. Others seem to enjoy participating in an online “travel community” (tips and stuff) first, planning in advance, doing local cultural activities together… and other stuff I probably have no idea about.</p>
<p>I generally like the principle to make things (at least) one level more abstract than the underlying activity, to allow scope for appropriation of the tool for uses the designers did not know about (considering how much is possible with general chat/facebook groups alone, there is quite some scope there!).</p>
<p>I’m curious if there is any tooling for building activity pub ontologies, or whatever, to help express possibilities? Although I most highly value chat (voice/video) in addition to written “backup”, and more concrete exploration, shortly followed by working code <img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/images/emoji/twitter/computer.png?v=9" title=":computer:" class="emoji" alt=":computer:"></p>
<p>I’m not sure how much capacity I have to contribute to this practically though - I do quite enjoy the position of bridging abstract conceptual blahblahblah-ing into what might be needed for code to appear, which is sometimes more human, sometimes more technical.</p>
<p>Anyway that’s (more than) enough from me for now!</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/8">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/8</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 22 May 2021 12:38:16 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1765-8</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765.rss">Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <aside class="quote no-group" data-username="mariha" data-post="6" data-topic="1765">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/mariha/40/1133_2.png" class="avatar"> mariha:</div>
<blockquote>
<p>I’d ask guys to join SocialHub, we’ve been discussing in communities’ Slacks so far and missing a common discussion channel.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>I can strongly recommend using Matrix for chat environment. Slack is proprietary and not well-loved on the fediverse, and Matrix, decentralized, has many different chatrooms to join with topics related to federation. It is <em>the</em> ‘community extension’ for chat, imho.</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/7">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/7</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 14:04:58 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1765-7</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765.rss">Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</source>
      </item>
      <item>
        <title>Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[mariha]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Thanks, there is indeed a lot to read and learn! If only the day had more than 24h and my daughter slept most of that time <img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/images/emoji/twitter/wink.png?v=9" title=":wink:" class="emoji" alt=":wink:"></p>
<p><a href="https://community.humanetech.com/" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Human Tech Community</a> seems very interesting, even though my relationship with humanity is a difficult one. I’ve been focusing mostly on minimizing human impact on the rest of the nature most recently… but I do recognize that I can’t do it alone, after all.</p>
<p>I’d ask guys to join SocialHub, we’ve been discussing in communities’ Slacks so far and missing a common discussion channel.</p>
<p>[to be continued]</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/6">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765/6</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 11:57:23 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-1765-6</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/hospitality-exchange-community-considers-moving-to-the-fediverse/1765.rss">Hospitality exchange community considers moving to the fediverse ;)</source>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
