<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:discourse="http://www.discourse.org/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>ActivityPub - SocialHub</title>
    <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/c/activitypub/5</link>
    <description>Topics in the &#39;ActivityPub&#39; category Discuss the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/TR/activitypub/&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow noopener&quot;&gt;ActivityPub Recommendation&lt;/a&gt;, how to implement it, how to extend it. Home of the ActivityPub &lt;abbr title=&quot;Special Interest Group&quot;&gt;SIG&lt;/abbr&gt;.</description>
    
      <lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Jun 2021 14:39:45 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <atom:link href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/c/activitypub/5.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        <item>
          <title>How do I store activities and objects in an SQL database?</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[protheory8]]></dc:creator>
          <category>ActivityPub</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>There are two ways of doing that I can think about:</p>
<ol>
<li>Have a table for each activity type and store them there.</li>
<li>Have a one big <code>activities</code> table and store activities as JSON.</li>
</ol>
<p>Both of those options seem to have some serious disadvantages, the former one makes it difficult to get all activities from one actor in the chronological order and is not very scalable, the latter one doesn’t allow me to know what actor created the activity and other data without parsing JSON first.</p>
<p>Is there a better way than using those two option? Or is there a way to “fix” disadvantages that I mentioned?</p>
            <p><small>11 posts - 6 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/how-do-i-store-activities-and-objects-in-an-sql-database/1880">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/how-do-i-store-activities-and-objects-in-an-sql-database/1880</link>
          <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jun 2021 14:39:45 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-topic-1880</guid>
          <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/how-do-i-store-activities-and-objects-in-an-sql-database/1880.rss">How do I store activities and objects in an SQL database?</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Querying ActivityPub collections</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[grishka]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Server to Server</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>It’s me again with my efforts to extend collections. This is somewhat of a continuation of the discussion started in the <a class="hashtag" href="/tag/fep-400e">#<span>fep-400e</span></a> topic, but I feel like it warrants having a topic (and at some point a FEP) of its own.</p>
<p>Sometimes, it’s useful to have the ability to issue a single request to ask a remote instance “does this collection contain this object?” for an authoritative answer. This can be useful both for collection synchronization and to enforce bilateral relationships.</p>
<p>Example <span class="hashtag">#1</span>. There’s a wall post made by a user from instance A on the wall of a group on instance B (in accordance to my <a class="hashtag" href="/tag/fep-400e">#<span>fep-400e</span></a>). The user from instance A mentions a user from instance C in a reply to that post. The instance C fetches both the post and the reply to display them to its local user in a notification. <em>How does instance C verify that instance B has approved that parent post?</em></p>
<p>Example <span class="hashtag">#2</span>. A user from instance A and a user from instance B add each other as friends. They each have a “friends” collection that contains all such connections. Each sends an Add activity to their followers to keep friend lists in sync across instances. <em>How do recipients verify that this relationship was actually established on the other end if they only follow one of the users?</em></p>
<p>Currently, there’s no non-ugly way to do this — the only way you can get something out of a collection is by going through its pages. I’d like to discuss an easy way to query a collection, for example, using a well-defined query parameter or an HTTP header. You’d send a request to the collection ID URL, specifying the ID of the object you’re checking for, and the response would be one of three discernible states:</p>
<ul>
<li>The collection contains the object</li>
<li>The collection does not contain the object</li>
<li>Inconclusive — the server doesn’t support responding to these requests</li>
</ul>
            <p><small>19 posts - 6 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/querying-activitypub-collections/1866">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/querying-activitypub-collections/1866</link>
          <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jun 2021 02:18:13 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-topic-1866</guid>
          <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/querying-activitypub-collections/1866.rss">Querying ActivityPub collections</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Is json-ld compatibe to json-ld and what does activityPub understand with json-ld</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[naturzukunft]]></dc:creator>
          <category>ActivityPub</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>unfortunately i keep running into problems with parsing json-ld and the problem that others can’t interpret “my” json-ld. if i take “my” json-ld and paste it into <a href="https://json-ld.org/playground/" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">JSON-LD Playground</a> everything seems to be ok.<br>
So it looks like activityPub implementations speak a different json-ld. But I have the feeling that this json-ld is not specified.<br>
Am I the only one with this problem?<br>
I don’t want to write a json-ld parser/generator, but use libraries that exist and are provided in the RDF context. At the moment I rely on <a href="https://github.com/jsonld-java/jsonld-java" class="inline-onebox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">GitHub - jsonld-java/jsonld-java: JSON-LD implementation for Java</a> which is used in the context of rdf4j.</p>
<p>Framing does not seem to solve the problem either. At least it didn’t with Pleroma.</p>
            <p><small>3 posts - 2 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/is-json-ld-compatibe-to-json-ld-and-what-does-activitypub-understand-with-json-ld/1841">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/is-json-ld-compatibe-to-json-ld-and-what-does-activitypub-understand-with-json-ld/1841</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2021 19:25:17 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-topic-1841</guid>
          <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/is-json-ld-compatibe-to-json-ld-and-what-does-activitypub-understand-with-json-ld/1841.rss">Is json-ld compatibe to json-ld and what does activityPub understand with json-ld</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Minimum Viable ActivityPub Implementation</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[robertlong]]></dc:creator>
          <category>ActivityPub</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Hello, I’m working with the <a href="https://github.com/omigroup/OMI" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Open Metaverse Interoperability Group</a> (OMI) on figuring out how we might use ActivityPub to represent identity across multiple virtual worlds. Identity in this case being, at a minimum, display name and a url to the person’s avatar model.</p>
<p>Our definition of the metaverse aligns pretty closely with the fediverse. We believe that the metaverse is composed of a series of interconnected virtual worlds. No one organization can control the metaverse and anyone can create and host a connected virtual world. We’re focused on determining pieces that can be interoperable and this identity spec is the first of one of those possible points of interoperability.</p>
<p>I attended the W3C SocialWeb CG meeting this morning and brought up a concern from some people in our community. ActivityPub is a large spec, creating a full implementation is a lot of work. Right now we could get away with only requiring the data expressed in the Actor object and a small extension for the avatar model. Would encouraging members of our community to focus on supporting this small subset of the spec and allowing for servers that only implement the inbox/outbox and activities that modify the Actor object be in line with the views of this community? I’ve seen ActivityPub servers that only support certain subsets of the spec, but this is a very extreme case. Would we be creating a mess if we encouraged people to do this?</p>
<p>I don’t see how we can require users wishing to develop their own server implementations for our use case to implement the whole ActivityPub spec. Certainly, some will take the existing full implementations like Mastodon and extend it to support OMI’s specs. But people want to be able to implement the whole stack themselves. Removing requirements for additional complexity that we won’t use seems like a good way to get people on board with ActivityPub in our field.</p>
<p>Curious to hear your feedback, thank you!</p>
            <p><small>7 posts - 6 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/minimum-viable-activitypub-implementation/1790">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/minimum-viable-activitypub-implementation/1790</link>
          <pubDate>Fri, 21 May 2021 20:33:16 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-topic-1790</guid>
          <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/minimum-viable-activitypub-implementation/1790.rss">Minimum Viable ActivityPub Implementation</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>What does ActivityStreams Conformance mean?</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[aschrijver]]></dc:creator>
          <category>ActivityPub</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I see a lot of times the conformance of applications being brought up in topics, e.g:</p>
<aside class="quote group-redaktor.me" data-username="Sebastian" data-post="13" data-topic="1649">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/sebastian/40/38_2.png" class="avatar"><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/2021-05-01-fediverse-interest-group-meeting/1649/13">2021-05-01 Fediverse Interest Group Meeting</a>
</div>
<blockquote>
<p>The <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/activitypub/#specification-profiles">Conformance Section, 2.1</a> often says “the entirety” when it comes to being<br>
“ <em>ActivityPub conformant</em> ” …</p>
<ul>
<li>What is this theoretical entirety (which personally I strive for) and what does it mean in reality?</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>Indeed, what is “the entirety” and in that light what is Conformant?</p>
<aside class="quote group-redaktor.me" data-username="Sebastian" data-post="4" data-topic="624">
<div class="title">
<div class="quote-controls"></div>
<img alt="" width="20" height="20" src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/user_avatar/socialhub.activitypub.rocks/sebastian/40/38_2.png" class="avatar"><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/representing-images/624/4">Representing images</a>
</div>
<blockquote>
<p>About “subsets”, the <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/activitypub/#conformance">Conformance Section </a> made very clear what is ActivityPub conformant (“the entirety”) and what is not. So, we need to decide for ourselves if we “copy” short-message-box-logics or if we are ActivityPub conformant.</p>
</blockquote>
</aside>
<p>It seems to me that ‘conformance’ (as applying to AS vocab) has a <em>very broad</em> range:</p>
<ul>
<li>All properties are optional (including the <code>id</code> and <code>type</code> ).</li>
<li>Most properties are defined on the root <code>Object</code> type, applying to all sub-types.</li>
<li>Applications are free to define the semantics, e.g. choose to use <code>Document</code> for images.</li>
<li>And this applies to activities and social graphs too, e.g. my <code>Create{Note}</code> may have completely different meaning than yours.</li>
<li>Applications ignore objects that are not handled, or respond with an error.</li>
</ul>
<p>And still be fully conformant, or not? Posts seem to criticize apps for non-conformance (looks to me), but is that justified?<br>
Genuine question, because I don’t know if I understand the conformance part well enough.</p>
            <p><small>7 posts - 2 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/what-does-activitystreams-conformance-mean/1733">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/what-does-activitystreams-conformance-mean/1733</link>
          <pubDate>Wed, 12 May 2021 07:54:39 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-topic-1733</guid>
          <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/what-does-activitystreams-conformance-mean/1733.rss">What does ActivityStreams Conformance mean?</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Delivery</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[naturzukunft]]></dc:creator>
          <category>ActivityPub</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I’m a little bit confused by:</p>
<h3>
<a name="611-delivery-1" class="anchor" href="#611-delivery-1"></a>6.11 Delivery</h3>
<p>Federated servers <em>MUST</em> perform delivery on all Activities posted to the <strong>outbox</strong> according to <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/activitypub/#outbox-delivery" rel="noopener nofollow ugc"> outbox delivery</a>.</p>
<h3>
<a name="71-delivery-2" class="anchor" href="#71-delivery-2"></a>7.1 Delivery</h3>
<p><em>The following is required by federated servers communicating with other federated servers only.</em></p>
<p>I understand it like this:<br>
if only C2S is implemented, then there is no delivery between actors.<br>
And that sounds strange, doesn’t it? Why should there be no delivery without federation?</p>
            <p><small>6 posts - 2 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/delivery/1694">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/delivery/1694</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 03 May 2021 13:32:40 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-topic-1694</guid>
          <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/delivery/1694.rss">Delivery</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Content-addressing and URN resolution</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[rustra]]></dc:creator>
          <category>ActivityPub</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p><a href="https://gitlab.com/openengiadina/cpub/" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">CPub</a> as a general semantic ActivityPub server is using content-addressable RDF with <a href="https://inqlab.net/projects/eris/" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">ERIS</a>.</p>
<p>Object’s <code>id</code> should be de-referencable URI. There is no problem with loading a content using HTTP for URLs. However URNs require some another way for it.</p>
<p>Any existing ActivityPub client will be surprised to see something like this:</p>
<pre><code class="lang-auto">{
  "@context": "https://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#",
  "id": "urn:erisx2:AAADAF4BGFGNTYG65ZX3JW7A75VBCMRWN7B2WGIQ7PAQGBHOKYGMRESC2QZVSBDYW5P45R6FRRPBZYGZ5H6XTWSNR6HEXKOD735UG3B7IQ",
  "object": "urn:erisx2:AAAFVNIJDY22FZJZBL2LEWM7XR6P7GHUJ52NWP2E4EBR4O2LSBAOSW2YHA5DA5726X53KPABXYYO5ZRWLIOOLTEXNPE6FIBQW23LDEEMEM",
  "to": "local:rustra",
  "type": "Create"
}
</code></pre>
<p>For that reason we need a mechanism to resolve URNs to URLs / resources.</p>
<p>One of the proposal could be an agreement about exact endpoints similar to <code>/.well-known</code>. <a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2169" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">RFC2169</a> describes a trivial convention for using HTTP in URN resolution.</p>
<p>The general approach used to encode resolution service requests is quite simple:<br>
<code>GET /uri-res/&lt;service&gt;?&lt;uri&gt;  HTTP/1.0</code></p>
<p>Examples of services:</p>
<ul>
<li>N2L (URN to URL);</li>
<li>N2Ls (URN to URLs);</li>
<li>N2R (URN to Resource);</li>
<li>N2Rs (URN to Resources).</li>
</ul>
<p>Please share your opinion according to RFC2169 and ideas about any possible ways of URN resolution.</p>
            <p><small>9 posts - 5 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/content-addressing-and-urn-resolution/1674">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/content-addressing-and-urn-resolution/1674</link>
          <pubDate>Wed, 28 Apr 2021 18:28:22 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-topic-1674</guid>
          <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/content-addressing-and-urn-resolution/1674.rss">Content-addressing and URN resolution</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>S2S Create Activity</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[naturzukunft]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Server to Server</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Question to <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/activitypub/#create-activity-inbox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">S2S Create Activity</a></p>
<p>A client sends an activity to <a href="http://server_a.com/max" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">http://server_a.com/max</a>  .<br>
It gets the id: <a href="http://server_a.com/max/activity_0815" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">http://server_a.com/max/activity_0815</a>.<br>
The property <strong>as:to</strong> of <a href="http://server_a.com/max/activity_0815" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">http://server_a.com/max/activity_0815</a> is <a href="http://server_b.com/jane" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">http://server_b.com/jane</a>.</p>
<p>So <a href="http://server_a.com/max/outbox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">http://server_a.com/max/outbox</a> is something like that:</p>
<pre><code class="lang-auto">    {
    	  "@context": "[https://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams](https://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams)",
    	  "type": "OrderedCollection",
    	  "totalItems": 1,
    	  "orderedItems": [
    	    {
    	      "type": "Create",
    	      "id": "http://server_a.com/max/activity_0815"
    	      "name": "A Simple Activity"
    	      "to": "http://server_b.com/jane"
    	    }
    	  ]
    }	
</code></pre>
<p>Now <a href="http://server_a.com" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">http://server_a.com</a> has to deliver the activity to <a href="http://server_b.com/jane/inbox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">http://server_b.com/jane/inbox</a>:</p>
<pre><code class="lang-auto">{
	  "@context": "https://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams",
	  "type": "OrderedCollection",
	  "totalItems": 1,
	  "orderedItems": [
	    {
	      "type": "Create",
	      "id": "???????????????????"
	      "name": "A Simple Activity"
	      "to": "http://server_b.com/jane"
	    }
	  ]
}	
</code></pre>
<p>What is the <strong>id</strong> of the activity in <a href="http://server_b.com/jane/inbox" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">http://server_b.com/jane/inbox</a> ? Is it also <a href="http://server_a.com/max/activity_0815" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">http://server_a.com/max/activity_0815</a> because it’s a 100% copy (like a cache)<br>
Or does it gets a new Id <a href="http://server_b.com/max/activity_15" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">http://server_b.com/max/activity_15</a> ?</p>
            <p><small>21 posts - 3 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/s2s-create-activity/1647">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/s2s-create-activity/1647</link>
          <pubDate>Fri, 23 Apr 2021 16:54:46 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-topic-1647</guid>
          <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/s2s-create-activity/1647.rss">S2S Create Activity</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>The Block activity, how&#39;s that supposed to work?</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[grishka]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Server to Server</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I’m now at the point where I’m satisfied with my main features and almost ready to make my first release. Though in order to be a feasible fediverse server, I need to implement some sort of user blocking. So here goes.</p>
<p>The spec says that the Block activity is c2s only. Mastodon does send Block and Undo{Block} activities when you block and unblock a remote actor. What am I meant to do upon receipt of these activities? Remove all follow relationships and disallow the blocked actor any interactions with the originating actor and their content? Something else?</p>
<p>(I’m not really a fan of the whole “you see more if you log out” approach most social media implementations out there take, both centralized and not. I won’t be hiding anything publicly viewable if its author blocked you.)</p>
            <p><small>2 posts - 2 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/the-block-activity-hows-that-supposed-to-work/1572">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/the-block-activity-hows-that-supposed-to-work/1572</link>
          <pubDate>Sun, 11 Apr 2021 17:32:38 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-topic-1572</guid>
          <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/the-block-activity-hows-that-supposed-to-work/1572.rss">The Block activity, how&#39;s that supposed to work?</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Unfollow &amp; soft block in c2s - how to find the original Follow in order to undo / reject?</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[datatitian]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Client to Server</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>If I want to stop following someone, I believe I should send an Undo whose object is the Follow that I sent them in the past. Likewise, if I want to rescind permission to follow me, I should either Reject the Follow they originally sent me or perhaps Undo my Accept.</p>
<p>In all those cases, I need a reference to a potentially very old activity to be the object of my new activity. How can I find that within a client-to-server implementation?</p>
<p>The way <code>activitypub-express</code> works, I am actually looking up those old Follows whenever I’m fetching <code>Following</code> &amp; <code>Followers</code> collections, but spec says those endpoints return actors rather than activities, so the activity id I need does not reach the client.</p>
<p>The only other option I see that is strictly C2S spec would be to crawl my inbox or outbox page-by-page until I find the Follow I seek, but this could be a really long journey.</p>
<p>Am I missing something obvious? If I implement a custom unfollow endpoint, is my implementation no longer a true Client-to-Server AP implementation?</p>
            <p><small>5 posts - 3 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/unfollow-soft-block-in-c2s-how-to-find-the-original-follow-in-order-to-undo-reject/1484">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/unfollow-soft-block-in-c2s-how-to-find-the-original-follow-in-order-to-undo-reject/1484</link>
          <pubDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 21:30:40 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-topic-1484</guid>
          <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/unfollow-soft-block-in-c2s-how-to-find-the-original-follow-in-order-to-undo-reject/1484.rss">Unfollow &amp; soft block in c2s - how to find the original Follow in order to undo / reject?</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Create Activity (Object or Objects)</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[naturzukunft]]></dc:creator>
          <category>ActivityPub</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Hello all,<br>
I am wondering in relation to the ActivityPub specification specifically on C2s, but is more general.</p>
<p>When I create an activity, I actually create an object. And does the specification specify that this object should be exactly ONE object? Or can it be an object that links other objects?</p>
<p>I add an example (without surrounding activity!)</p>
<pre><code>@prefix output-file: &lt;http://www.w3.org/ns/person#&gt; .
@prefix schema: &lt;http://schema.org/&gt; .
@prefix foaf: &lt;http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/&gt; .
@prefix rdfs: &lt;http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#&gt; .
@prefix rdf: &lt;http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#&gt; .
@prefix SLR: &lt;http://xxxxxxxxxxx/ns/slr#&gt; .
@prefix as: &lt;http://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#&gt; .
@prefix xsd: &lt;http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#&gt; .

&lt;http://example.com/rootObjectToAdd&gt; a SLR:CreateActor;
  &lt;http://www.w3.org/2005/01/wf/flow#assignee&gt; &lt;http://localhost:8082/actors/4c207e4d-4b66-4a38-afa9-ec626a9f7a51&gt;;
  as:object &lt;http://example.com/actors/33333333&gt;;
  as:to &lt;http://localhost:8082/actors/4d055143-83c7-423e-bf5e-312e4443f467&gt; .

&lt;http://example.com/actors/33333333&gt; a as:Object;
  as:name "33333333" .
</code></pre>
<p>And how does the C2S create activity has to handle that? Just create the Object <code>http://example.com/rootObjectToAdd</code> and ignore <code>http://example.com/actors/33333333</code> or save both objects.</p>
<p>Fredy</p>
<p><img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/original/1X/0522712f5e0aa545dc4676d7bb711c915535df7e.png" alt="sample" data-base62-sha1="Jqb77R8XZdgzu9o9LDiG3kCqRg" width="261" height="361"></p>
            <p><small>6 posts - 2 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/create-activity-object-or-objects/1470">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/create-activity-object-or-objects/1470</link>
          <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2021 17:27:47 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-topic-1470</guid>
          <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/create-activity-object-or-objects/1470.rss">Create Activity (Object or Objects)</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>ActivityPub and Solid?</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[carian]]></dc:creator>
          <category>ActivityPub</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Hi. I recently looked at the Solid protocol, and I was wondering how they could coexist. I’ve seen forum posts about it, but never saw a concrete solution. So for example, a pure-Solid Mastodon would be like this: all instances are just web gateways and not servers, your username is your WebID instead of <span class="mention">@name</span>@instance. When you follow someone, you’re adding that person to a list of following in the Pod, and you also maintain a list of followers in your pod, as well as a list of posts. There would be only one feed, which is the feed of all the public posts in your Pod and all the Pods of your followers. This is fundamentally incompatible with ActivityPub today since a) identifiers would be WebIDs b) it wouldn’t exactly provide any extra functionality if integrated with the Fediverse.<br>
So, does anyone have a rough idea of how Solid and ActivityPub would work together? Could you give an example with Mastodon in the comments? Thanks.</p>
            <p><small>3 posts - 3 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/activitypub-and-solid/1466">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/activitypub-and-solid/1466</link>
          <pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2021 22:52:27 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-topic-1466</guid>
          <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/activitypub-and-solid/1466.rss">ActivityPub and Solid?</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Best (or Various) Way(s) to Check if Your Users Belong to Collections in Addressing?</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[WammKD]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Server to Server</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Simply, how might one handle checking (to process) addressing (<code>to</code>, <code>bto</code>, <code>cc</code>, <code>bcc</code>)?</p>
<p>Handling specific Object IDs or Public addressing is, obviously, easy but what about collections?</p>
<p>If the types of collections were limited (say to only followers and following), I could see an easy way to verify quickly but, as far as I understand the spec., any collection technically qualifies for what can be put in the addressing attributes.</p>
<p>And you can’t (easily) just grab the collection to check if any of your users reside in said collection since that collection could be paginated.</p>
<p>And large collections mean, potentially, churning through a ton of pages just to check if you see any of your users.</p>
<p>And there’s no provided way to request the remote instance to see if some user is a part of one of the instance’s collections so the searching, I would thing, ultimately resides with you.</p>
<p>So…how can you know whether an Object is addressed to any of your users with the expectation that said addressing could contain any collection, whatsoever?</p>
<p>I feel like I’m missing something obvious but I can’t seem to reason my way out of this conundrum.</p>
<p>Thanks for any help!</p>
            <p><small>4 posts - 2 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/best-or-various-way-s-to-check-if-your-users-belong-to-collections-in-addressing/1451">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/best-or-various-way-s-to-check-if-your-users-belong-to-collections-in-addressing/1451</link>
          <pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2021 17:06:22 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-topic-1451</guid>
          <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/best-or-various-way-s-to-check-if-your-users-belong-to-collections-in-addressing/1451.rss">Best (or Various) Way(s) to Check if Your Users Belong to Collections in Addressing?</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>FEP-400e: Publicly-appendable ActivityPub collections</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[grishka]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Fediverse Enhancement Proposals</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>The following FEP was proposed by <a class="mention" href="/u/grishka">@grishka</a> and received on 2021-02-12:</p>
<blockquote>
<h1><a href="https://git.activitypub.dev/ActivityPubDev/Fediverse-Enhancement-Proposals/src/commit/f94077e1514928c2d2ae79d86a5953c93874b73d/feps/fep-400e.md" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">FEP-400e: Publicly-appendable ActivityPub collections</a></h1>
<h2>Summary</h2>
<p>In social media, it’s a frequent pattern when there’s a collection owned by someone that other people can contribute to. Examples include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Walls where others can post</li>
<li>Forums as well as topics within</li>
<li>Photo albums in groups where group members can add photos</li>
</ul>
<p>Currently, there is no generic way to signify that an object was created as part of a collection and should only be considered in its context.</p>
<p>This proposal describes how ActivityPub servers and clients could specify collections to which objects created by their actors belong.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>We ask all ActivityPub developers to which this is relevant to carefully read the specification text and provide your feedback!</p>
            <p><small>18 posts - 3 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-400e-publicly-appendable-activitypub-collections/1438">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-400e-publicly-appendable-activitypub-collections/1438</link>
          <pubDate>Sat, 13 Feb 2021 15:08:02 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-topic-1438</guid>
          <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/fep-400e-publicly-appendable-activitypub-collections/1438.rss">FEP-400e: Publicly-appendable ActivityPub collections</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>ActivityPub C2S and CORS headers</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[kaniini]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Client to Server</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I am working on <a href="https://github.com/kaniini/jejune" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Jejune</a>, a personal ActivityPub server that has a featureset similar to Tumblr.</p>
<p>As part of this, <a href="https://github.com/kaniini/jejune-client" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Jejune Client</a> is an ActivityPub C2S client which runs in the browser to allow the user to manage her instance, read posts in her inbox and publish new posts to her friends.</p>
<p>As part of this process, I have discovered that many AP servers do not consistently provide CORS headers when fetching ActivityPub objects.</p>
<p>For example, SocialHome does not provide any CORS headers when fetching ActivityStreams objects, which means that posts from SocialHome users do not appear in a correctly attributed way (as we can’t fetch the attributed actor), and Mastodon only provides CORS headers when fetching actors, but not posts and activities, which causes problems with building functionality where a user may want to examine a thread.</p>
<p>These can be mitigated by proxying the requests through the local AP server, but I don’t think this is a good design – if I can fetch something with curl on the commandline, I believe I should be able to fetch the same content with a browser.</p>
<p>So, I think it may be good to document the use of CORS headers when interacting with ActivityStreams/ActivityPub objects and endpoints over HTTP.  What do people think?</p>
            <p><small>5 posts - 4 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/activitypub-c2s-and-cors-headers/1418">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/activitypub-c2s-and-cors-headers/1418</link>
          <pubDate>Sat, 06 Feb 2021 22:22:09 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-topic-1418</guid>
          <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/activitypub-c2s-and-cors-headers/1418.rss">ActivityPub C2S and CORS headers</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Vocabulary question: as:id -&gt; DeprecatedProperty</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[naturzukunft]]></dc:creator>
          <category>ActivityPub</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Hi there,<br>
in <a href="https://github.com/w3c/activitystreams/blob/54a6723ed1c8b95a12997b4e73100308e267fc8f/vocabulary/activitystreams2.owl" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://github.com/w3c/activitystreams/blob/54a6723ed1c8b95a12997b4e73100308e267fc8f/vocabulary/activitystreams2.owl</a><br>
the as:id definition is “owl:DeprecatedProperty”.<br>
That surprises me a little! Does anybody know the reason ?</p>
<pre><code>as:id a owl:DatatypeProperty ,
        owl:FunctionalProperty,
        owl:DeprecatedProperty ;
  rdfs:label "id"@en ;
  rdfs:range xsd:anyURI ;
  rdfs:domain [
    a owl:Class ;
    owl:unionOf (as:Link as:Object)
  ] .</code></pre>
            <p><small>2 posts - 2 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/vocabulary-question-as-id-deprecatedproperty/1416">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/vocabulary-question-as-id-deprecatedproperty/1416</link>
          <pubDate>Sat, 06 Feb 2021 18:56:18 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-topic-1416</guid>
          <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/vocabulary-question-as-id-deprecatedproperty/1416.rss">Vocabulary question: as:id -&gt; DeprecatedProperty</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>ActivityStreams protocol spec question</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[mathew_001]]></dc:creator>
          <category>ActivityPub</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I am confused about something in the activity streams specification<br>
in the Activity Vocabulary doc a <em>Collection.Current</em> can be a <em>PagedCollection</em> <strong>or</strong> a <em>Link</em><br>
<a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/activitystreams-vocabulary/#dfn-current" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Activity Vocabulary (w3.org)</a></p>
<p>However their example 75 (at link above) current has the “summary” element which is not avalable to something of         type “Link” (see below).  Am I misunderstanding that current is not an Object or Link but Object <strong>AND</strong> Link?  What do other implementations do with summary in this case?</p>
<pre><code>     "current": {
        "type": "Link",
        "summary": "Most Recent Items",
        "href": "http://example.org/collection"
      },</code></pre>
            <p><small>4 posts - 3 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/activitystreams-protocol-spec-question/1401">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/activitystreams-protocol-spec-question/1401</link>
          <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2021 21:16:48 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-topic-1401</guid>
          <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/activitystreams-protocol-spec-question/1401.rss">ActivityStreams protocol spec question</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Create Activity with graph</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[naturzukunft]]></dc:creator>
          <category>ActivityPub</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Hi there,<br>
if a client stores an “activity” with an “object”, that references “anotherObject”,<br>
should the activity pub implementation then also save “anotherObject” or validate, that “anotherObject” is existend?<br>
Or just store the IRI/URL?</p>
<p>Means:<br>
Is a createActivity limited to one object or is it also for graphs/trees.<br>
Or should there be a create activity for each object of the graph/tree?</p>
<p>activity.object -&gt; someObject ;<br>
someObject.anotherObject -&gt; anotherObject;</p>
<p>Thanks Fredy</p>
            <p><small>4 posts - 2 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/create-activity-with-graph/1336">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/create-activity-with-graph/1336</link>
          <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2021 08:40:34 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-topic-1336</guid>
          <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/create-activity-with-graph/1336.rss">Create Activity with graph</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>ActivityPub - How to start?</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[fervi]]></dc:creator>
          <category>ActivityPub</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Hello, I’ve been working on a project for a while and wanted to add my own protocol to it. However, I decided that I would use ActivityPub if there is an option. However, this protocol seems to be terribly overkill. Nevertheless, I would like to understand it.</p>
<p>The project is in PHP, so I initially use ActivityPHP.</p>
<p>I would like to know what exactly I need to do to make the initial server.</p>
<p>Unfortunately in my opinion the documentation is a bit … difficult?</p>
<hr>
<p>So each user is an actor (actor can also be a bot, but whatever). What important parameters do you think it must have? Is it possible to add public keys in the actor field?</p>
<p>Additionally what text mode do I need to choose for articles. For now I’ve set “article” because it seems to have all the fields. Just wondering how to add the tags (they should be an array, but it doesn’t work very well for me.</p>
<p>How exactly is the server supposed to work? Obviously ActivityPHP has an option to create a server (how?), but I haven’t found information on what the server should have in order to be received from outside.</p>
<p>It would be nice if there were people (Discord, Matrix?) who would be willing to help me understand ActivityPub and at the same time know how it works (so I can ask questions and learn).</p>
            <p><small>4 posts - 2 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/activitypub-how-to-start/1330">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/activitypub-how-to-start/1330</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2021 20:38:46 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-topic-1330</guid>
          <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/activitypub-how-to-start/1330.rss">ActivityPub - How to start?</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Using types from other namespaces as as:object</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[naturzukunft]]></dc:creator>
          <category>ActivityPub</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Hi there,<br>
i’m new in RDFS, AS, AP, etc. And have a problem understanding the reuse of schemas.<br>
If i want to add a as:object to a as:Activity that’s type is not from the AS namespace, how do i do that?</p>
<pre><code>{
  "@context": "https://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams",
  "summary": "Martin created an email",
  "type": "Create",
  "actor": "http://www.test.example/martin",
  "object" : {
   "id": "http://www.test.example/mail/abc123/xyz",
   "type": "Object",
   "url": "http://www.test.example/mail/abc123/xyz"
  }
}
</code></pre>
<p>thr url points to a schema:EmailMessage.<br>
Or do i have to create a new owl:Class that extends schema:EmailMessage and has a “id” and a “type” property?</p>
<p>Thanks Fredy</p>
            <p><small>5 posts - 2 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/using-types-from-other-namespaces-as-as-object/1326">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/using-types-from-other-namespaces-as-as-object/1326</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2021 12:41:32 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-topic-1326</guid>
          <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/using-types-from-other-namespaces-as-as-object/1326.rss">Using types from other namespaces as as:object</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Unit-Testing Federations (or networks in general)</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[calummackervoy]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Server to Server</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Hello !</p>
<p>I’ve been writing unit tests in Django and we rely quite heavily on ActivityStreams messages being sent between servers in the federation. The first solution I wrote turned out to have an infinite loop in it, because two servers were reacting to each other’s messages by sending another one <img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/images/emoji/twitter/grin.png?v=9" title=":grin:" class="emoji" alt=":grin:"> infinite oneupmanship</p>
<p>if I had a magic wand I’d love to be able to write unit tests in which I had multiple servers. I haven’t been able to find anything like this for Django specifically, but does anyone know of any examples in other frameworks, have any insight into the topic or any interesting reading ?</p>
            <p><small>1 post - 1 participant</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/unit-testing-federations-or-networks-in-general/1296">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/unit-testing-federations-or-networks-in-general/1296</link>
          <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 08:31:41 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-topic-1296</guid>
          <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/unit-testing-federations-or-networks-in-general/1296.rss">Unit-Testing Federations (or networks in general)</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Activity specification turtle documents</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[naturzukunft]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Client to Server</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>I found this one: (not easy to find, ask me why!)</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams-owl" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams-owl</a></li>
</ul>
<p>But i miss the turtle file for <a href="https://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#activitypub" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">https://www.w3.org/ns/activitystreams#activitypub</a></p>
<p>Any idea ?<br>
Thanks</p>
            <p><small>4 posts - 3 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/activity-specification-turtle-documents/1293">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/activity-specification-turtle-documents/1293</link>
          <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 14:46:14 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-topic-1293</guid>
          <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/activity-specification-turtle-documents/1293.rss">Activity specification turtle documents</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Notify an actor about new activities by email</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[naturzukunft]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Client to Server</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Hi there, is there a sample, etc. how to handle email notification about new activities?</p>
            <p><small>2 posts - 2 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/notify-an-actor-about-new-activities-by-email/1272">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/notify-an-actor-about-new-activities-by-email/1272</link>
          <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jan 2021 09:09:21 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-topic-1272</guid>
          <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/notify-an-actor-about-new-activities-by-email/1272.rss">Notify an actor about new activities by email</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>Inbox: mark as read</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[naturzukunft]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Client to Server</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Hi all, is there a recommendation how to mark a activity as read ?</p>
            <p><small>3 posts - 2 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/inbox-mark-as-read/1271">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/inbox-mark-as-read/1271</link>
          <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jan 2021 09:06:40 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-topic-1271</guid>
          <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/inbox-mark-as-read/1271.rss">Inbox: mark as read</source>
        </item>
        <item>
          <title>How to stop incoming updates?</title>
          <dc:creator><![CDATA[aveltens]]></dc:creator>
          <category>Server to Server</category>
          <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Since I experimented with ActivityPub my server keeps getting updates about user deletions from other instances like mastodon.social</p>
<p>How can I stop those?</p>
            <p><small>3 posts - 2 participants</small></p>
            <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/how-to-stop-incoming-updates/1266">Read full topic</a></p>
          ]]></description>
          <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/how-to-stop-incoming-updates/1266</link>
          <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jan 2021 08:56:47 +0000</pubDate>
          <discourse:topicPinned>No</discourse:topicPinned>
          <discourse:topicClosed>No</discourse:topicClosed>
          <discourse:topicArchived>No</discourse:topicArchived>
          <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-topic-1266</guid>
          <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/how-to-stop-incoming-updates/1266.rss">How to stop incoming updates?</source>
        </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
