<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>Help with Relays on Pleroma please</title>
    <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/help-with-relays-on-pleroma-please/731</link>
    <description>Hello, I&#39;m new here and need help.  lol.  I am totally new to ActivityPub but I set up a Pleroma server on Digital Ocean a few days ago.  That generally went smoothly.  I set up a few relays and I&#39;m showing lots of activity from those relays.

Anyway, I have relay regret with one instance and I&#39;m trying to delete them.  When I try to delete the relay in the UI of Pleroma-FE, I get this (below). 

![image|555x73](upload://kcavtucHudXoOMVDXsLhaDO5ta4.png) 

So I googled and found I can use &quot;pleroma_ctl relay unfollow&quot; and that pukes with a &quot;not found&quot; error on line 159. So I edit pleroma_ctl and find on line 159 it&#39;s looking for a binary called pleroma and I can&#39;t find that anywhere. Tons of directories named pleroma but no binaries (that I saw).

Is it really this hard to delete a relay?</description>
    
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 16:41:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <category>Software</category>
    <atom:link href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/help-with-relays-on-pleroma-please/731.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
        <title>Help with Relays on Pleroma please</title>
        <dc:creator><![CDATA[regnatarajan]]></dc:creator>
        <description><![CDATA[
            <p>Hello, I’m new here and need help.  lol.  I am totally new to ActivityPub but I set up a Pleroma server on Digital Ocean a few days ago.  That generally went smoothly.  I set up a few relays and I’m showing lots of activity from those relays.</p>
<p>Anyway, I have relay regret with one instance and I’m trying to delete them.  When I try to delete the relay in the UI of Pleroma-FE, I get this (below).</p>
<p><img src="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/uploads/default/original/1X/8d8ba4adb1bc58dff0cf8d4da02cbe86188ba3fc.png" alt="image" data-base62-sha1="kcavtucHudXoOMVDXsLhaDO5ta4" width="555" height="73"></p>
<p>So I googled and found I can use “pleroma_ctl relay unfollow” and that pukes with a “not found” error on line 159. So I edit pleroma_ctl and find on line 159 it’s looking for a binary called pleroma and I can’t find that anywhere. Tons of directories named pleroma but no binaries (that I saw).</p>
<p>Is it really this hard to delete a relay?</p>
          <p><a href="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/help-with-relays-on-pleroma-please/731/1">Read full topic</a></p>
        ]]></description>
        <link>https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/help-with-relays-on-pleroma-please/731/1</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 16:41:12 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid isPermaLink="false">socialhub.activitypub.rocks-post-731-1</guid>
        <source url="https://socialhub.activitypub.rocks/t/help-with-relays-on-pleroma-please/731.rss">Help with Relays on Pleroma please</source>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
